Blind Sight by Peter Watts, narrated by Zachary Reid. For Lisa, if we're not in
pain, we're not alive. This is what fascinates me most in existence, the
peculiar necessity of imagining what is, in fact, real. Philip Gurovich, you will
die like a dog for no good reason, Ernest Hemingway. Prologue. Try to touch
the past. Try to deal with the past. It's not real. It's just a dream. Ted Bundy.
It didn't start out here. Not with the scramblers or roar shock, not with Big
Ban or Theesius or the vampires. Most people would say it started with the
fireflies, but they'd be wrong. It ended with all those things. For me, it began
with Robert Pagliano. At the age of eight, he was my best and only friend. We were
fellow outcasts bound by complimentary misfortune. Mine was developmental. His
was genetic, an uncontrolled genotype that left him predisposed to
nearsightedness, acne, and, as it later turned out, a susceptibility to narcotics.
His parents had never had him optimized. Those few twin-sen relics who still
believed in God also held that one shouldn't try to improve upon his
handiwork. So although both of us could have been repaired, only one of us had
been. I arrived at the playground to find Pagliano at the center of attention for
some half-dozen kids, those lucky few in front punching him in the head, the
others making do with taunts of mongrel and Polly awaiting their turn. I watched
him raise his arms, almost hesitantly, to ward off the worst the blows. I could
see into his head better than I could see into my own. He was scared that his
attackers might think those hands were coming up to hit back, that they'd read
it as an act of defiance and hurt back even more. Even then, at the tender age of
eight and with half my mind gone, I was becoming a superlative observer. But I
didn't know what to do. I hadn't seen much of Pagliano lately. I was pretty sure
he'd been avoiding me. Still, when you're best friends in trouble, you help out,
right? Even if the odds are impossible, and how many eight-year-olds would go up
against six bigger kids for a sandbox buddy, at least you call for backup,
flag a sentry, something. I just stood there. I didn't even especially want to
help him. That didn't make sense. Even if he hadn't been my best friend, I should
have at least empathized. I'd suffered less than Pag in the way of overt
violence. My seizures tended to keep the other kids at a distance, scared them
even as they incapacitated me. Still, I was no stranger to the taunts and insults,
or the foot that appears from nowhere to trip you, on-route from A to B. I knew how
that felt, or I had once. But that part of me even cut out along with the bad
wiring. I was still working up the algorithms to get it back, still learning
by observation. Pag animals always tear apart the weaklings in their midst. Every
child knows that much instinctively. Maybe I should just let that process
unfold. Maybe I shouldn't try to mess with nature. Then again, Pag's parents
hadn't messed with nature, and look what it got them. A son curled up in the dirt
while a bunch of engineered superboys kicked in his ribs. In the end, propaganda
work were empathy failed. Back then, I didn't so much as think as observe. Didn't
adduce so much as remember. And what I remembered was a thousand inspirational
stories, louding anyone who ever stuck up for the underdog. So I picked up a rock
the size of my fist, and hit two of Pag's assailants across the backs of their
heads before anyone even knew I was in the game. A third, turning to face the new
threat, took a blow to the face that audibly crunched the bones of his cheek.
I remember wondering why I didn't take any satisfaction from that sound, and why
it meant nothing beyond the fact that I had one less opponent to worry about.
The rest of them ran at the sight of blood. One of the braver promised me I
was dead, shouting, fucking zombie over his shoulder as he disappeared around the
corner. Three decades it took to see the irony in that remark. Two of the enemy
twitched at my feet. I kicked one in the head until it stopped moving, turned to
the other. Something grabbed my arm and I swung without thinking, without looking
until Pag yelped and ducked out of reach. Oh, I said. Sorry. One thing lay
motionless. The other moaned and held its head and curled up in a ball. Oh shit,
Pag panted. Blood cursed unheeded from his nose and splattered down his shirt. His
cheek was turning blue and yellow. Oh shit, oh shit, oh shit, oh shit. I thought
of something to say. You alright? Oh shit, you, I mean you never... he wiped his mouth.
Blood smeared the back of his hand. Oh man, are we in trouble? They started it. Yeah,
but you, I mean look at them. The moaning thing was crawling away on all fours. I
wondered how long it would be before it found reinforcements. I wondered if I
should kill it before then. You'd have never done that before, Pag said. Before
the operation, he meant. I actually did feel something then. Faint, distant, but
unmistakable. I felt angry. They started Pag backed away, eyes wide. What are you
doing? Put that down! I raised my fists. I didn't remember doing that. I hand
clenched them. It took a while. It took a while. I had to look at my hands very
hard for a long, long time. The rock dropped to the ground, bloodstained and
glistening. I was trying to help. I didn't understand why he couldn't see that.
You're not the same, Pag said from a safe distance. You're not even
serious anymore. I am too. Don't be a fuckwad. They cut out your brain. Only half
for the ep- I know for the epilepsy. You think I don't know? But you were in that
half or like part of you was. He struggled with the words, with the concept
behind them. And now you're different. It's like your mom and dad murdered you.
My mom and dad, I said, suddenly quiet. Saved my life. I would have died.
I think you did die, said my best and only friend. I think Ciri died. They scooped
him out and threw him away and you've got some whole other kid that just just
grew back out of what was left. You're not the same. Ever since, you're not the
same. I still don't know if Pag really knew what he was saying. Maybe his mother
just pulled the plug in whatever game he'd been wired into for the previous 18
hours, forced him outside for some fresh air. Maybe after fighting pod people in
game space, he couldn't help but see them everywhere. Maybe. But you could make a
case for what he said. I remember Helen telling me, and telling me, how difficult
it was to adjust. Like you had a whole new personality, she said. And why not?
There's a reason they call it radical, hemiospherectomy. Half the brain thrown
out with yesterday's krill, the remaining half press ganged into double duty. Think
of all the rewiring that one lonely hemisphere must have struggled with as
it tried to take up the slack. It turned out okay, obviously. The brain's a very
flexible piece of meat. It took some doing, but it adapted. I adapted. Still, think
of all that must have been squeezed out, deformed, reshaped by the time the
renovations are through. You could argue that I'm a different person than the one
who used to occupy this body. The grown-up showed up eventually, of course.
Medicine was besowed, ambulance is called. Parents were outraged, diplomatic
volleys exchanged, but it's tough to draw up neighborhood outrage on behalf of
your injured baby when playground surveillance in three angles shows
little darling and five of his buddies kicking in the ribs of a disabled boy.
My mother, for her part, recycled the usual complaints about problem children
and absentee fathers. Dad was off again in some other hemisphere, but the dust
settled pretty quickly. Pag and I even stayed friends after the short hiatus
that reminded us both of the limited social prospects open to schoolyard
rejects who don't stick together. So I survived that and a million other
childhood experiences. I grew up and got along. I learned to fit in. I observed,
recorded, derived the algorithms and mimicked appropriate behaviors. Not
much of it was, heartfelt, I guess the word is. I had friends and enemies like
everyone else. I chose them by running through checklists of behaviors and
circumstances compiled from years of observation. I may have grown up distant,
but I grew up objective and I have Robert Pagliano to thank for that. His
seminal observation was set everything in motion. It led me into synthesis,
faded me to our disastrous encounter with the scramblers, spared me the worst
fate of falling earth or the better one I suppose depending on your point of
view point of view matters. I see that now blind talking to myself trapped in a
coffin falling past the edge of the solar system. I see it for the first time
since some beaten bloody friend on a childhood battlefield convinced me to
throw my own point of view away. He may have been wrong. I may have been, but
that that distance, a chronic sense of being an alien among your own kind. It's
not entirely a bad thing. It came in especially handy when the real aliens
came calling.
Theseus. Blood makes noise. Suzanne Vega. Imagine you are Siri Keaton. You
awaken an agony of resurrection grasping after a record shattering bout of sleep
and a shrapnel. You can feel your blood and syrupy with dobutamine and
Lone and Kephalin forcing its way through artery shriveled by months on standby.
The body inflates in painful increments. Blood vessels dilate. Flesh peels apart
from flesh. Ribs crack in your ears with sudden, unaccustomed flexion. Your joints
have seized up through disuse. You're a stick man frozen in some perverse rear
vitae. You'd scream if you had the breath. Vampires did this all the time, you
remember. It was normal for them. It was their own unique take on resource
conservation. They could have taught your kind a few things about restraint if that
absurd aversion to right angles hadn't done them in at the dawn of civilization.
Maybe they still can. They're back now after all, raised from the grave with the
voodoo of paleogenetics, stitched together from junk genes and fossil
marrow, steeped in the blood of sociopaths and high functioning autistics.
One of them commands this very mission. A handful of his genes live on in your
own body so it too can rise from the dead here at the edge of interstellar
space. Nobody gets past Jupiter without becoming part vampire.
The pain begins just slightly to recede. You fire up your inlays and access
your own vitals. It'll be long minutes before your body responds fully to
motor commands, hours before it stops hurting. The pain is an unavoidable
side effect. That's just what happens when you splice vampire subroutines into
human code. You asked about pain killers once, but nerve blocks of any kind
compromise metabolic reactivation. Suck it up, soldier. You wonder if this was how
it felt for Chelsea before the end. But that evokes a whole other kind of pain,
so you block it out and concentrate on the life pushing its way back into your
extremities. Suffering in silence, you check the logs for fresh telemetry. You
think that can't be right? Because if it is, you're in the wrong part of the
universe. You're not in the Kuiper Belt where you belong. You're high above the
ecliptic and deep into the oar. The realm of long period comets that only grace
the sun every million years or so. You've gone interstellar, which means you
bring up the system clock. You've been undead for 1800 days. You've overslept by
almost five years. Lid on your coffin slides away. Your own cadaverous body
reflects from the mirrored bulkhead opposite, a desiccated lungfish waiting
for the rains. Ladders of isotonic saline cling to its limbs like
engorged anti-parasites, like the opposite of leeches. You remember the
needles going in just before you shut down way back when your veins were more
than dry twisted filaments of beef jerky. Spindle's reflection stares back from
his own pod to your immediate right. His face is as bloodless and skeletal as
yours. His wide, sunken eyes jiggle in their sockets as he reacquires his own
links. Sensory interface is so massive that your own off-the-shelf inlay is
amount to shadow puppetry in comparison. You hear coughing and the rustling of
limbs just past line of sight catch glimpses of reflected motion where the
others stir at the edge of vision. What? Your voice is barely more than a
horse whisper. How? Spindle works his jaw. Bone cracks audibly.
Suckered! He hisses. You haven't even met the aliens yet and they're already
running rings around you. So we dragged ourselves back from the dead. Five
part-time cadavers, naked, emaciated, barely able to move even in zero G. We
merged them our coffins like premature moths from their cocoons. Still half
grub. We were alone and off course and utterly helpless and it took a conscious
effort to remember they would never have risked our lives if we hadn't been
essential. Morning, Commissar! Isaac Spindle reached one trembling in since
eight hand for the feedback gloves at the base of his pod. Just past him, Susan
James was curled into a loose a loose fetal ball murmuring to
herself. Only Amanda Bates, half dressed and cycling through a sequence of
bone cracking isometrics possessed anything approaching mobility. Every
now and then she tried bouncing a rubber ball off the bulkhead but not even
she was up to catching it on the rebound yet. The journey had melted us down to a
common archetype. James's round cheeks and hips, Spindle's high forehead and
lumpy, lanky chasses, even the enhanced carb platinum brick shithouse that Bates
used for a body all had shriveled to the same desiccated collection of sticks and
bones. Even our hair seemed to have become strangely discolored during the
voyage although I knew that was impossible. More likely it was just
filtering the pallor of the skin beneath. Still, the pre-dead James had been dirty
blonde, Spindle's hair had been almost dark enough to call black, but the stuff
floating from their scalps looked the same dull kelpy brown to me now. Bates
kept her head shaved, believing her eyebrows weren't as rusty as I remembered
them. We'd revert to our old skills soon enough, just add water. For now though the
old slur was freshly relevant. The undead really did look all the same if you
didn't know how to look. If you did of course, if you forgot appearance and
watched for motion, ignored meat and studied topology, you'd never mistake one
for another. Every facial tick was a data point. Every conversational pause spoke
volumes more than the words to either side. I could see James's personae
shatter and coalesce in the flutter of an eyelash. Spindle's unspoken distrust of
a man to Bates shouted from the corner of his smile. Every twitch of the
phenotype cried aloud to anyone who knew the language. Where's James croached,
croaked, coughed, waved one Spindle arm at Sarastee's empty coffin gaping at the
end of the row. Spindle's lips cracked in a small rictus. Gone back to fab, eh?
Getting the ship to build some dirt to lie on. Probably communing with the
captain. Bates breathed louder than she spoke. A dry rustle from pipes still
getting reacquainted with the idea of respiration. James again, could do that
up here. Could take a dump up here too, eh? Spindle rasped. Some things you do by
yourself. And some things you kept to yourself. Not many baselines felt
comfortable locking stairs to the vampire. Sarastee, ever courteous, tended to
avoid eye contact for exactly that reason. But there were other surfaces to his
apology. Just as mammalian and just as readable. If he had withdrawn from public
view, maybe I was the reason. Maybe he was keeping secrets. After all, these is
damn well was. She'd taken us a good 15 AU's towards our destination before
something scared her off course. Then she'd skidded north like a startled cat
and started climbing. A wild, high, 3G burn off the ecliptic. 1300 tons of
momentum buckling against Newton's first. She'd emptied her pen tanks, bled dry her
substrate mass, squandered 140 days of fuel in hours. Then a long, cold coast
through the abyss, years of stingy accounting, the thrust of every anti-
proton weighed against the drag of seething it from the void. Teleportation
isn't magic. The Icarus stream couldn't send us the actual antimatter it made,
only the quantum specs. The easiest had to filter feed the raw material from
space one ion at a time. For long, dark years, she'd made do on pure inertia,
hoarding every swallowed atom. Then flip, ionizing lasers strafing the space ahead,
a ram scoop thrown wide in a heartbreak. The weight of a trillion, trillion
protons slowed her down and refilled her gut and flattened us all over again.
Beasius had burned relentless until almost the moment of our resurrection.
It was easy enough to retrace those steps. Our course was there in consensus
for anyone to see. Exactly why the ship had blazed the trail was another matter.
Doubtless it would come all out during the post-Raz briefing. We were hardly the
first vessel to travel under the cloak of sealed orders, and if there'd been a
pressing need to know by now, we've known by now. Still, I wondered who had locked
out the comm logs, mission control maybe, or Sarasti, or Theesius herself for that
matter. It was easy to forget the quantical AI at the heart of the ship. It stayed so
discreetly in the background, nurtured and carried us to permeate our existence
like an unintrusive god. But like god, it never took your calls.
Sarasti was the official intermediary. When the ship did speak, it spoke to him,
and Sarasti called it captain. So did we all. He'd given us four hours to come back.
It took more than three just to get me out of the crypt. By then, my brain was at least firing on most of its synapses,
although my body, still sucking fluids like a thirsty sponge, continued to ache
with every movement. I swapped out drained electrolyte bags or fresh ones and headed
aft. Fifteen minutes to spin up. Fifty to the post-Raz briefing. Just enough time
for those who preferred gravity bow and sleep to haul their personal effects
into the drum and stake out their allotted 4.4 square meters of floor space.
Gravity, or any centripetal facsimile thereof, did not appeal to me. I set up my
own tent in zero G in as far as Stern as possible, nuzzling the forward wall of the
starboard shuttle tube. The tent inflated like an abscess on Theesius's spine, a
little climate-controlled bubble of atmosphere in the dark cavernous vacuum
beneath the ship's carapace. My own effects were minimal. It took all of 30
seconds to stick them to the wall and another 30 to program the tent's
environment. Afterwards, I went for a hike. After five years, I needed the
exercise. Stern was closest, so I started there, at the shielding that separated
payload from propulsion. A single sealed hatch blistered the aft bulkhead dead
center. Behind it, a service tunnel warmed back through the machinery best left
untouched by human hands. The fat, superconducting torus of the ram scoop
ring. The antennae fan behind it unwound now into an indestructible soap bubble
big enough to shroud a city. Its face turned sunward to catch the faint
quantum sparkle of the aqueous antimatter stream. More shielding behind
that than the telematter reactor, where raw hydrogen and refined information
conjured fire 300 times hotter than the sun's. I knew the incantations, of
course, antimatter cracking and deconstruction, the teleportation of
quantum serial numbers, but it was still magic to me how we'd come so far so
fast. It would have been magic to anyone, except Sarasti, maybe. Around me, the same
magic worked at cooler temperatures and to less volatile ends. A small riot of
shoots and dispensers crowded the bulkhead on all sides. A few of those
openings would choke on my fist. One or two could swallow me whole. The easiest
fabrication plant could build everything from cutlery to cockpits, give it a big
enough matter stockpile and it could even have built another thesias, albeit in
many small pieces and over a very long time. Some wondered if it could build
another crew as well, although we'd been assured that was impossible. Not even
these machines had fine enough fingers to reconstruct a few trillion SNAT synapses
in the space of the human skull. Not yet, anyway. I believed it. They would never
have shipped us out fully assembled if there had been a cheaper alternative. I
faced forward. Putting the back of my head against that sealed hatch, I could see
almost a thesias' bow, an uninterrupted line of sight extending to a tiny dark
bullseye 30 meters ahead. It was like staring at a great textured target in
shades of white and gray, concentric circles, hatches centered within
bulkheads one behind another, perfectly aligned. Every once stood open in
non-schlot defiance of a previous generation's safety codes. We could keep
them closed if we wanted to, if it made us feel safer. That was all it would do
though. It wouldn't improve our Imperial odds one bit. In the event of trouble,
those hatches would slam shut milliseconds before human senses could even make
sense of an alarm. They weren't even computer controlled. The easiest body
parts had reflexes. I pushed off against the stern plating, wincing at the tug
and stretch of disused tendons, and coasted forward, leaving the fab behind.
The shuttle-axis hatches to Silla and Caribdis briefly constricted my passage
to either side. Past them, the spine widened into a corrugated extensible
cylinder two meters across and, at the moment, maybe 15 long. A pair of ladders
ran opposite each other along its length. Raised portholes the size of manhole covers
stippled the bulkhead to either side. Most of those just looked into the hold.
A couple served as general-purpose airlocks should anyone want to take a
stroll beneath the Caribbas. One opened into my tent. Another, four meters
further forward, opened to debates. From a third, just short of the forward
bulkhead, Yucca Sardosti climbed into view like a long white spider. If he'd
been human, I'd have known instantly what I saw there. I'd have smelled murderer
all over his topology. And I wouldn't have been able to even guess at the number
of his victims because his affect was so utterly without remorse. The killing of
100 was so... ah, start over. The killing of 100 would leave no more stain on
Sardosti's services and the swatting of an insect. Gilt beat it and rolled off
its creature like water on wax. But Sardosti wasn't human. Sardosti was a
whole different animal and coming from him all those homicidal refractions
meant nothing more than predator. He had the inclination. He had the
inclination. Was born to it. Whether he had ever acted on it was between him and
mission control. Maybe they cut you some slack, I didn't say to him. Maybe it's
just the cost of doing business. Your mission critical after all. For all I
know they cut you a deal. You're so very smart. You know we wouldn't have brought
you back in the first place if we hadn't needed you. From the day they cracked
that vat you knew you had leverage. Isn't that how it works, Yucca? You save
the world and the folks who hold your leash agree to look the other way. As a
child I'd read tales about jungle predators transfixing their prey with a
stare. Only after I'd met Yucca Sardosti did I know how it felt. But he wasn't
looking at me now. He was focused on installing his own tent and even if he
had looked me in the eye there'd have been nothing to see with the dark wrap
around visor. He wore indeference to human skittishness. He ignored me as I
grabbed a nearby rung and squeezed past. I could have sworn I smelled raw meat
on his breath. Into the drum. Drums, technically. The biomed hoop at the back
spawning its own bearings. I flew through the center of a cylinder 16 meters
across. Theseus spinal nerves ran along its axis. The exposed plexi and piping
bundled against the ladders on either side. Past them spindles and James
freshly erected tents rose from nooks on opposite sides of the world. Spindle
himself loaded off my shoulders. Still naked but for his gloves. I could tell
from the way his fingers moved that his favorite color was green. He anchored
himself to one of the three stairways to nowhere arranged around the drum.
Steep narrow steps rising five vertical meters from the deck into empty air.
The next hatch gave dead center of the drum's forward wall. Pipes and
conduits plunged into the bulkhead on either side. I grabbed a convenient
rung to slow myself, biting down once more on the pain, and floated through.
T-junction. The spinal corridor continued forward. A small diverticulum
branched off to an EVA cubby in the forward airlock. I stayed the course and
found myself back in the crypt, mirror bright and less than two meters deep.
Empty pods gaped to the left, sealed ones to the right. We were so irreplaceable we'd come with
replacements. They slept on, oblivious. I'd met three of them back in training.
Hopefully none of us would be getting reacquainted anytime soon. Only four pods
to starboard though. No backup for Svarasti. Another hatchway, smaller this time.
I squeezed through into the bridge. Dim light there. A silent, shifting mosaic of icons and
alphanumerics iterating across dark glassy surfaces. Not so much bridge as cockpit and a
cramped one at that. I'd emerged between two acceleration couches, each surrounded by a horseshoe
array of controls and readouts. Nobody expected to ever use this compartment. Thesias was perfectly
capable of running herself. And if she weren't, we were capable of running her from our inlays.
And if we weren't, odds were overwhelming we were all dead anyway. Still, against that
astronomically off-the-wall chance, this was where one or two intrepid survivors could pilot
the ship home after everything else had failed. Between the footwells, the engineers had crammed
one last hatch and one last passageway to the observation blister on Thesias' prow. I hunched
my shoulders, tendons cracked and complained, and pushed through into darkness. Clam shell shielding
covered the outside of the dome like a pair of eyelids squeezed tight. A single icon glowed
softly from a touchpad to my left. A faint stray light followed me through from the spine,
brushed in fingers across the concave enclosure. The dome resolved in faint shades of blue and
gray as my eyes adjusted. A stale draft stirred the webbing floating up from the rear bulkhead,
mixed oil and machinery at the back of my throat. Buckles clicked faintly in the breeze like
impoverished wind chimes. I reached out and touched the crystal. The innermost layer of two,
warm air piped through the gap between to cut the cold. Not completely, though. My fingertips
chilled instantly. Space out there. Perhaps en route to our original destination, Thesias had seen
something that scared her clear out of the solar system. More likely she hadn't been running away
from anything but to something else, something that hadn't been discovered until we'd already
died and gone to heaven. In which case, I reached back and tapped the touchpad. I half expected
nothing to happen. Thesias windows could be as easily locked as their com logs. But the dome
split instantly before me. A crack, then a crescent, then a wide-eyed, lidless stare as the shielding
slid smoothly back into the hull. My fingers clenched reflexively into a fistful of webbing.
The sudden void stretched empty and unforgiving in all directions, and there was nothing to cling
to but a metal disk barely four meters across. Stars everywhere. So many stars that I could not
for the life of me understand how the sky could contain them yet all be so black. Stars and nothing
else. What did you expect, I chided myself. An alien mothership hanging off the starboard bow?
Well, why not? We were out here for something. The others were anyway. They'd be essential no
matter where we ended up. My own situation was different, I realized. My usefulness degraded
with distance, and we were over half a light year from home. When it is dark enough, you can see the
stars. Emerson. Where was I when the lights came down? I was emerging from the gates of heaven,
mourning a father who was, to his own mind at least, still alive. It had been scarcely two months
since Helen had disappeared under the cowl. Two months by hour reckoning at least. From her
perspective it could have been a day or a decade, the virtually omnipotent set their subjective
clocks along with everything else. She wasn't coming back. She would only deign to see her husband
under conditions that amounted to a slap in the face. He didn't complain. He visited as often as
she would allow. Twice a week, then once, then every two. Their marriage decayed with the exponential
determinism of a radioactive isotope, and he still sought her out, except for her conditions.
On the day the lights came down, I had joined him at my mother's side. It was a special occasion,
the last time we would ever see her in the flesh. For two months her body had lain in a state along
with 500 other new ascendants on the ward, open for viewing by the next of kin. The interface was
no more real than it would ever be, of course. The body could not talk to us, but at least it was there.
Its flesh warm, the sheets clean and straight, Helen's lower face still visible below the cowl,
though eyes and ears were helmeted. We could touch her. My father often did. Perhaps some distant
part of her still felt it. But eventually someone has to close the casket and dispose of the remains.
Room must be made for new arrivals, so we came to this last day at my mother's side.
Jim took her hand one more time. She would still be available in her world on her terms,
but later this day the body would be packed into storage facilities crowded far too efficiently
for flesh and blood visitors. We had been assured that the body would remain intact.
The muscles electrically exercised, the body flexed and fed, the corpus kept ready to return
to active duty should have an experience on inconceivable and catastrophic meltdown.
Everything was reversible, we were told. And yet, there were so many who had ascended,
and not even the deepest catacombs go on forever. There were rumors of dismemberment,
of non-essential body parts hewn away over time according to some optimum packing algorithm.
Perhaps Helen would be a torso this time next year, and is somebody to head the year after.
Perhaps chassis would be stripped down to the brain before we'd even left the building,
awaiting only that final technological breakthrough that would herald the arrival of the great digital
upload. Rumors, as I say, I personally didn't know of anyone who'd come back after ascending,
but then why would anyone want to? Not even Lucifer left heaven until he was pushed.
Dad might have known for sure. Dad knew more than most people about the things that people
weren't supposed to know, but he never told tales out of turn. Whatever he knew, he'd obviously
decided its disclosure wouldn't have changed Helen's mind. That would have been enough for him.
We'd on the hoods that served as day passes for the unwired, and we met my mother in the Spartan
visiting room she imagined for these visits. She'd built no windows into the world she occupied,
no hint of whatever utopian environment she'd constructed for herself. She hadn't even opted
for one of the prefab visiting environments designed to minimize dissonance among visitors.
We found ourselves in a featureless bay sphere five meters across. There was nothing in there
but her. Maybe not so far removed from her version of utopia after all, I thought. My father smiled.
Helen. Jim! She was twenty years younger than the thing on the bed, but still she made my skin crawl.
Siri, you came! She always used my name. I don't think she ever called me son.
You're still happy here? My father asked.
Wonderful! I do wish you could join us.
Jim smiled. Someone asked to keep the lights on.
Now you know this isn't goodbye, she said. You can visit whenever you like.
Only if you do something about the scenery. Not just a joke, but a lie. Jim would have come at
her call even if the gauntlet involved bare feet and broken glass. And Chelsea too, Helen continued.
It would be so nice to finally meet her after all this time.
Chelsea's gone, Helen, I said. Oh yes, but I know you stay in touch. I know she was special to you.
Just because you're not together anymore doesn't mean she can't. You know she...
A startling possibility stopped me in mid-sentence. Maybe I hadn't actually told them.
Son, Jim said quietly. Maybe you could give us a moment.
I would have given them a fucking lifetime. I unplugged myself back to the ward, looked from
the corpse on the bed to my blind and catatonic father on his couch, murmuring sweet nothings
into the data stream. Let them perform for each other. Let them formalize and finalize their so
called relationship in whatever way they saw fit. Maybe just once they could even bring themselves
to be honest, there in that other world where everything else was a lie. Maybe.
I felt no desire to bear witness either way. But of course I had to go back in for my own
formalities. I adopted my role and the familial set piece one last time, partook of the usual lies.
We all agreed that this wasn't going to change anything and nobody deviated enough from the
script to call anyone else liar on their account. And finally, careful to say until next time rather
than goodbye, we took our leave of my mother. I even suppressed my gag reflex long enough to
give her a hug. Jim had his inhaler in hand as we emerged from the darkness. I hoped, without much
hope, that he'd throw it in the garbage receptacles we passed through the lobby. But he'd raised it
to his mouth and took another hit of vasopressin that he would never be tempted. Fidelity in an
aerosol. You don't need that anymore, I said. Probably not, he agreed. It won't work anyway.
You can't just imprint on someone who isn't even there, no matter how many hormones you snored.
It just... Jim said nothing. We passed beneath the muzzles of centuries panning for infiltrating
realists. She's gone, I blurted. She doesn't care if you find someone else. She'd be happy if you did.
It would let her pretend the books had been balanced. She's my wife, he told me.
That doesn't mean what it used to. It never did. He smiled a bit at that. It's my life, son.
I'm comfortable with it. Dad, I don't blame her, he said, and neither should you.
Easy for him to say. Easy even to accept the hurt he'd inflicted on him all these years.
This cheerful facade here at the end, hardly made up for the endless bitter complaints my father had
endured throughout living memory. Do you think it's easy when you disappear for a month on end?
Do you think it's easy always wondering who you're with and what you're doing and even if you're alive?
Do you think it's easy raising a child like that on your own?
She'd blamed him for everything, but he bore it gracefully because he knew it was all a lie.
He knew he was only the pretense. She wasn't leaving because he was AWOL or unfaithful.
Her departure had nothing to do with him at all. It was me. Helen left the world because she couldn't
stand to look at the thing who replaced her son. I would have pursued it, would have tried yet again
to make my father see, but by now we'd left the gates of heaven for the streets of Purgatory,
where pedestrian's and all sides murmured an astonishment and stared open mouth at the sky.
I followed their gaze to a strip of raw twilight between the towers and gasped.
The stars were falling. The zodiac had rearranged itself into a precise grid of bright points with
luminous tails. It was as though the whole planet had been caught in some great closing net, the
knots of its mesh aglow with St. Elmo's fire. It was beautiful. It was terrifying.
I looked away to recalibrate my distance vision to give this ill-behaved hallucination a chance
to vanish gracefully before I set my empirical gaze to high beam. I saw a vampire in that moment,
a female, walking among us like the archetypal wolf in sheep's clothing. Vampires were uncommon
creatures on street level. I'd never seen one in the flesh before. She had just stepped onto the
street from the building across the way. She stood ahead taller than the rest of us, her eyes
shining yellow and bright as a cat in the deep, deepening dark. She realized as I watched that
something was amiss. She looked around, glanced at the sky, and continued on her way, totally
indifferent to the cattle on all sides, to the heavenly portent that had transfixed them.
Totally indifferent to the fact that the world had just turned inside out.
It was 1035 Greenwich Mean Time, February 13th, 2082.
They clenched around the world like a fist. Each black as the inside of an event horizon until
those last bright moments when they all burned together. They screamed as they died. Every radio
up to geostat, groaned in unison. Every infrared telescope went briefly snow-blind. Ashes stained
the sky for weeks afterwards. Mesophheric clouds high above the jet stream turned to glowing rust
with every sunrise. The objects apparently consisted largely of iron. Nobody ever knew
what to make of that. But for perhaps the first time in history the world knew before being told,
if you'd seen the sky, you had the scoop. The usual arbiters of newsworthiness stripped of the
accustomed role in filtering reality had to be content with merely labeling it. It took them
90 minutes to agree on fireflies. A half hour after that, the first Fourier transforms had
appeared in the news sphere. To no one's great surprise, the fireflies had not wasted their
dying breaths on static. There was pattern embedded in that terminal chorus, some cryptic
intelligence that resisted all earthly analysis. The experts, rigorously empirical, refused to
speculate. They only admitted that the fireflies had said something. They didn't know what.
Everyone else did. How else would you explain 65,536 probes evenly dispersed along a latitude
longitude grid that barely left any square meter of planetary surface unexposed? Obviously,
the flies had taken our picture. The whole world had been caught with its pants down in panoramic
composite freeze frame. We'd been surveyed. Whether as a prelude to formal introductions or outright
invasion was anyone's guess. My father might have known someone who might have known. But by then he'd
long since disappeared, as he always did during times of hemispheric crisis. Whatever he knew or
didn't, he'd left me to find my own answers with everyone else. There was no shortage of
perspectives. The news sphere seethed with scenarios ranging from utopian to apocalyptic.
The fireflies had seated lethal germs throughout the jet stream. The fireflies had been on nature
safari. The Icarus Array was being retooled to power a doomsday weapon against the aliens.
The Icarus Array had already been destroyed. We had decades to react. Anything from another
solar system would have to obey the light speed limit just like everything else.
We had days to live. Organic warships had just crossed the asteroid belt and would be fumigating
the planet within a week. Like everyone else, I bore witness to lurid speculations and talking
heads. I visited blather nodes, soaked myself in other people's opinions. That was nothing new
as far as it went. I'd spent my whole life as a sort of alien ethologist in my own right,
watching the world behave, gleaning patterns and protocols, learning the rules that allowed
me to infiltrate human society. It had always worked before. Somehow, though, the presence of
real aliens had changed the dynamics of the equation. Mirror observation didn't satisfy
anymore. It was as though the presence of this new outgroup had forced me back into the clade
whether I liked it or not. The distance between myself and the world suddenly seemed forced and
faintly ridiculous. Yet I couldn't for the life of me figure out how to let it go.
Chelsea had always said that telepresence emptied the humanity from human interaction.
They say it's indistinguishable, she told me once. Just like having your family right there,
snuggled up so you can see them and feel them and smell them next to you. But it's not. It's just
shadows on the cave wall. I mean, sure, the shadows come in 3D color with force feedback,
tactile interactivity. They're good enough to fool the civilized brain, but your gut knows
those aren't people, even if it can't put its finger on how it knows. They just don't feel real.
Know what I mean? I didn't. Back then I'd had no clue what she was talking about.
But now we were all cavemen again, huddling beneath some overhang while lightning split
the heavens and vast formless monsters barely glimpsed in bright strobe-frozen instance roared
and clashed in darkness on all sides. There was no comfort in solitude. You couldn't get it from
interactive shadows. You needed someone real at your side, someone to hold on to, someone to share
your airspace along with your fear and hope and uncertainty. I imagine the presence of
companions who wouldn't vanish the moment I unplugged, but Chelsea was gone and Pag in her wake.
The few others I could have called, peers and former clients with whom I impersonations of rapport
had been especially convincing, didn't seem worth the effort. Flesh and blood had its own
relationship to reality, necessary but not sufficient. Watching the world from a distance
that occurred to me at last, I knew exactly what Chelsea had meant with her lead-out ramblings about
desaturated humanity and the colorless interactions of virtual space. I'd known all along. I'd just
never been able to see how it was any different from real life.
Imagine you are a machine. Yes, I know, but imagine you're a different kind of machine,
one built from metal and plastic and designed not by blind haphazard natural selection by
engineers and astrophysicists with their eyes fixed firmly on specific goals. Imagine that your
purpose is not to replicate or even to survive but to gather information. I can imagine that easily.
It is in fact a much simpler impersonation than the kind I'm usually called on to perform.
I coast through the abyss on the colder side of Neptune's orbit. Most of the time I exist only as
an absence to any observer on the visible spectrum, a moving asymmetrical silhouette blocking the stars.
But occasionally during my slow endless spin, I glint with dim hints of reflected starlight.
If you catch me in those moments, you might infer something of my true nature,
a segmented creature with foil skin bristling with joints and dishes and spindly antennae.
Here and there a whisper of accumulated frost clings to a joint or seam, some frozen
wisp of gas encountered in Jupiter space perhaps. Elsewhere I carry the microscopic corpses of
earthly bacteria who thrived with carefree abandon on the skins of space stations or the benign lunar
surface, but who had gone to crystal at only half present distance from the Sun. Now a breath away
from absolute zero they might shatter to Photon's touch. My heart is warm at least. A tiny nuclear
fire burns in my thorax, leaves me indifferent to the cold outside. It won't go out for a thousand
years barring some catastrophic accident. For a thousand years I will listen for faint voices
from mission control and do everything they tell me to do. So far they have told me to study comets.
Every instruction I have received has been a precise and unambiguous elaboration on that one
overriding reason for my existence. Which is why these latest instructions are so puzzling,
for they make no sense at all. The frequency is wrong. The signal strength is wrong. I cannot
even understand the handshaking protocols. I request clarification. The response arrives
almost a thousand minutes later and it is an unprecedented mix of orders and requests for
information. My answer is best I can. Yes, this is the bearing at which signal strength was greatest.
No, it is not the usual bearing for mission control. Yes, I can retransmit. Here it is all over again.
Yes, I will go into standby mode. I await further instructions. They arrive 839 minutes later and
they tell me to stop studying comets immediately. I am to commence a controlled, possessive tumble
that sweeps my antenna through a consecutive 5 degree arc increments along all three axes
with a period of 94 seconds. Upon encountering any transmission resembling the one which confused
me, I am to fix upon the bearing of maximal signal strength and arise a series of parameter values.
I am also instructed to retransmit the signal to mission control.
I do as I am told. For a long time I hear nothing, but I am infinitely patient and incapable of boredom.
Eventually, a fleeting familiar signal brushes against my afferent array. I reacquire and track
it to source, which I am well equipped to describe, a trans-Neptunian comet in the Kuiper Belt,
approximately 200 kilometers in diameter. It is sweeping a 21 centimeter tight beam radio wave
across the heavens with a periodicity of 4.57 seconds. This beam does not intersect mission
control's coordinates at any point. It appears to be directed at a different target entirely.
It takes much longer than usual for mission control to respond to this information.
When it does, it tells me to change course. Mission control informs me that henceforth
my new destination is to be referred to as Burns Callfield. Given current fuel and inertial constraints,
I will not reach it in less than 39 years. I am to watch nothing else in the meantime.
I had been liaising for a team at the Kurzweil Institute, a fractured group of cutting-edge
savants convinced they were on the verge of solving the quantum glial paradox,
that particular logjam installed AI for decades. Once broken, the expert promised we'd be 18 months
away from the first personality upload and only two years from reliable human consciousness emulation
in a software environment. It would spell the end of corporeal history, usher in a singularity that
had been wading in the wings impatiently for nigh on 50 years. Two months after firefall,
the institute cancelled my contract. I was actually surprised it had taken them so long.
It had cost us so much, this overnight inversion of global priorities, these breakneck measures
making up for lost initiative. Not even our shiny, new post-scarcity economy could withstand such a
seismic shift without lurching towards bankruptcy. Installations in deep space, long-sense imagines
secure by virtue of their remoteness, were suddenly vulnerable for exactly the same reason.
The Grange habitats had to be refitted for defense against an unknown enemy. Commercial ships on
the Martian loop were conscripted, weaponized, and reassigned. Some secured to the high ground
over Mars while others fell sunward to guard the Icarus Array. It didn't matter that the fireflies
hadn't fired a shot at any of these targets. We certainly couldn't afford the risk. We were all
in it together, of course, desperate to regain some hypothetical upper hand by any means necessary.
Kings and corporations scribbled IOUs on the backs of napkins and promised to sort everything out
once the heat was off. In the meantime, the prospect of utopia in two years took a back seat
to the shadow of Armageddon reaching back from next Tuesday. The Kurzweil Institute, like everyone
else, suddenly had other things to worry about. So I returned to my apartment, split a bulb of
Genfiddich, and arrayed virtual windows like daisy petals in my head. Everyone icons debated on all
sides, serving up leftovers two weeks past their expiry date. This graceful breakdown of global
security. No harm done. Calm sats annihilated, thousands dead. Random collisions, accidental deaths.
Who sent them? We should have seen them coming. Why didn't we? Deep space, inverse square, do the math.
They were stealthed. What do they want? We were raped. Jesus Christ, they just took our picture.
Why the silence? Moon's fine. Mars is fine. Where are they? Why haven't they made contact?
Nothing's touched the O'Neill's. Technology implies belligerence. Are they coming back?
Nothing attacked us. Yet. Nothing invaded. So far. But where are they? Are they coming back?
Anyone? Jim Moore voice only encrypted. Except? The text blossomed directly in my line of sight,
eclipsing the debate. I read it twice. I tried to remember the last time he'd called from the field,
and couldn't. I muted the other windows. Dad? Son, he replied after a moment. Are you well?
Like everyone else, still wondering whether we should be celebrating or crapping our pants.
He didn't answer immediately. It's a big question, all right? He said it last.
I don't suppose you could give me any advice. They're not telling us anything at ground level.
It was a rhetorical request. His silence was hardly necessary to make the point.
I know I added after a moment. Sorry, it's just they're saying the Icarus of Wittoray went down,
and you know I can't. Oh, my father paused. That's ridiculous. Icarus is fine. It is?
He seemed to be weighing his words. The fireflies probably didn't even notice it.
There's no particle trail as long as it stays off stream, and it would be buried in solar glare
unless someone knew where to search. It was my turn to fall silent. This conversation felt suddenly
wrong. Because when my father went on the job, he went dark. He never called his family.
Because even when my father came off the job, he never talked about it. It wouldn't matter
whether the Icarus Array was still online or whether it had been shredded and thrown into the
sun like a thousand kilometers of torn origami. He wouldn't tell either tale unless an official
announcement had been made. Which, I refreshed and indexed when Doge has to be sure. It hadn't.
Because while my father was a man of few words, he was not a man of frequent indecisive pauses,
and he had hesitated before each and every line he'd spoken in this exchange.
I tugged ever so gently on the line. But they've sent ships, and started counting.
One one thousand, two one thousand, just a precaution. Icarus was overdue for a visit anyway.
You don't want to swap out your whole grid without at least dropping in and kicking the
new tires first. Nearly three seconds to respond.
You're on the moon, I said. Pause. Close enough.
What are you, dad? Why are you telling me this? Isn't this a security breach?
You're going to get a call, he told me. From who? Why? They're assembling a team, the kind of
people you deal with. My father was too rational to dispute the contributions of the
reconz and hybrids in our midst, but he'd never been able to hide his mistrust of them.
They need a synthesis, he said.
Isn't it lucky you've got one in the family? Radio bounced back and forth.
This isn't nephysism, Ciri. I've wanted very much for them to pick someone else.
Thanks for the vote of Kant, but he'd seen it coming, and preempted me before my words could
cross the distance. It's not a slap at your abilities and you know it. You're simply the
most qualified and the work is vital. So why, I began and stopped. He wouldn't want to keep
me away from some theoretical gig at a West Ham lab. What's this about, dad?
The fireflies. They found something.
What? A radio signal from the Kuiper. We traced the bearing.
They're talking?
Not to us, he cleared his throat. It was something of a fluke that we even intercepted the transmission.
Who were they talking to? We don't know. Friendly, hostile, sun, we don't know.
The encryption seems similar, but we can't even be sure of that. All we have is the location.
So you're sending a team. You're sending me. We'd never gone to the Kuiper before.
It had been decades since we'd even sent robots. Not that we lacked capacity. We just hadn't
bothered. Everything we needed was so much closer to home. The interplanetary age had stagnated at
the asteroids. But now something lurked at the furthest edge of our backyard, calling into the
void. Maybe it was talking to some other solar system. Maybe it was talking to something closer.
Something en route. It's not the kind of situation we can safely ignore, my father said.
What about probes? Of course, but we can't wait for them to report back. The follow-ups
then fast-tracked. Updates can be sent en route. He gave me a few extra seconds to digest that.
When I still didn't speak, he said, You have to understand. Our only edge is that as far as we
know Burns Callfield doesn't know we're onto it. We have to get as much as we can in whatever window
of opportunity that grants us. But Burns Callfield hidden itself. Burns Callfield might not welcome
a forced introduction. What if I refuse? The time lag seemed to say Mars. I know you son,
you won't. But if I did, if I'm the best qualified, if the job's so vital,
he didn't have to answer. I didn't have to ask. At these kind of stakes, mission critical elements
didn't get the luxury of choice. I wouldn't even have the child's satisfaction of holding my breath
and refusing to play. The will to resist is no less mechanical than the urge to breathe.
Both can be subverted but the right neurochemical keys.
You killed my Kurzweil contract, I realized. That's the least of what we did.
We let the vacuum between us speak for a while.
If I could go back and undo the thing that made you what you are, Dad said after a while,
I wouldn't in a second. Yeah. I have to go. I just wanted to give you the heads up.
Yeah, thanks. I love you son. Where are you? Are you coming back?
Thanks, I said again. That's good to know.
This is what my father could not un-make. This is what I am.
I am the bridge between the bleeding edge and the dead center.
I stand between the Wizard of Oz and the man behind the curtain. I am the curtain.
I am not an entirely new breed. My roots reach back to the dawn of civilization,
but those precursors served a different function, a less honorable one.
They only greased the wheels of social stability. They would sugarcoat unpleasant truths or
inflate imaginary bogeymen for political expedience. They were vital enough in their own way.
Not even the most heavily armed police state can exert brute force on all its citizens all the time.
Meme management is so much subtler. The rose-tinted refraction of perceived reality,
the contagious fear of threatening alternatives. There have always been those tasked with the
rotation of informational topologies, but throughout most of history they had little to do with
increasing its clarity. The new millennium changed all that. We've surpassed ourselves now. We're
exploring terrain beyond the limits of merely human understanding. Sometimes it contours,
even in conventional space, are just too intricate for our brains to track.
Other times its very axes extend into dimensions inconceivable to minds built to
fucking fight on some prehistoric grassland. So many things constrain us from so many directions.
The most altruistic and sustainable philosophies fail before the brute brainstem imperative of
self-interest. Subtle and elegant equations predict the behaviour of the quantum world,
but none can explain it. After 4,000 years we can't even prove that reality exists beyond the
mind of the first person dreamer. We have such need of intellects greater than our own. But we're
not very good at building them. The forced matings of minds and electrons succeed and fail with
equal spectacle. Our hybrids become as brilliant as savants and as autistic. We graft people to
prosthetics, making their overloaded motor strips jiggle meat and machinery and shake our heads when
their fingers twitch and their tongues stutter. Computers bootstrap their own offspring, grow
so wise and incomprehensible to their communiques assume the hallmarks of dementia, unfocused and
irrelevant to the barely intelligent creatures left behind. And when your surpassing creations
find the answers you asked for, you can't understand their analysis and you can't verify their answers.
You have to take their word on faith. Or you use information theory to flatten it for you,
to squash the Tesseract into two dimensions and the Klein bottle into three, to simplify reality
and pray to whatever gods survive the millennium but your honourable twisting of the truth hasn't
ruptured off any of its load-bearing pylons. You hire people like me, the cross-bred progeny of
profilers and proof assistants and information theorists. In formal settings you'd call me a
synthesis. On the street you'd call me jargonaut or poppy. If you're one of those savants whose hard
one truths are being bastardized and lobotomized or powerful no-nothings interested only in market
share you might call me a mole or a chaperone. If your eyes expindle you'd call me commisar
and when the jive would be a friendly one it would also be more than that. I've never convinced myself
that we made the right choice. I can cite the usual justifications in my sleep, talk endlessly
about the rotational topology of information and the irrelevance of semantic comprehension.
But after all the words I'm still not sure. I don't know if anyone else is either. Maybe it's just
some grand consensual con. Marks and players all in league. We won't admit that our creations are
beyond us. They may speak in tongues but our priests can read those signs. Gods leave their
algorithms carved into the mountain side but it's just little old me bringing the tablets down to
the masses and I don't threaten anyone. Maybe the singularity happened years ago. We just don't want
to admit we were left behind. All kinds of animals living here. Occasional demons too. Ian Anderson,
catfish rising. The third wave they called us. All in the same boat, driving into the long,
dark courtesy of a bleeding edge prototype, crash graduated from the simulators full 18 months
ahead of schedule. In a less fearful economy such violence to the timetable would have bankrupted
four countries and 15 multi-corps. The first two waves came out of the gate and even more of a hurry.
I didn't find out what happened to them until 30 minutes before the briefing.
When Sodosti released the telemetry into consensus. Then I opened wide. Experience flooded up my
inlays and spilled across my parietal cortex in glorious high density fast forward. Even now I
can bring those data back fresh as the day they were recorded. I'm there. I'm them. I am unmanned.
I am disposable. I am souped up and stripped down. A telematter drive with a couple of cameras bolted
to the front end pushing G's that would turn meat to jelly. I sprint joyously toward the darkness.
My twin brother hysterioscopic hundred clicks to starboard. Dual streams of backspat pions boosting
us to relativity before poor old theseus had even crawled past Mars. But now six billion kilometers
to stern mission control turns off the tap and leaves us coasting. The comet swells in our sights.
A frozen enigma sweeping its signal across the sky like a lighthouse beam. We bring rudimentary
senses to bear and stare it down a thousand wavelengths. We've lived for this moment.
We see an erratic wobble that speaks of recent collisions. We see scars smooth icy expanses
where once acne skin is liquefied and refrozen far too recently for the insignificant sun at our
backs to be of any kind of suspect. We see an astronomical impossibility. A comet with a heart
of refined iron burns call field sings as we glide past. Not to us. It ignores our passage as it
ignored our approach. It sings to someone else entirely. Perhaps we'll meet that audience someday.
Perhaps they're waiting in the desolate wastelands ahead of us. Mission control flips us onto our
backs. Keep us fixed on our target past any realistic hope of acquisition. They send last
ditch instructions. Squeeze our fading signals for every last bit among the static.
I can sense their frustration. Their reluctance to let us go. Once or twice we're even asked if
some judicious mix of thrust and gravity might let us linger here a bit longer. But deceleration is
for pansies. We are headed for the stars. Bye, Burnsy. Bye, Mission Control. Bye, Sol. See you at heat death.
Wherely we close on target. There are three of us in the second wave. Slower than our predecessors,
yes, but still so much faster than anything flash constrained. We are weighed down by payloads which
make us virtually omniscient. We see on every wavelength from radio to string. Our autonomous
microbes measure everything our masters anticipated. Tiny onboard assembly lines that can build tools
from the atoms up to assess the things they did not. Atoms scavenged from where we are,
joined with ions beamed from where we were, thrust and material accumulate in our bellies.
This extra mass has slowed us, but midpoint breaking maneuvers have slowed us even more.
The last half of this journey has been a constant fight against momentum from the first.
It is not an efficient way to travel. In lesser times we would have been built early to some
optimal speed, perhaps slung around a convenient planet for a little extra oomph, coasted most of
the way. But time is pressing, so we burn at both ends. We must reach our destination. We cannot
afford to pass it. Cannot afford to kamikaze exuberance of the first wave. They merely glimpse
the lay of the land. We must map it down to the moats. We must be more responsible.
Now, slowing towards orbit, we see everything they saw and more. We see the scabs, the possible iron
core, we hear the singing. And there, just beneath the comet's frozen surface, we see the structure,
an infiltration of architecture into geology. We are not yet close enough to squint, and radar
is too long in the tooth for fine detail. But we are smart, and there are three of us,
widely separated in space. The wavelengths of three radar sources can be calibrated to interfere
at some predetermined point of convergence, and those tripartite echoes, hologrammically
remixed, will increase resolution by a factor of 27. Burns' call field stops singing the moment we
put our planet to action. In the next instant, I go blind. It's a temporary aberration. A reflex
amping off filters to compensate for the overload. My arrays are back online in seconds, diagnostics
green and within and without. I reach out to the others, confirm identical experiences, identical
recoveries. We are still fully functional unless the sudden increase in ambient ion density is
some kind of sensory artifact. We are ready to continue investigation of Burns' call field.
The only real problem is that Burns' call field seems to have disappeared.
Theseus carried no regular crew. No navigators or engineers, no one to swab the decks, no meat
wasted on tasks that machinery orders of mag smaller can perform orders of mag better.
Let superfluous deck hands weigh down other ships, if the non-ascended hordes needed to
attack some pre-tensive usefulness to their lives. Let them infest vessels driven only by commercial
priorities. The only reason we were here was because nobody had yet optimized software for
first contact. Bound past the edge of the solar system, already freighted with the fate of the
world, Theseus wasted no mass on self-esteem. So here we were, rehydrated and squeaky clean.
Isaac Spindle to study the aliens, the gang of four, Susan James and her secondary persona to
talk to them. Major Amanda Bates was here to fight, if necessary, and Yuka Sodosti to command us all,
to move us like chess pieces on some multi-dimensional game board that only vampires could see.
He'd arrayed us around a conference table that warped gently through the commons,
keeping a discreet and constant distance from the curved deck beneath. The whole drum was furnished
in early concave, tricked unwary and hung over brains into thinking they were looking at the
world through fisheye lenses. In deference to the greakiness of the Nevoa undead, it spun in a
mere fifth of a G, but it was just warming up. We'd be at half-grave in six hours, stuck there for
the 18 out of every 24 until the ship decided we were fully recovered. For the next few days,
freefall would be a rare and blessed thing. Light sculptures appeared on the tabletop. Sodosti
could have fed the information directly into our inlays. The whole briefing could have gone
through consensus without the need to assemble physically in the same place, but if you want
to make sure everyone's paying attention, you bring them together. Spin the lead in conspiratorily
at my side. Or maybe the bloodsucker just gets off seeing all this meat in close quarters, eh?
If Sodosti heard he didn't show it, not even to me, he pointed it to the dark heart at the
center of the display, his eyes lost behind the black glass. A wasa object, infrared emitter,
methane glass. On the display was nothing. Our apparent destination was a black disc,
a round absence of stars. In real life, it weighed in at over 10 Jupiters and measured 20%
wider at the belly. It was directly in our path, too small to burn, too remote for the reflection
of distant sunlight, too heavy for a gas giant, too light for a brown dwarf. When did that show up?
Bates squeezed her rubber ball in one hand, the knuckles whitening.
X-Race bike appears during the 76th microwave survey, six years before firefall.
Never confirmed, never reacquired, like a torsion flare from an L-class dwarf,
but we should see anything big enough to generate that kind of effect in the sky's
dark on that bearing. IAU calls it a statistical artifact. Spindle's eyes drew together like
courting caterpillars. What changed? Sotosti smiled faintly, keeping his mouth closed.
The meta-base gets crowded after firefall. Everyone skittish, looking for clues.
After Burns' call field explodes, he clicked at the back of his throat. Turns out the spike
might arise from a sub-dwarf object after all, if the magnetosphere is torqued enough.
Bates, torqued by what? Don't know.
No.
Layers of statistical interference piled up on the table while Sotosti's sketched background.
Even with a solid bearing and half the world's attention, the object had hidden from all but
the most intensive search. A thousand telescopic snapshots had been stacked one on another and
squeezed through a dozen filters before something emerged from the static, just below the 3-meter
band on the threshold of certainty. For the longest time, it hadn't even been real,
just a probabilistic ghost until Thesias got close enough to collapse the waveform.
A quantum particle, heavy as 10 Jupiters. Earthbound cartographers were calling it Big Ben.
Thesias had barely passed Saturn's orbit when it showed up in the residuals.
That discovery would have been moot for anyone else. No other ship caught on route could have
packed enough fuel for anything but the long dejected loop back home. But Thesias' thin,
infinitely attenuate fuel line reached all the way back to the Sun. She could turn on the proverbial
dime. We changed course in our sleep and the Icarus stream tracked our moves like a cat after
prey, feeding us at light speed. And here we were. Talk about long shots, spindle grumbled.
Across the table, baits flicked her wrist. Her ball sailed over my head. I heard it bounce off the deck.
Not the deck, something in me amended. Handrail.
We're assuming the comet was a deliberate decoy then.
Sardosti nodded. The ball ricocheted back into my line of sight, high overhead, and disappeared
briefly behind the spinal bundle, looping through some eccentric, counter-intuitive parabola in the
drum's feeble grav. So they want to be left alone. Sardosti steepled his fingers and turned his face
in her direction. That your recommendation? She wished it was. No, sir. I'm just saying that
Burns Caulfield took a lot of resources and effort to set up. Whoever built it obviously values
their anonymity and has the technology to protect it. The ball bounced one last time and wobbled
back towards the commons. Baits half hopped from her seat. She floated briefly, barely catching
it on its way past. There remained a newborn animal awkwardness to her movements, half choreolous,
half residual rigor. Still, a big improvement in four hours. The rest of the humans were barely
past the walking stage. Maybe it wasn't much trouble for them at all, eh? Spindle amusing.
Maybe it was dead easy. In which case they might or might not be as xenophobic, but they're even
more advanced. We don't want to rush into this. Sardosti turned back to the simmering graphics.
So. Baits needed the recovered ball with her fingertips. The second mouse gets the cheese.
We may have blown our top of the line recon in the Kuiper, but we don't have to go in blind.
Send in our own drones along separate vectors. Hold off on a close up approach until we at least
know whether we're dealing with friendlies or hostels. James shook her head. If they were hostile,
they could have packed the fireflies with antimatter, or sent one big object instead of 60,000
little ones. Let the impact take us out. The fireflies only imply an initial curiosity, Baits said.
Who knows if they like what they saw. What if this whole diversion theory is just so much shit?
I turn briefly startled. James' mouth had made the words. Sasha had spoken them.
You want to stay hidden. You don't light up the sky with fucking fireworks, she continued.
You don't need a diversion if nobody's looking for you, and nobody's looking for you if you lie low.
If they were so curious, they could have just snuck in a spy cam.
Risk detection, the vampire said mildly. Hate to break at Yuka, but the fireflies
didn't exactly slip under the ra- Sadasti opened his mouth, closed it again,
filed teeth, briefly visible, clicked audibly behind his face.
Tabletop graphics reflected off his visor, a band of writhing polychrome distortions where eyes
should be. Sasha shut up.
Sadasti continued. They traded stealth for speed. By the time you react, they already have what
they want. He spoke quietly, patiently, a well-fed predator explaining the rules of the game to pray
that really should know better. The longer it takes me to track you down, the more hope you have of
escaping. But Sasha had already fled. Her service is it's scattered like a flock of panicked starlings,
and the next time James's mouth, Susan James's mouth, opened it was Susan James who spoke through
it. Sasha's aware of the current paradigm Yuka. She's simply more worried that it might be wrong.
Got another way we could trade it in on? Spindle wondered. More options, longer warranty?
I don't know, James sighed. I guess not. It's just odd that they'd want to actively mislead us.
I'd hope that they were merely, well, she spread her hands. Probably no big deal. I'm sure they'll
still be willing to talk if we handle the introductions right. We just need to be a little bit more
cautious, perhaps. Sadasti unfolded himself from his chair and loomed over us. We go in. What we
know weighs against further delay. Bates frown and pitched her ball back into orbit. Sir, all we know
is that an Owasa emitters in our path. We don't even know if there's anyone there.
There is, Sadasti said. They expect us. Nobody spoke for a few seconds. Someone's joint
cracked in silence. Uh, Spindle began. Without looking, Sadasti flicked out his arm and snatched
Bates' returning ball from the air. Later our ping's thesy is four hours forty eight minutes ago.
We respond with an identical signal. Nothing. Probe launches half hour before we wake up.
We don't go in blind, but we don't wait. They see us already. Longer we wait, greater risk of
countermeasures. I looked at the dark, featureless placeholder on the table, bigger than Jupiter
and we couldn't even see it yet. Something in the shadow of that mass had just reached out
with a casual, unimaginable precision and tapped us on the nose with a laser beam.
This was not going to be an even match. Spindle spoke for all of us. You knew that all along?
You're telling us now? This time Sadasti's smile was wide and toothy. It was though a gash
had opened in the lower half of his face. Maybe it was a predator thing. He just couldn't help
playing with his food. It wasn't so much the way they looked. The elongate limbs, the pale skin,
the canines and the extended mandible. Noticable, yes, even alien, but not disturbing, not frightening.
Not even the eyes, really. The eyes of dogs and cats shine in the darkness. We don't shiver at the
sight. Not the way they looked. The way they moved. Something in the reflexes, maybe. The way they
held their limbs, like mantis limbs, long, jointed things you just knew could reach out and snatch
you from right across the room anytime they felt like it. When Sadasti looked at me, really looked,
naked-eyed, unfiltered by the visor. A half million years just melted away. The fact that he was
extinct meant nothing. The fact that we'd come so far, grown strong enough to resurrect our own
nightmares to serve us, meant nothing. The genes aren't fooled. They know what to fear. Of course,
you had to experience it in person. Robert Pagliani knew the story of vampires down to molecules,
but even with all those technical specs in his head, he never really got it.
He called me before we left. I hadn't been expecting it, ever since the roster had been
announced. Our watches had blocked Hall so many would not explicitly contact listed. I'd forgot
that Pag had been. We hadn't spoken since Chelsea. I'd given up on ever hearing from him again.
But there he was. Podman? He smiled, a tentative overture.
It's good to see you, I said, because that's what people said in similar situations.
Yeah, well, I saw your name on the noose. You've made it big for a baseline.
Not so big.
Crap, you're the vanguard of the human race. You're our first, last, and only hope against the unknown.
Man, you showed them. He held up his fist and shook it, vicariously triumphant.
Showing them had become a cornerstone of Robert Pagliano's life. He'd really made it work for him,
too, overcome the handicap of a natural birth with retrofits and enhancements and sheer bloody
mindedness. In a world in which humanity had become redundant and unprecedented numbers,
we'd both retain the status of another age, working professional.
So you're taking orders from a vamp, he said now, talk about fighting fire with fire.
I guess it's practice until we run up against the real thing.
He laughed. I couldn't imagine why, but I smiled back anyway. It was good to see him.
So what do they like? Pag asked. Vampires? I don't know, just met my first one yesterday.
And? Hard to read. Didn't even seem to be aware of his surrounding sometimes. He seemed to be
often his own little world. He's aware, all right. Those things are so fast, it's scary.
You know they can hold both aspects of the necker cube in their heads at the same time?
The term rang a bell. I subtitled and saw the wire, the thumbnail of a familiar wireframe box.
Now I remembered. Classic ambiguous illusion. Sometimes the shaded panel seemed to be in front,
sometimes behind. The perspective flipped back and forth as you watched.
You or I, we can only see it one way or the other, Pag was saying.
Vamp's see it both ways at once. Do you have any idea what kind of an edge that gives him?
Not enough of one. Touche. Hey, not their, not their fault. Neural traits get fixed in small
populations. I don't know if I'd call the crucifix glitch neutral. It was at first.
How many intersecting right angles do you see in nature? He waved one dismissive hand. Anyway,
that's not the point. The point is they can do something that's neurologically impossible for
us humans. They can hold simultaneous multiple worldviews, podman. They just see things we have
to work out step by step. They don't have to think about it. You know, there isn't a single baseline
human who could just tell you just off the top of their heads every prime number between one and
a billion. In the old days, only a few autistics could do shit like that. He never uses the past
tense, I murmured. Huh? Oh, that, Pag nodded. They never experienced the past tense. It's just another
thread to them. They don't remember stuff. They relive it. What, like a post-traumatic flashback?
Not so traumatic, he grimaced. Not for them, at least. So this is obviously your current
hotspot, vampires. Vampires are the capital hot spot for anyone with a neuro in their CV.
I'm just doing a couple of histology papers. Pattern matching receptors, Mexican hat arrays,
reward irrelevance filters, the eyes basically. Right, I hesitated. Those kind of throw you.
No shit, Pag nodded knowingly. That tap lucid under theirs, that shine, scary. He shook his head,
impressed all over at the recollection. You've never met one, I surmised.
What, in the flesh? I'd give my left ball. Why? It's not the shine, it's... I groped for another word
that fit. The attitude, maybe. Yeah, he said after a bit. I guess sometimes you just gotta be there,
huh? Which is why I envy you, podman. You shouldn't. I shouldn't. Even if you've never met who sent
the flies, you're in for one Christly research opportunity with that... Sarasti, is it? Wasted
on me, the only neuro in my files under medical history. He laughed. Anyway, like I said, I just
saw your name in the headlines and figured, hey, the man's leaving in a couple months. I should
probably stop waiting around for him to call. It had been over two years. I didn't think I'd get through.
I thought you shiftlisted me. No, never. He looked down though and fell silent.
But you should've called her, he said at last. I know. She was dying. You should've...
There wasn't time. He let the lie sit for a while. Anyway, he said at last. I just wanted to wish you
luck. Which wasn't exactly true either. Thanks, I appreciate that. Kick their alien asses. If
aliens have asses. There's five of us, Pag. Nine if you count the backups. We're not exactly an army.
Just an expression, fellow mammal. Bury the hatchet, damn the torpedoes, soothe the serpent.
Raise the white flag, I thought. I guess you're busy, he said. I'll...
Look, you want to get together in airspace? I haven't been to cubits in a while.
Love to, Pod. Unfortunately, I'm in Mancoya, splice and dice workshop.
What, you mean physically? Cutting edge research. Old school habits.
Too bad. Anyway, I'll let you go. I just wanted, you know...
Thanks, I said again. So, you know, bye. Robert Pagliano told me. Which was, when you get down
to it, the reason he called. He wasn't expecting another chance.
Pag blamed me for the way it ended with Chelsea. Fair enough. I blamed him for the way it began.
He'd gone into neuroeconomics, at least partly because his childhood buddy had turned into a
pod person before his eyes. I'd ended up in synthesis for roughly the same reason. Our paths
had diverged, and we didn't see each other in the flesh all that often. But two decades after
I'd brutalized a handful of children on his behalf, Robert Pagliano was still my best and only friend.
You seriously need to thaw out, he told me. And I know just the lady to handle the oven mitts.
That is perhaps the worst use of metaphor in the history of human language, I said.
Seriously, Pod, she'll be good for you. A counterbalance. Easy a bit on the comfy mean, you know?
No, Pag, I don't. What is she, another neuroeconomist?
Neuro-Aesthetist, he said. There's still a market for those?
I couldn't imagine how. Why pay to tweak your compatibility with some significant other when
significant others themselves were so out of fashion. Not much of one, Pag admitted.
Fact is, she's pretty much retired, but she still got the tools, my man. Very thigmotatic.
Likes all her relationships face to face and in the flesh.
I don't know, Pag. Sounds like work. Not like your work. She's gotta be easier than the
bleeding composites you front for. She's smart, she's sexy, and she's nicely inside the standard
except for the personal contact thing, which is not so much outright perversion as charming fetish.
In your case, it could even be therapeutic. If I wanted therapy, I'd see a therapist.
She does a bit of that too, actually. Yeah, and then despite myself. Any good? He looked me up and
down. No one's that good. That's not what this is. I just figured you two would click. Chelsea is
one of the few who might not be completely put off by your intimacy issues. Everyone's got into
me as intimacy issues these days in case you hadn't noticed. He must have. The population
have been dropping for decades. I was being euphemistic. I mean, you're aversion to general
human contact. Making it euphemistic to call you human? He grinned. Different deal. We got history.
No thanks. Too late, she's already on route to the appointed place. A point you're an asshole,
Pag. The tightest. Which was how I found myself intrusively face to face in an airspace lounge
south of Beth and Bear. The lighting was low and indirect, creeping from under seats and at the
edges of tables. The chromatics, this afternoon at least, were defiantly long wave. It was a place
where baselines could pretend to see an infrared. So I pretended for a moment, assessing the woman
in the corner booth, gangly and glorious, half a dozen ethnicities coexisting peacefully with no
single voice dominant. Something glowed on her cheek, a faint emerald staccato against the ambient
redshift. Her hair floated in a diffuse, ebony cloud above her head. As I neared, I caught occasional
glints of metal within that nimbus, the threads of a static generator, pervading the illusion of
weightlessness. In normal light, her blood red skin would doubtless shift down to the fashionable
but water scotch of an unrepentant mongrel. She was attractive, but so was everyone in this kind
of light. The longer the wavelength, the softer the focus. There's a reason fuck cubbies don't come
with fluorescent lights. You will not fall for this, I told myself. Chelsea, she said. Her little
finger rested on one of the tables, inset trickle chargers. Former neuroesthetist, presently a
parasite on the body economic thanks to genes and the machines on the cutting edge. I glow, the glow
on her cheek flapped bright and lazy wings. A tattoo, a bioluminescent butterfly. Siri, I said.
Freelance synthesis indentured servant to the genes and machines that turned you into a parasite.
She waved at the empty seat. I took it, assessing the system before me, sizing up the best approach
for a fast, yet diplomatic disconnect. The set of her shoulders told me she enjoyed lightscapes and
was embarrassed to admit it. Monahan was her favorite artist. She thought herself a natural girl
because she'd stayed on chemical libidinals all these years, even though a synaptic edit would
have been simpler. She reveled in her own inconsistency, a woman whose professional machinery edited
thought itself, yet mistrustful of the dehumanizing impact of telephones. Inanately affectionate
and innately afraid of unreturned affection and indomitably unwilling to let any of that stop her.
She liked what she saw when she looked at me. She was a little afraid of that too.
Chelsea gestured at my side of the table. The touch pads there glowed soft, dissonant sapphire
in the bloody light, like a set of splayed fingerprints. Good dope here. Extra hydroxyl
on the ring or something. Assemblyline Neurofarm doesn't do much for me. It's optimized for people
with more meat in their heads. I fingered one of the pads for appearances and barely felt the tangle.
So, a synthesis, explaining the incomprehensible to the indifferent. I smiled on cue, more like
bridging the gap between the people who make the breakthroughs and the people who take the credit for
them. She smiled back. So how do you do it? All those optimized frontal lobes and refits?
I mean, if they're incomprehensible, how do you comprehend them?
It helps to find pretty much everyone else incomprehensible too, provides experience.
There, that should force a bit of difference.
It didn't. She thought I was joking. I could see her lining up to push for more details,
to ask questions about what I did. Which would lead to questions about me? Which would lead?
Tell me what it's like, I said smoothly, rewiring people's heads for a living.
Chelsea grimaced. The butterfly on her cheek fluttered nervously at the motion, wings brightening.
God, you make it sound like we turn them into zombies or something. They're just tweaks,
mainly. Changing taste in music or cuisine, optimizing make-impedibility. It's completely
reversible. There aren't drugs for that? Nah, too much developmental variation between brains.
Our targeting is really fine scale. But it's not all microsurgery and fried synapses, you know?
You'd be surprised how much rewiring could be done noninvasively. You can start all sorts of
cascades just by playing certain sounds in the right order or showing images with the right
balance of geometry and emotion. I assume those are new techniques. Not really. Rhythm and music
hang their hats in the same basic principle. We just turned art into science. Yeah, but when?
The recent past, certainly. Sometime within the last 20 years or so.
Her voice grew suddenly quiet. Robert told me about your operation. Some kind of viral epilepsy,
right? Back when you were just a tyke? I'd never explicitly asked him to keep it a secret. What
was the difference anyway? I'd made a full recovery. Besides, Peg still thought that had happened to
someone else. I don't know your specifics, Chelsea continued gently. But from the sound of it,
noninvasive techniques wouldn't have helped. I'm sure they only did what they had to.
I tried to suppress the thought and couldn't. I like this woman.
I felt something then. A strange unfamiliar sensation that somehow loosened my vertebrae.
The chair felt subtly, indefinably more comfortable at my back.
Anyway, my silence had thrown her off stride. Haven't done much since the bottom dropped out of the
market. But it did leave me with a fondness for face-to-face encounters, if you know what I mean.
Yeah, Peg said you took your sex in the first person. She nodded.
I'm very old school. You okay with that?
I wasn't certain. I was a virgin in the real world, one of the few things I still had in
common with the rest of civilized society. In principle, I guess, it just seems a lot of effort
for not as much payoff, you know? Don't I, she smiled. Real fuck buddies aren't airbrushed,
got all those needs and demands that you can't edit out. How can you blame anyone for saying no
thanks to all that? Now there's a choice. You gotta wonder how our parents ever stayed together
sometimes. You gotta wonder why they did. I felt myself sinking deeper into the chair,
wondered again at this strange new sensation. Chelsea had said the dopamine was tweaked.
That was probably it. She leaned forward, not koi, not kuketish, not breaking eye contact for an
instant in the long wave gloom. I could smell the lemony tang of pheromones and synthetics
mingling on her skin. But there are advantages too once you learn the moves, she said. The body's
got a long memory. And you do realize there's no trickler under your left finger there, don't you,
Siri? I looked. My left arm was slightly extended, index finger touching one of the trickle pads.
And my right hand mirrored the motion while I wasn't watching, its own finger tapping
uselessly on a blank tabletop. I pulled it back. Bit of a bilateral twitch, I admitted.
The body creeps into symmetrical poses when I'm not looking. I waited for a joke, at least a raised
eyebrow. Chelsea just nodded and resumed her thread. So have your game for this, so am I.
I've never been entangled with a synthesis before. Jargonaut's fine. I'm not proud.
Don't you always know just exactly what to say? She cocked her head at me.
So your name, what's it mean? Relaxed. That was it. I felt relaxed.
I don't know, it's just a name. Well it's not good enough. If you're going to be swapping spit
for any length of time, you gotta get a name that means something. And we were, I realized.
Chelsea had decided while I wasn't looking. I could have stopped her right there, told her what
a bad idea this was, apologized for any misunderstanding. But then there'd be wounded looks and hurt
feelings and guilt because after all, if I wasn't interested, why the hell had I even shown up?
She seemed nice. I didn't want to hurt her. Just for a while, I told myself. It'll be an experience.
I think I'll call you Cygnus, Chelsea said. The swan, I said. A bit preta- a bit precious,
but it could have been worse. She shook her head. Black hole. Cygnus X1.
I furrowed my brow at her, but I knew exactly what it meant. A dark, dense object that sucks
up the light and destroys everything in its path. Thanks a whole fucking lot. Why? I'm not sure.
Something dark about you. She shrugged and gave me a great toothy grin. But it's not unattractive.
And let me give you a tweak or two. I bet you'd grow right out of it.
Pag admitted afterward a bit sheepishly that maybe I should have read that as a warning sign.
Live and learn.
Leaders are visionaries with a poorly developed sense of fear and no concept of the odds against
them. Robert Jarvik. Our scout fell towards orbit watching Ben. We fell days behind watching
the scout. And that was all we did. Sitting Thesias belly while the system's stream telemetry
were inlays. Essential, irreplaceable, mission critical. We might as well have been ballast
during the first approach. We passed Ben's Raleigh limit. Thesias squinted at a meagre
mission spectrum and saw a rogue halo element from Canid's major. A dismembered remnant of some
long lost galaxy that had drifted into ours and ended up as Roadkill, uncounted billions of years ago.
We were closing on something from outside the Milky Way.
The probe had arced down and in, drew close enough for false color enhance. Ben surfaced
brightened to a seething parfait of high contrast bands against a diamond-hard starscape.
Something twinkled there. Faint sparkles on endless overcast.
Lightning, James wondered. Spindle shook his head.
Media writes, must be a lot of rock in the neighborhood.
Wrong color, Sir Oste said. He was not physically among us. He was back in his tent hard-lined
into the captain, but consensus put him anywhere on board he wanted to be. Morphometrics scrolled
across my inlays. Mass, diameter, mean density. Ben's day lasted seven hours, 12 minutes.
Diffused with massive accretion belts circling the equator, more torus than ring,
extending almost a half million kilometers from cloud tops. The pulverized corpses of moons,
perhaps, ground down to leftovers. Media writes, Spindle grinned. Dolja.
He seemed to be right. Increasing proximity speared many of those pinpoint sparkles into
bright ephemeral hyphens, scratching the atmosphere. Closer to the poles, cloud banks flickered with
dim, intermittent flashes of electricity. Weak radio emission peaks at 31 and 400 meters,
outer atmosphere heavy with methane and ammonia, lithium, water, carbon monoxide and abundance.
Ammonia hydrogen sulfide, alky halide mixing locally in those torn, swirling clouds,
neutral alkalis in the upper layers. By now, even thesius could pick those things out from a distance,
but our scout was close enough to see the filigree. It was no longer a disk. It gazed down at a dark
convex wall and seething layers of red and brown, soft faint stains of anthracine and pyrene.
One of the myriad meteorite contrails scorched Ben's face directly ahead. For a moment, I thought I
could even see a tiny dark speck at its core, but sudden static scratched the feet. Baits
cursed softly. The image blurred, then steadied as the probe pitched its voice higher up the spectrum.
Unable to make itself heard, among the long wave din, it now spoke down a laser.
And still, it stuttered. Keeping it aligned across a million fluctuating kilometers should
have posed no problem at all. Our respective trajectories were known parabolas,
our relative positions infinitely predictable at any time t. But the meteorite's contrail jumped
and skittered on the feet as if the beam were being repeatedly, infinitesimally knocked out of
alignment. Incandescent gas blurred its details. I doubted that even a rock-steady image would
have offered any sharp edges for a human eye to hold onto. Still, there was something wrong about
it somehow. Something about the tiny black dot at the core of that fading brightness.
Something that some primitive part of my mind refused to accept as natural.
The image lurched again and flashed to black and didn't return.
Probes fried, Baits reported, spiked there at the end, like it hit a Parker spiral but with a
really tight wind. I didn't need to call it the subtitles. It was obvious in the set of her face
the sudden creases between her eyebrows. She was talking about a magnetic field.
It's... she began and stopped as a number popped up in consensus.
11.2 Tesla. Holy shit, spindle whispered. Is that right?
Sonosti clicked from the back of his throat in the back of the ship. A moment later he
served up an instant replay. Those last few seconds of telemetry zoomed in and smoothed in
contrast and handsome visible light deep down to infrared. There was that same dark shard called
in flame. There was the contrail burning in its wake. Now it dimmed as the objects skipped off
the denser atmosphere beneath and regained altitude. Within moments the heat trace had faded
entirely. The thing that burned at its center rose back into space a fading ember. A great conic
scoop at its front end agaped like a mouth. Stubby fins disfigured an ovoid abdomen.
Ben lurched and went out all over again.
Meteorites, bait said dryly. The thing had left me with no sense of scale. It could have been an
insect or an asteroid. How big, I whispered a split second before the answer appeared on my inlays.
400 meters along the major axis. Ben was safely distanced in our sights once more. A dark, dim
disc centered in Theesius forward viewfinder. But I remembered to close up a twinkling orb of
black-hearted fires, a face gashed and pockmarked, endlessly wounded, endlessly healing. There'd
been thousands of the things. Theesius shivered along her length. It was just a pulse of decelerating
thrust, but for that one moment I imagined I knew how she felt.
We headed in and hedged our bets. Theesius weaned herself with the 98 second burn, edged us into
some vast arc that might with little effort turn into an orbit, or into a quick, discrete flyby if
the neighborhood turned out to be a little too rough. The Icarus stream fell invisibly to port,
its unwavering energy lost to spacetime. Our city-sized molecule-thick parasol wound down
and packed itself away until the next time the ship got thirsty. Anti-matter stockpiles began
dropping immediately. This time we were alive to watch it happen. The dip was infinitesimal,
but there was something disquieting about the sudden appearance of that minus sign on the display.
You could have retained the apron strings, left a buoy behind in the telematter stream to bounce
energy down the well after us. Susan James wondered why we hadn't.
Too risky, Sadasti said without elaboration. Spindle leaned in James' direction.
Why give him something else to shoot at, eh? We sent more probes ahead, though, spat them out hard
and fast and too fuel constrained for anything but flyby and self-destruct. They couldn't take
their eyes off the machine swinging around big bend. Theesius stared her own unblinking stare,
more distant, though more acute. But if those high divers even knew we were out there,
they ignored us completely. We tracked them across the closing distance,
watched them swoop and loop through a million parabolas at a million angles.
We never saw them collide, not with each other, not with the cauldron of rock tumbling around
Ben's equator. Every perigee dipped briefly into atmosphere. There they burned and slowed and
accelerated back into space, their anterior scoops glowing with residual heat.
Bates grabbed a consensus image, drew highlights and a conclusion around the front end. Scramjet.
We tracked nearly 400,000 in less than two days. That appeared to be most of them.
New sightings leveled off afterwards. The cumulative curve flattening towards some
theoretical asymptote. Most of the orbits were close and fast, but Sadasti projected a frequency
distribution extending almost back to Pluto. We might stay out here for years and still catch
the occasional new shovel nose returning from its extended foray into the void.
The faster ones are pulling over 50 Gs on the hairpin turn, Spindle pointed out.
Meat couldn't handle that. I say they're unmanned.
Meat's reinforceable, Sadasti said. If it's got that much scaffolding, you might as well
stop splitting hairs and call it a machine anyway. Surface morphometrics were absolutely uniform.
400,000 divers, everyone identical. If there was an alpha male calling the shots
among the herd, it couldn't be distinguished on sight. One night, as such things are measured on
board, I followed a soft squeal of tortured electronics up to the observation blister.
Spindle floated there watching the skimmers. He'd closed the clam shells,
blocked off the stars, and built a little analytical nest in their place.
Graphs and windows spilled across the inside of the dome as though the virtual space in Spindle's
head was insufficient to contain them. Tactical graphics lit him from all sides, turned his
body into a bright patchwork of flickering tattoos. The illustrated man.
Mind if I come in? I asked. He grunted. Yeah, but not enough to push it.
Inside the dome, the sound of heavy rainfall hissed and spat behind the screeching that had
led me there. What is that? Ben's magnetosphere. He didn't look back. Nice, eh?
Synthesis didn't have opinions on the job. It keeps observers, observer effects to a minimum.
This time, I permitted myself a small breach. The static's nice. I could do without the screeching.
Are you kidding me? That's the music of the sphere, his connoisseur. It's beautiful. Like
old jazz. I never got the hang of that, either. He shrugged and squelched the upper register,
letting the rain pattering around us. His jiggling eyes fixed on some arcane graphic.
Want a scoop for your notes? Sure. There you go.
Light reflective office feedback glove, iridescing like the wing of a dragonfly as he pointed.
An absorption spectrum, a looped time series. Bright peaks surged and subsided, surged and
subsided across a 15 second time frame. Subtitles only gave me wavelengths and angstroms.
What is it? Diver farts. Those bastards are dumping complex organics into the atmosphere.
How complex. Hard to tell so far. Faint traces and they dissipate like that. But sugars and
aminos at least. Maybe proteins. Maybe more. Maybe life. Microbes. An alien terraforming project.
Depends how you define life, eh? Spindle said. Not even Dianocus would last long down there,
but it's a big atmosphere. They better not be in any hurry if they're reworking the whole thing by
direct inoculation. If they were, the job would go a lot faster with self-replicating inoculates.
Sounds like life to me. Sounds like agricultural aerosols is what it sounds like. Those fuckers
are turning the whole damn gas ball into a rice paddy bigger than Jupiter. He gave me a scary grin.
Something's got a big appetite, hm? You gotta wonder if we aren't gonna be a teeny bit outnumbered.
Spindle's findings were front and center at our next get-together. The vampire summed it up for us.
Visual aids dancing on the table. Vaughn Newman's self-replicating R-selector. Seed washes up and
sprouts skimmers. Skimmers harvest raw materials from the accretion belt. Some perturbations in
those orbits. Belt still unsettled. Haven't seen any of the herd giving birth, Spindle remarked.
Any sign of a factory? Sardasty shook his head. Discarded, maybe. Decompiled. Or the herd stopped
breeding at optimal end. These are only the bulldozers, Bates pointed out. There'll be tenets.
A lot of them, eh? Spindle added. Outnumber us by orders of Meg.
James. But they might not show up for centuries. Sardasty clicked. Do these skimmers build
fireflies? Burns Caulfield? It was a rhetorical question. Spindle answered anyway. Don't see how.
Something else does, then. Something already local.
Nobody spoke for a moment. James' topology shifted and shuffled in the silence. When she opened her
mouth again, someone indefinably younger was on top. Their habitat isn't anything like ours,
if they're building a home way out here. That's hopeful. Michelle. The Synthesite. Proteins. Sardasty's
eyes were unreadable behind the visor. Comparable biochemistries. They might eat us.
Whatever these beings are, they don't even live in sunlight. No territorial overlap. No resource
overlap. No basis for conflict. There's no reason we shouldn't get along just fine.
On the other hand, Spindle said, technology implies belligerence.
Michelle storted stoffly. According to a coterie of theoretical historians who've never actually
met an alien, yes. Maybe now we get to prove them wrong. And in the next instance, she was just gone.
Her affect scattered like leaves in a dust devil. And Susan James was back in her place saying,
why don't we just ask them? Ask, Bates said. There are 400,000 machines out there. How do we
know they can't talk? We'd have heard, Spindle said. They're drones. Can't hurt to ping them just
to make sure. There's no reason they should talk even if they are smart. Language and intelligence
aren't all that strongly correlated. Eat them on Earth. James rolled her eyes. Why not try at least?
It's what we're here for. It's what I'm here for. Just send a bloody signal.
After a moment, Bates picked up the ball. Bad game theory, Sue's. Game theory. She made it sound
like a curse. Tit for tat's the best strategy. They pinged us. We pinged back. Ball's in their
court now. We send another signal. We may give away too much. I know the rules, Amanda. They say if
the other party never takes the initiative again, we ignore each other for the rest of the mission
because game theory says you don't want to look needy. The rule only applies when you're going
up against an unknown player, the Major explained. We'll have more options the more we will learn.
James sighed. It's just you all seem to be going into this assuming they'll be hostile,
as if a simple hailing signal was going to bring them down on us.
Bates shrugged. It only makes sense to be cautious. I may be a jarhead, but I'm not eager to piss off
anything that hops between stars and terraform super Jovians for a living. I don't have to remind
anyone here that Theseus is no worship. She'd said anyone she'd meant Sarashti, and Sarashti
focused on his own horizon didn't answer. Not out loud at least, but his surface spoke in a
different tongue entirely. Not yet, they said. Bates was right, by the way. Theseus was officially
tricked out for exploration, not combat. No doubt our masters would have preferred to load
her up with nukes and particle cannons as well as her scientific payload, but not even a telemattered
fuel stream can change the laws of inertia. A weaponized prototype would have taken longer to
build, a more massive one laden with heavy artillery would have taken longer to accelerate.
Time, our masters decided, was of greater essence than armament. In a pinch, our fabrication
facilities could build almost anything we needed given time. It might take a while to build a
particle beam cannon from scratch, and we might have to scavenge a local asteroid for the raw
material, but we could do it. Assuming our enemies would be willing to wait in the interests of fair
play. What were the odds that even our best weapons would prove effective against the
intelligence that had pulled off the firefall? If the unknown was hostile, we would probably
do them no matter what they did. The unknown was technologically advanced, and there were some
who claimed that that made them hostile by definition. Technology implies belligerence, they said.
I suppose I should explain that now that it's completely irrelevant. You've probably forgotten
after all this time. Once there were three tribes. The optimists, whose patron saints were Drake and
Sagan, believed in a universe crawling with gentle intelligence. Spiritual breath were
in vaster and more enlightened than we, a great galactic siblinghood into whose ranks we would
someday ascend. Surely, said the optimists, space travel implies enlightenment, for it requires
the control of great destructive energies. Any race which can't rise above its own brutal instincts
will wipe itself out long before it learns to bridge the interstellar gulf. Of cross from the
optimists sat the pessimists, who genuflected before graven images of Saint Fermi and a host of
lesser lightweights. The pessimists envisioned a lonely universe full of dead rocks and prokaryotic
slime. The odds are just too low, they insisted. Too many rogues, too much radiation, too much
eccentricity, and too many orbits. It's a surpassing miracle that even one earth exists,
to hope for many is to abandon reason and embrace religious mania. After all, the universe is 14
billion years old. If the galaxy were alive with intelligence, wouldn't it be here by now?
Equidistant to the other two tribes, sat the historians. They didn't have too many thoughts
on the probable prevalence of intelligent spacefaring extraterrestrials. But if there are any,
they said, they're not just going to be smart, they're going to be mean.
It might almost seem too obvious a conclusion. What is human history if not an ongoing succession
of greater technologies grinding lesser ones beneath their boots? But the subject wasn't
merely human history, or the unfair advantage the tools give to any given side. The oppressed
snatch up advanced weaponry as readily as the oppressor, given half a chance. No, the real
issue was how those tools got there in the first place. The real issue was what tools are for.
To historians, tools existed for only one reason, to force the universe into unnatural shapes.
They treated nature as an enemy, thereby definition or rebellion against the way things were.
Technology is a stunted thing in benign environments. It never thrived in any culture,
gripped by belief in natural harmony. Why invent fusion reactors if your climate is comfortable,
if your food is abundant? Why build fortresses if you have no enemies? Why force change upon a
world which poses no threat? Human civilization had a lot of branches not so long ago. Even into
the 21st century, a few isolated tribes had barely developed stone tools. Some settled down with
agriculture, others weren't content that they had endured nature itself, still others until they
built cities in space. We all rested eventually though. Each new technology trampled lesser ones,
climbed to some complacent asymptote and stopped. Until my own mother packed herself away like a
larva in a honeycomb softened by machinery, robbed of incentive by her own contentment.
But history never said that everyone had to stop where we did. It only suggested that those who
had stopped no longer struggled for existence. There could be other more hellish worlds where
the best human technology would crumble, where the environment was still the enemy, where the only
survivors were those who fought back with sharper tools and stronger empires. The threats contained
in those environments would not be simple ones. Harsh weather and natural disasters either kill
you or they don't, and once conquered or adapted to, they lose their relevance. No, the only environmental
factors that continued to matter were those that fought back. They countered new strategies with
newer ones that forced their enemies to scale ever greater heights just to stay alive. Ultimately,
the only enemy that mattered was an intelligent one. And if the best toys do end up in the hands
who've never forgotten that life itself is an act of war against intelligent opponents,
what does that say about a race whose machines travel between the stars?
The argument was straightforward enough. It might have even been enough to carry the historians to
victory if such debates were ever settled on the basic of logic, and if a poor population hadn't
already awarded the game to Fermi on points. But the historian paradigm was just too ugly,
too Darwinian for most people, and besides, no one really cared anymore. Not even the
Cassidy surveys late breaking discoveries changed much. So what if some dirt ball at
Ursa Majoris Aridani had an oxygen atmosphere? It was 43 light years away and it wasn't talking.
If you wanted flying chandeliers and alien messiahs, you could build them to order in heaven.
If you wanted testosterone and target practice, you could choose an afterlife chock full of nasty
alien monsters with really bad aim. If the mere thought of an alien intelligence threatened your
worldview, you could explore a virtual galaxy of empty real estate, ripe and awaiting for any
godfearing earthly pilgrims who chanced by. It was all there, just on the other side of a 15-minute
splice job in a cervical socket. Why endure the cramped and smelly confines of real-life space
travel to go visit Pondskum on Europa? And so, inevitably, a fourth tribe arose, a heavenly
host that triumphed over all, the tribe that just didn't give a shit. They didn't know what to do
and the fireflies showed up. So they sent us, in honor of the belated historian Mantra. They sent
along a warrior just in case. It was doubtful in the extreme that any child of Earth would be a
match for a race with interstellar technology, should they prove unfriendly. Still, I could
tell that Bates' presence was a comfort to the human members of the crew, at least. If you go up
unarmed against an angry T-Rex with a four-digit IQ, it can't hurt to have a trained combat specialist
on your side. At the very least, she might be able to fashion a pointy stick from the branch of some
convenient tree.
I swear, if the aliens end up eating the lot of us, we'll have the Church of Game Theory to thank
for it, Sasha said. She was grabbing a brick of couscous from the galley. I was there for the caffeine.
We were more or less alone. The rest of the crew was strewn from dome to fab.
Linguists don't use it. I knew some that did. We don't. And the others are hacks.
Thing about Game Theory is, it assumes rational self-interest among the players,
and people just aren't rational. It used to assume that, I allowed. These days, they factor in social
neurology. Human social neurology. She bit off a corner of her brick, spoke about around a mouthful
of semolina. That's what Game Theory is good for. Rational players or human ones. And let me take a
wild stab here and wonder if either of those is going to apply to that. She waved her hand at some
archetypal alien lurking past the bulkhead. It's got its limitations, I admitted. I guess you use
the tools you can lay hands on. Sasha snorted. So if you couldn't get your hands on a proper set of
blueprints, you'd base your dream home on a book of dirty limericks. Maybe not. And then a bit
defensive in spite of myself, I added, I found it useful, though, in areas you might not expect it
to be. Yeah, name one. Birthdays, I said, and I immediately wished I hadn't. Sasha stopped chewing.
Something behind her eyes flickered, almost strobed, as if her other selves were pricking up their
ears. Go on, she said, and I could feel the whole gang listening in. It's nothing really, just an
example. So tell us. Sasha Cock James' head at me. I shrugged, no point in making a big thing out of
it. Well, according to Game Theory, you should never tell anyone when your birthday is. I don't
follow. It's a lose-lose proposition. There's no winning strategy. What do you mean strategy? It's
a birthday. Chelsea had said the exact same thing when I tried to explain it to her. Look, I'd said,
say you tell everyone when it is and nothing happens. It's kind of a slap in the face.
Or say, suppose they throw you a party, Chelsea, it replied. Then you don't know whether they're
doing it sincerely, or if your earlier interaction just guilted them into observing an occasion
they'd rather have ignored. But if you don't tell anyone and nobody commemorates the event,
there's no reason to feel badly because after all, nobody knew. And if someone does buy you a drink,
then you know it's sincere because nobody would go to all the trouble of finding out when your
birthday is and then celebrating it if they honestly didn't like you. Of course, the gang was more
up to speed on such things. I didn't have to explain it verbally. I could just grab a piece of consensus
and plot out the payoff matrix. Tell, don't tell, along the columns, celebrated, not celebrated,
along the rows, the unassailable black and white logic of cost and benefit in the squares themselves.
The math was irrefutable. The one winning strategy was concealment. Only fools revealed their birthdays.
Sasha looked at me. You ever show this to anyone else? Sure, my girlfriend. Her eyebrows lifted.
You had a girlfriend, a real one? I nodded once. I mean, after you showed this to her.
Well, yes. Uh-huh. Her eyes wandered back to the payoff matrix. Just curious, Ciri, how did she react?
She didn't really. Not at first. Then, well, she laughed. Better woman than me, Sasha shook her head.
I'd have dumped you on the spot.
My nightly constitutional up the spine, glorious dreamy flight along a single degree of freedom,
I sailed through hatches and corridors through my arms wide and spun in the gentle cyclonic
breeze of the drum. Bates ran circles around me, bounced, bouncing her ball against bins and
bulkheads, stretching the field to curving rebound and torque pseudograph. The toy ricocheted off a
stairwell and out of reach as I passed. The major's curses followed me through the needle's eye from
Crip to Bridge. I break to just short of the dome, stopped by the sound of quiet voices on the head.
Of course they're beautiful, spindle murmured, they're stars.
And I'm guessing I'm not your first choice to share the view, James said.
You're a close second, but I've got a date with Mish. She never mentioned it. She doesn't tell you
everything, ask her. Hey, this body's taking its antelibs, even if yours isn't. Mind out of the
gutters, Seuss. Eros is only one kind of love, eh? Ancient Greeks recognized for. Right.
Definitely not Susan, not anymore. Figures you take your lead from a bunch of sodomites.
Fuck, Sasha, all I'm asking is a few minutes alone with Mish before the whip starts cracking again.
My body too, Ike? You want to pull your eyes over my wool? I just want to talk, eh? Alone?
That too much to ask? I heard Sasha take a breath. I heard Michelle let it out.
Sorry, kid. You know the gang. Thank God. It's like some group inspection whenever I come looking
for FaceTime. I guess you're lucky they like you then. I still say you ought to stage a coup.
You could always move in with us. I heard the rustle of bodies and gentle contact.
How are you, spindle-last? You okay? Pretty good. I think I'm finally used to being alive again. You?
Hey, I'm a spaz no matter how long I've been dead. You get the job done.
Why, merci. I try. A small silence. Thiesi has hummed quietly to herself.
Mom was right, Michelle said. They are beautiful. What do you see when you look at them, and then
catching himself? I mean, they're prickly, Michelle told him. When I turn my head, it's like the bands
of very fine needles rolling across my skin and waves. But it doesn't hurt at all. It's almost
electric. It just tingles. It's nice. Wish I could feel that way. You've got the interface. Just patch
a camera into your parietal lobe instead of your visual cortex. That just tell me how a machine
feels vision, eh? Still wouldn't know how you do. Isaac, spindle. You're romantic. Nah. You don't want
to know. You want to keep it mysterious. Already got more than enough mystery to deal with out here
in case you hadn't noticed. Yeah, but we can't do anything about that. That'll change. We'll be
working our asses off in no time. You think? Count on it, spindle said. So far we've just been
peaking from a distance, eh? Bet all kinds of interesting stuff happens when we get in there
and start poking it with a stick. Maybe for you, there's got to be a biological somewhere in the
mix with all those organics. Damn right, and you'll be talking to them while I'm giving them their
physicals. Maybe not. I mean, mom would never admit it in a million years, but you had a point
about language. When you get right down to it, it's a workaround. Like trying to describe dreams
with smoke signals. It's noble. It's maybe the most noble thing a body can do, but you can't turn a
sunset into a string of grunts without losing something. It's limiting. Maybe whatever's out
here doesn't even use it. Bet they do, though. Since when? You're the one who's always pointing
out how inefficient language is. Only when I'm trying to get under your skin. Your pants,
a whole other thing. He laughed at his own joke. Seriously, what are they going to use instead,
telepathy? I say you'll be up to your elbows in hieroglyphics before you know it. And what's more,
you'll decode them in no time. You're sweet, but I wonder. Half the time I can't even decode Yuka.
Michelle fell silent. He actually kind of throws me sometimes. You and seven billion others.
Yeah, I know it's silly, but when he's not around, there's a part of me that can't stop wondering
where he's hiding. And when he's right there in front of me, I feel like I should be hiding.
Not his fault he creeps us out. I know, but it's hardly a big morale booster.
What genius came up with the idea of putting a vampire in charge. Where else are you going to
put him a you want to be the one getting orders to him? And it's not just the way he moves. It's
the way he talks. It's just wrong. You know, he I'm not talking about the present tense thing or
about all the glottals. He Well, you know how he talks, he's terse. It's efficient. It's artificial,
Isaac. He's smarter than all of us put together. But sometimes he talks like he's got a 50 word
vocabulary, a soft snort. It's not like I'd kill him to use an adverb once in a while.
Ah, but you say that because you're a linguist and you can't see why anyone wouldn't want to
wallow in the sheer beauty of language. Spindle harromped with mock pomposity. Now me, I'm a
biologist, so it makes perfect sense. Really? Then explain it to me. Oh, why is an powerful
mutilator of frogs? Simple. Bloodsuckers are transient, not a resident. What are Oh, those
are killer whales, right? Whistle dialects. I said forget the language. Think about the lifestyle.
Residents are fish eaters, eh? They hang out in big groups. Don't move around much talk all the time.
I heard a whisper of motion. Imagine spindle laying in and laying a hand on Michelle's arm.
I imagine the sensors in his gloves telling him what she felt like. Transients now. They eat mammals.
Seals, sea lions, smart prey, smart enough to take cover when they hear a fluke slap or a click
train. So transients are sneaky, eh? Hunt in small groups, range all over the place,
keep their mouths shut so nobody hears him coming. And yuka's a transient.
Man's instinct tell him to keep quiet around prey. Every time he opens his mouth, every time he lets
us see him, he's fighting his own brainstem. Maybe we shouldn't be too harsh on the old guy just
because he's not the world's best motivational speaker, eh? He's fighting the urge to eat us
every time we have a briefing. That's reassuring. Spindle chuckled. It's probably not that bad.
I guess even killer whales let their guard down after making a kill. Why sneak around in a full
snum, eh? So he's not fighting his brainstem. He just isn't hungry. Probably a little of both.
Brainstem never really goes away, you know. But I'll tell you one thing. Some of the playfulness
ebbed from spindle's voice. I've got no problem if Sudosti wants to run the occasional briefing
from his quarters. But the moment we stop seeing him altogether, that's when you start watching your back.
End of part two.
Looking back, I can finally admit it. I envied spindle his way with the ladies.
Spliced in dice to gangly massive ticks and jitters that could barely feel his own skin.
Somehow he managed to be... charming. That's the word. Charming.
As a social necessity, it was all but obsolete, fading into irrelevance along with two-party
non-virtual sex pairing. But even I'd tried one of those, and it would have been nice to have
spindle's self-deprecating skill set to call on. Especially when everything with Chelsea started
falling apart. I had my own style, of course. I tried to be charming in my own peculiar way.
Once, after one too many fights about honesty and emotional manipulation,
I started to think maybe a touch of whimsy might smooth things over. I'd come to suspect that
Chelsea just didn't understand sexual politics. Sure, she edited brains for a living, and maybe
she just memorized all that circuitry without giving any thought to how it had arisen in the
first place. To the ultimate rules of natural selection that had shaped it. Maybe she honestly
didn't know that we were evolutionary enemies, that all relationships were doomed to failure.
If I could slip that insight into her head, if I could charm my way past her defenses,
maybe we'd be able to hold things together. So I thought about it, and came up with the
perfect way to raise her awareness. I wrote her a bedtime story, a disarming blend of humor and
affection, and I called it The Book of Oogenesis. In the beginning there were gemmets, and though
there was sex, low there was no gender, and life was in balance. And God said, let there be sperm,
and some seeds did shrivel in size and grow cheap to make, and they did flood the market.
And God said, let there be eggs, and other seeds were afflicted by a plague of sperm,
and yay, few of them bore full fruit, for sperm brought no food for the zygote,
and only the largest eggs could make up for the shortfall, and these grew yet larger in the fullness
of time. And God put the eggs into the womb, and said, wait here, for thy bulk has made the
unwieldy, and sperm must seek thee out in thy chambers. Henceforth shout thou be fertilized
internally, and it was so. And God said to the gemmets, the fruit of thy fusion may abide in
any place, and take any shape. It may breathe air, or water, or the sulfurous muck of hydrothermal
vents. But do not forget my one commandment unto you, which has not changed from the beginning of
time. Spread thy genes. And thus did sperm and egg go into the world, and sperm said,
I am cheap and plentiful, and if I so debundantly I will surely fulfill God's plan,
I shall forever seek out new mates, and then abandon them when they are with child,
for there are many wombs and little time. But egg said, low, the burden of procreation weighs
heavily upon me. I must carry flesh that is but half mine, gestate and feed it even when it leaves
my chamber, for by now many of eggs bodies were of warm, furry, warm blood and furry besides.
I can have but few children, and must devote myself to those, and protect them at every turn,
and I will make sperm help me, for he got me into this. And he doth struggle at my side,
I shall not let him strain, or lie with my competitors. And sperm liked this knot. And
God smiled, for its commandment had put sperm and egg at war with each other,
even until the day they made themselves obsolete. I brought her flowers one dusky Tuesday evening
when the light was perfect. I pointed out the irony of that old romantic tradition,
the sever genitalia of another species offered as a pre-copulatory bribe,
and then recited my story just as we were about to fuck. To this day I still don't know what went wrong.
The glass ceiling is in you. The glass ceiling is conscience.
Jacob Holtzbrink, the keys to the planet.
There were stories before we left earth of a fourth wave, a fleet of deep-space dreadknots
running silent on our wake, should the cannon fodder up front run into something nasty.
Or if the aliens were friendly, an ambassadorial frigate full of politicians and CEOs ready to
elbow their way to the front of the line. Never mind that earth had no deep-space dreadknots or
ambassadorial spaceships. Easy as hadn't existed either before firefall. Nobody had told us of
any such contingent, but you never show the big picture to your front line. The less they know,
the less they can betray. I still don't know if the fourth wave ever existed. I never saw any
evidence of one, for whatever that's worth. We might have left them floundering back at Burns
Caulfield, or maybe they followed us all the way to Big Ben, crept just close enough to see what
we were up against and turn tail before things got ugly. I wonder if that's what happened. I wonder
if they made it back home. I look back now and hope not. A giant marshmallow kicked theseus in the
side, down and swung like a pendulum. Across the drum spindle, yelped as if scalded, in the galley,
a cracking a bulb of hot coffee. I nearly was. This is it, I thought. We got too close. They're
hitting back. What the... A flicker on the party line as baits linked from the bridge.
Main drive just kicked in. We're changing course.
To what? Where? Whose orders? Mine, Sudasti said, appearing above us.
Nobody spoke, drifting into the drum through the stern hatchway, the sound of something grinding.
I pinged Theseus' resource allocation stack. Fabrication was retooling itself for the mass
production of doped ceramics. Radiation shielding. Solid stuff, bulky and primitive,
not the controlled magnetic fields we usually relied on. The game emerged, sleepy-eye from their
tent, Sasha grumbling. What the fuck? Watch. Sudasti took hold of consensus and shook it.
It was a blizzard, not a briefing. Gravity wells and orbital trajectories,
sheer stress simulations in thunderheads of ammonium and hydrogen, stereoscopic
planetscapes buried under filters ranging from gamma to radio. I saw breakpoints and
saddle points and unstable equilibria. I saw fold catastrophes plotted in five dimensions.
My augments strained to rotate the information. My meaty half-brain struggled to understand
the bottom line. Something was hiding down there, in plain sight. Ben's accretion belt wasn't
misbehaving. Its delinquency wasn't obvious, Sudasti hadn't had to plot every pebble and
mountain and planetesimal to find the pattern, but he'd come close. And neither he nor the
conjoined intelligence he shared with the captain had been able to explain those trajectories as
the mere aftermath of some past disturbance. The dust wasn't just settling, some of it marched
down hill to the beat of something that even now reached out from the cloud tops and pulled debris
from orbit. Not all that debris seemed to hit. Ben's equatorial regions flickered constantly
with the light of meteorite impacts, much fainter than the bright wakes of the skimmers and gone in
the wink of an eye, but those frequency distributions didn't quite account for all the rocks that had
fallen. He was almost as though every now and then some piece of incoming detris simply vanished
into a parallel universe, or got caught by something in this one. Something that circled Ben's equator
every 40 hours, almost low enough to graze the atmosphere. Something that didn't show up in
visible light or infrared or radar. Something that might have remained pure hypothesis if a skimmer
hadn't burned an incandescent trail across the atmosphere behind it when the easiest it happened
to be watching. Sudasti threw that one dead center, a bright contrail streaking diagonally across Ben's
perpetual nightscape, stuttering partway a degree or two to the left, stuttering back just
before it passed from sight. Freeze frame showed a beam of light frozen solid, a segment snapped
from its midsection and jiggled just a hair out of alignment. A segment nine kilometers long.
It's cloaked, Sasha said, impressed. Not very well. Bates emerged from the forward hatch and
stailed spinward. Pretty obvious refactory artifact. She caught stairs halfway to the deck,
used the torque of spin against spam to flip upright and plant her feet on the steps.
Why didn't we catch that before? No backlight, spindle suggested. It's not just the contrail,
look at the clouds. Sure enough, Ben's cloudy backdrop showed the same subtle dislocation.
Bates stepped onto the deck and headed for the conference table. We should have seen this earlier.
The other probes see no such artifact, Sudasti said. This probe approaches from a wider angle,
27 degrees. Wider angle to what? Sasha said. To the line, Bates murmured, between us and them.
It was all there on tactical. The easiest fell inwards along an obvious arc, but the probes
weren't, we dispatched, hadn't dicked around with the Hohmann transfers. They'd burnt straight down,
their courses barely bending, all within a few degrees of the theoretical line connecting Ben
Dethesius. Except this one. This one had come in wide and seen a trickery. The further our bearing,
the more obvious the discontinuity, Sudasti intoned. I think it's clearly visible on any
approach perpendicular to ours. So we're in a blind spot. We see it if we change course.
Bates shook her head. The blind spot's moving, Sasha. It's... tracking us.
Sasha sucked breath between her teeth. Motherfucker! Spindle twitched. So what is it, our skimmer factory?
The freeze frame's pixels began to crawl. Something emerged, granular and indistinct,
from the turbulent swirls and curlicues of Ben's atmosphere. There were curves and spikes and no
smooth edges. I couldn't tell how much of the shape was real and how much of fractal intrusion
of underlying cloudscape. But the overall outline was that of a torus, or perhaps a collection of
smaller jagged things piled together in a rough ring and it was big. Those nine clicks of displaced
contrail had merely grazed the perimeter, cut across an arc of 40 or 50 degrees. The thing
hiding in the shadow of 10 Jupiters was almost 30 kilometers from side to side.
Sometime during Sadasti's executive summary we'd stopped accelerating. Down was back where it
belonged. We weren't, though. Our hesitant maybe-maybe-not approach was a thing of the past. We vectored
straight in now and damned the torpedoes.
Uh, that's 30 clicks across, Sasha pointed out. And it's invisible. Shouldn't we maybe be a little
more cautious now? Spindle shrugged. We could second-guess vampires. We wouldn't need vampires,
eh? A new facet bloomed of the feed. Frequency histograms and a harmonic spectra erupted into
flatline into shifting mountain scapes. A chorus of visible light.
Modulated laser, Bates reported. Spindle looked up. From that? Bates nodded.
Right after we blow its cover. Interesting timing.
Scary timing, Spindle said. How'd it know? We changed course. We're heading right for it.
The lightscape played on, knocking at the window.
Whatever it is, Bates said. It's talking to us.
Well then, remarked a welcome voice. By all means, let's say hello. Susan James was back in the
driver's seat. I was the only peer spectator. They all performed what duties they couldn't.
Spindle ran Sadasti's sketchy silhouette through a series of filters,
perchance to squeeze a bit of biology from engineering. Bates compared morphometrics between
the cloaked artifact and the skimmers. Sadasti watched us all from overhead and thought vampire
thoughts deeper than anything we could aspire to. But it was all just make work. The gang of four
was on center stage, under the capable direction of Susan James. She grabbed the nearest chair,
sat, raised her hands as if queuing an orchestra. Her fingers trembled in midair as she played
virtual icons. Her lips and jaw twitched with subvocal commands. I tapped her feet and saw a text
decreting around the alien signal. Rorschach to vessel approaching 116 degrees azimuth,
negative 20 degrees declination relative. Hello, Thezius. Rorschach to vessel approaching 116
degrees azimuth, negative 23 degrees declination relative. Hello, Thezius. Rorschach to vessel
approaching 116 degrees azimuth, she decoded the damn thing already. She was even answering it.
Thezius to Rorschach. Hello, Rorschach. Hello, Thezius. Welcome to the neighborhood.
She'd had less than three minutes, or rather they'd had less than three minutes,
four fully conscious hub personalities and a few dozen unconscious semiotic modules all working in
parallel all exquisitely carved from the same lump of gray matter. I could almost see why someone
would do such deliberate violence to their own minds if it resulted in this kind of performance.
Up until now I had never convinced myself that even survival was sufficient cause.
Request permission to approach, the gang sent. Simple and straightforward, just facts and data
thank you with as little room as possible for ambiguity and misunderstanding. Fancy sentiments
like we come in peace could wait. A handshake was not the time for cultural exchange. You should
stay away. Seriously. This place is dangerous. That got some attention. Bates and Spindle
hesitated momentarily in their own head spaces and glanced into James. Request information on danger,
the gang sent back. Still keeping it concrete. Too close and dangerous to you. Low orbit
complications. Request information on low orbit complications. Lethal environment. Rocks and
rads. You're welcome. I can take it but we're like that. We are aware of the rocks in low orbit.
We are equipped to deal with radiation. Request information on other hazards. I dug under the
transcript to the channel if fed from. Theseus had turned part of the incoming beam into a sound
wave according to the color code. Vocal communication then. They spoke. Waiting behind that icon where
the raw sounds of an alien language. Of course I couldn't resist. Anytime between friends right?
Are you here for the celebration? English. The voice was human. Male. Old.
We're here to explore. Replied the gang. Although their voice was pure athesias. Request dialogue
with agents who sent objects into near solar space. First contact. Sounds like something to
celebrate. I double check the source. No this wasn't a translation. This was the actual unprocessed
signal coming from Rorschach. It had called itself. Part of the signal anyway. There were
other elements. Nonacoustic ones encoding in the beam. I browsed them while James said. Request
information about your celebration. Standard ship to ship hand taking protocols. You're interested.
The voice was stronger now. Younger. Yes. You are? Yes. The gang repeated patiently. You are?
The slightest hesitation. This athesias. I know that baseline. In Mandarin now. Who are you?
No obvious change in the harmonics. Somehow though the voice seemed to have acquired an edge.
This is Susan James. I am a... You wouldn't be happy here Susan. Fetishistic religious beliefs
involved. There are dangerous observances. James chewed her lip. Request clarification.
Are we in danger from these observances? You certainly could be. Request clarification.
Is it the observances that are dangerous or the low orbit environment? The environment of the
disturbances. You should pay attention Susan. Inattention connotes indifference, Rorschach said.
Or disrespect. It added after a moment.
We had four hours before Ben got in the way. Four hours of uninterrupted nonstop communication made
vastly easier than anyone had expected. It spoke our language after all. Repeatedly it expressed
polite concern for our welfare. And yet for all its facility with human speech it told us very little.
For four hours it managed to avoid giving a straight answer on any subject beyond the
extreme inadvisability of closer contact. And by the time it fell into eclipse we still didn't know why.
Sadasti dropped onto the deck halfway through the exchange, his feet never touching the stairs.
He reached out and grabbed a railing to steady himself on landing and staggered only briefly.
If I tried that I'd have ended up bouncing along the deck like a pebble in a cement mixer.
He stood still as stone for the rest of the session,
face motionless, eyes hidden behind his onyx visor. When Rorschach's signal faded in mid-sentence
he assembled us around the commons table with a gesture.
It talks, he said. James nodded. It doesn't say much except for asking us to keep our distance.
So far the voice has manifested as an adult male although the apparent age changed a few times.
He'd heard all that. Structure? The ship-to-ship protocols are perfect. Its vocabulary is far
greater than you could derive from standard nav chatter between a few ships so they've been
listening to all our in-system traffic I'd say for several years at least. On the other hand the
vocabulary doesn't have anywhere near the range you'd get by monitoring entertainment multimed so
they probably arrived after the broadcast age. How well do they use the vocabulary they have?
They're using phase structure grammar, long distance dependencies,
FLN recursion, at least four levels deep and I see no reason why won't go deeper with continued
contact. They're not parrots, Yuka. They know the rules. That name for instance. Rorschach,
Bates murmured, Knuckles cracking as she squeezed her pet ball. Interesting choice.
I checked the registry. There's an I-CAN freighter called Rorschach on the Martian loop. Whoever
we're talking to must regard their own platform the way we regard a ship and pick one of our names
to fit. Spinzel dropped into the chair beside me fresh from a galley run. A bulb of coffee glistened
like jelly in his hand. That name out of all ships in the intersist seems way too symbolic for random
choice. I don't think it was random. Unusual ship names promote Comet. Rorschach's pilot goes
ship to ship with some other vessel. The other vessel comes back with, oh grandma what an unusual
name you have. Rorschach replies with some off the cuff comment about non-clam- nominclature
origins and it all goes out in the e.m. Someone listening to all that chatter not only figures
out the name and the thing it applies to but can get some sense of meaning from the context.
Our alien friends probably easily dropped on half the registry and deduced that Rorschach
could be a better tag for someone unfamiliar than say the SS Jamie Matthews. Territorial and smart,
Spindle grimaced, conjuring a mug from beneath his chair. Wonderful. Bates shrugged.
Territorial maybe. Not necessarily aggressive. In fact I wonder if they could even hurt us if they
wanted to. I don't, Spindle said. Those skimmers. The major wave to dismissive hand. Big ships turn
slowly. If they were setting up to snooker us we'd see it well in advance. She looked around the table.
Look am I the only one who finds this odd an interstellar technology that redecorates super
Jovians and lines up meteoroids like elephants on parade and they were hiding from us? Unless there's
someone else out here, James suggested uneasily. Bates shook her head. The cloak was directional.
It was aimed at us and no one else. And even we saw through it, Spindle added. Exactly. So they go to
Plan B which so far amounts to nothing but bluster and vague warnings. I'm just saying they're not
acting like giants. Rorschach's behavior feels improvised. I don't think they expected us.
Of course not. Burns Caulfield was, I don't think they expected us yet.
Um, Spindle said, digesting it. The major ran one hand over her naked scalp.
Why would they expect us to just give up after we learned we'd been sniped? Of course we'd look
elsewhere. Burns Caulfield could only have intended as a delaying action. If I was them,
I'd plan on us getting out here eventually. But I think they miscalculated somehow. We got out here
sooner than they expected and caught them with their pants down. Spindle split the bowl but
emptied it into his mug. Pretty large miscalculation for something so smart, eh? A hologram bloomed on
contact with the steaming liquid, glowing in soft commemoration of the gods of glasslands.
The scent of plasticized coffee flooded the commons. Especially after they surveilled us
down to the square meter, he added. And what did they see? Icans. Solar sails. Ships that take
years to reach the Kuiper and don't have the reserves to go anywhere else afterwards. Telematter
didn't exist beyond bowing simulators and half a dozen prototypes back then. Easy to miss. They
must have figured one decoy would buy them all the time they needed. To do what, James wondered.
Whatever it is, Bates said, we're ringside. Spindle raised his mug with an infirm hand and sift.
The coffee trembled in its prison, the surface wobbling and blobbing in the drums half-hearted
gravity. James pursed her lips in faint disapproval. Open top containers for liquids were technically
verboten in variable gravity environments, even for people without spindle's dexterity issues.
So they're bluffing, Spindle said at last. Bates nodded. That's my guess. Rorschach's still under
construction. We could be dealing with an automated system of some kind. So we can ignore the keep
off the grass signs, eh? Walk right in. We can afford to bite our time. We can afford to not push it.
Ah, so even though you could maybe handle it now, you want to wait until it graduates from
covert to invulnerable. Spindle shuddered, set down his coffee. Where'd you get your military
training again, Sporting Chance Academy? Bates ignored the jibe. The fact that Rorschach's
still growing may be the best reason to leave it alone for a while. We don't have any idea what the
mature, I guess, what the mature form of this artifact might be. Sure, it hid. Lots of animals
take cover from predators without being predators, especially young ones. Sure, it's evasive. Doesn't
give us the answers we want. But maybe it doesn't know them. Did you consider that? How much luck
would you have interrogating a human embryo? Adult could be a whole different animal. Adult could
put our asses through a meat grinder. So could the embryo, for all we know. Bates rolled her eyes.
Jesus, Isaac, you're the biologist. I shouldn't have to tell you how many shy, reclusive critters
pack a punch when they're cornered. Porcupine doesn't want any trouble, but he'll still give you a
faceful of quills if you ignore the warning. Spindle said nothing. He slid his coffee sideways
along the concave tabletop to the very limit of his reach. The liquid sat there in the mug,
a dark circle perfectly parallel to the rim, but canted slightly towards us. I thought I could
make out even the merest convexivity in the surface itself. Spindle smiled faintly at the effect.
James cleared her throat. Not to downplay your concerns, Isaac, but we've hardly exhausted
the diplomatic route. At least it's willing to talk, even if it's not as forthcoming as we'd like.
Sure it talks, Spindle said. Eyes still leaning on the mug. Not like us. Well, no, there's some...
It's not just slippery. It's downright dyslexic sometimes, you noticed, and it mixes up its
pronouns. Given that it picked up the language entirely via passive eavesdropping, it's remarkably
fluent. In fact, from what I can tell, they're more efficient at processing speech than we are.
Gotta be efficient at the language if you're gonna be so evasive in it, eh?
If they were human, I might agree with you, James replied. But what appears to us as evasion or
deceit could just as easily be explained by reliance on smaller conceptual units.
Conceptual units? Bates, I was beginning to realize, never pulled up a subtitle if she could help it.
James nodded. Like processing a line of text word by word instead of looking at complete phrases,
the smaller the units, the faster they can be reconfigured. It gives you very fast semantic
reflexes. The downside is that it's difficult to maintain the same level of logical consistency
since the patterns within the larger structure are more likely to get shuffled.
Whoa. Spindle straightened, all thoughts of liquids and centipital force forgotten.
All I'm saying is we aren't necessarily dealing with deliberate deception here.
An entity who parses information at one scale might not be aware of inconsistencies at another.
It might not even have a conscious access to that level. That's not all you're saying. Isaac,
you can't apply human norms to a- I wondered what you were up to. Spindle drove into the
transcripts. A moment later he dredged up an excerpt. Request information on environments you
consider lethal. Request information on your response to the prospect of imminent exposure
to lethal environments. Glad to comply, but your lethal is different from us. There are many
migrating circumstances. You were testing it, Spindle crowed. He smacked his lips, his jaw ticked.
You were looking for an emotional response. It was just a thought. It didn't prove anything.
Was there a difference in the response time? James hesitated, then shook her head.
But it was a stupid idea. There are so many variables. We have no idea how they- I mean,
they're alien. The pathology is classic. What pathology? I asked. It doesn't mean anything
except they're different from the human baseline, James insisted, which is not something anyone
here can look down their nose about. I tried again. What pathology? James shook her head.
Spindle filled me in. There's a syndrome you might have heard about, eh? Fast talkers, no
conscience, tend to malopropism and self-contradiction, no emotional affect. We're not talking about
human beings here, James said again softly. But if we were, Spindle added, we might call Rorschach
a clinical sociopath. Sodosti had said nothing during the entire exchange. Now with the word
hanging out in the open, I noticed that nobody else would look at him.
We all knew that Yuka Sodosti was a sociopath, of course. Most of us just didn't mention it in
polite company. Spindle was never that polite. Or maybe it was just that he seemed to almost
understand Sodosti. He could look behind the monster and regard the organism, no less the
product of natural selection for all the human flesh it had devoured in Eon's past.
That perspective calmed him somehow. He could watch Sodosti watching him and not flinch.
I feel sorry for the poor son of a bitch, he said once back in training.
Some would have thought that absurd. This man so massively interfaced with machinery that his
own motor skills had degraded for want of proper care and feeding. This man who heard x-rays and
saw in shades of ultrasound, so corrupted by retrofits he could no longer even feel his own
fingertips without assistance. This man could pity anyone else.
Let alone an infra-eyed predator built to murder without the slightest twitch of remorse.
Empathy for sociopaths isn't common, I remarked.
Maybe it should be. We, at least. He waved an arm, some remote-length sensor cluster,
crossed the simulator, whirred and torqued reflexively, chose the add-ons. Vampires had to
be sociopaths. They're too much like their own prey. A lot of taxonomists don't even consider them
a subspecies, you know that? Never diverged far enough for complete reproductive isolation.
So maybe they're more syndrome than race. Just a bunch of obligate cannibals with a sense of
consistent deformities. And how does that make... if the only thing that you can eat is your own kind,
empathy is going to be the first thing that goes. Psychopathies no disorder in those shoes,
eh? Just survival strategy. But they still make our skin crawl, so we chain them up.
You think we should have repaired the crucifix glitch? Everyone knew why we hadn't. Only a
fooled, resurrected monster without safeguards in place. Vampires came with theirs built in.
Without his anti-euclidean, Serosti would go grand maul in the first thing he caught close sight
of the four-panel window frame. But Spindle was shaking his head. We couldn't have fixed it,
or we could have, he amended. But the glitch is in the visual cortex, eh? Linked to Omni-Savantism.
You fix it, you disable their pattern-matching skills, and then what's even the point of
bringing them back? I didn't know that. Well, that's the official story. He fell silent for a moment,
cracked a crooked grin. Then again, we didn't have any trouble fixing the
Proto-Cadiran pathways when it suited us. I subtitled.
Context-sensitive consensus served up Proto-Cadiran-Y, the magical hominid brain protein that vampires
had never been able to synthesize. The reason they hadn't just switched to zebras or warthogs
once denied human prey. Why our discovery of the terrible secret of the right angle had
spelled their doom. Anyway, I just think he's cut off. A nervous tick tugged at the corner of
Spindle's mouth. Lone wolf, nothing but sheep for company. Wouldn't you feel lonely? They don't like
company, I reminded him. You didn't put vampires of the same sex together, not unless you were
taking bets on a bloodbath. They were solitary hunters and very territorial. With a minimum
viable pred-prey ratio of one to ten, and human prey spread so sparsely across the Pliastocene
landscape, the biggest threat to their survival had been competition from their own kind.
Natural selection had never taught them to play nicely together.
That didn't cut any ice with Spindle, though. Doesn't mean he can't be lonely, he insisted.
Just means he can't fix it.
They know the music, but not the words. Hair without conscience.
We did it with mirrors. Great round parabolic things, each impossibly thin and three times as
high as a man. Theseus rolled them up and bolted them to firecrackers, stuffed with precious
antimatter from our dwindling stockpiles. With twelve hours to spare, she flung them like confetti
along precise ballistic trajectories. And when they were safely distant, she set them alight.
They pinwheeled off every which way, gamma-sleeting in their wake until they burned dry. Then they
coasted, unfurling, mercurial insect wings across the void. In the greater distance,
400,000 alien machines looped and burned and took no obvious notice.
Rorschach fell around a bend barely 1500 kilometers from atmosphere, a fast, endless circle that took
just under 40 hours to complete. By the time it didn't return to our sight, our mirrors were all
outside the zone of total blindness. A close-up of Ben's equatorial edge floated in consensus.
Mirror icons sparkled around it like an exploding schematic, like the disconnected facets of some
great expanding compound eye. None had breaks. Whatever high ground the mirrors held, they
wouldn't hold it for long. There, Bates said. A mirage wavered stage left, a tiny spot of swirling
chaos, perhaps half the size of a fingernail, held an arm's length. It told us nothing. It was pure
heat shimmer. But light bounced towards us some dozens of relayers. And while we each saw scarcely
more than our last probe had, a patch of dark clouds set slightly awry by some invisible prism,
each of these views refracted differently. The captain sieved flashes from the heavens and
stitched them into a composite view. Details emerged. First, a faint sliver of shadow, a tiny dimple
all but lost in the seething equatorial cloud bands. It had just barely rotated into view around
the edge of the disk, a rock in the stream, perhaps, an invisible finger stuck in the clouds,
turbulence and sheer stress shredding the boundary layers to either side. Spindle squinted. Plage
effect. Subtitle said he was talking about a kind of sunspot, a knot in Ben's magnetic field.
Higher, James said. Something floated above that dimple in the clouds, the way a ground effect
ocean liner floats above the depression it pushes into the water's surface. I zoomed. Next to an
oasis subdwarf with ten times the mass of Jupiter, Rorschach was tiny. Next to Thesias, it was a
colossus. Not just a torus but a tangle, a city-sized chaos of spun glass, loops and bridges and
a tenuette spires. The surface texture was pure artifice, of course. Consensus merely gift wrapped
the enigma and refracted background. Still, in some dark haunting way it was almost beautiful.
A nest of obsidian snakes and smoky crystalline spines.
It's talking again, James reported. Talk back, Sodosti said, and abandoned us.
So she did, and while the gang spoke with the artifact, the others spied upon it.
Their vision failed over time, mirrors fell away along their respective vectors, lines of
sight degraded with each passing second, but consensus filled with things learned in the meantime.
Rorschach massed 1.8 times 10 to the 10th kilograms with a total volume of 2.3 times 10 to the 8th
cubic meters. Its magnetic field, judging by radio squeals and its plage effect, was thousands of
times stronger than the sun's. Astonishingly, parts of the composite image were clear enough to discern
fine spiral grooves twined around the structure. Fibonacci sequence, Spindle reported. One jiggling
eye fixing me for a moment. At least they're not completely alien. Spheroid protuberances
disfigured the tips of at least three of Rorschach's innumerable spines. The grooves were more widely
spaced in those areas, like skin grown tight and swollen with infection. Just before one vital
mirror sailed out of range, it glimpsed another spine, split a third of the way along its length.
Torn material floated flaccid and unmoving in the vacuum.
Please, Bates said softly. Tell me that's not what it looks like.
Spindle grinned. Sporangium? Seed pod? Why not?
Rorschach may have been reproducing, but beyond a doubt it was growing,
fed by a steady trickle of in-falling debris from Ben's accretion belt.
We were close enough now to get a clear view of that procession.
Rocks and mountains and pebbles fell like sediments swirling around a drain.
Particles that collided with the artifact simply stuck. Rorschach engulfed prey like some vast
metastic amoeba. The acquired mass was apparently processed internally and shunted to atypical
growth zones. Judging by infinitesimal changes in the artifact's alimetry, it grew from the tips of
its branches. The procession never stopped. Rorschach was insatiable. It was a strange
attractor in the interstellar gulf, the paths along which the rocks fell were precisely and utterly
chaotic. It was as though some Keplerian black belt had set up the whole system like an astronomical
wind-up toy, kicked everything into motion, and let inertia do the rest.
Didn't think that was possible, Bates said. Spindle shrugged.
Hey, chaotic trajectories are just as deterministic as any other kind.
That doesn't mean you can even predict them, let along set them up like that.
Luminous intel reflected off the major's bald head. You have to know the starting conditions
of a million different variables to ten decimal places, literally. Yep. Vampires can't do that.
Quantical computers can't do that. Spindle shrugged like a marionette.
All the while the gang had been slipping in and out of character, dancing with some unseen partner
that, despite their best efforts, told us little beyond endless permutations of,
you really wouldn't like it here. Any interrogative it answered with another, yet somehow it left
the sense of questions answered. Did you send the fireflies? Sasha asked.
We send many things many places, Rorschach replied. What did their specs show?
We do not know their specifications. The fireflies burned up over Earth.
Then shouldn't you be looking there? When our kids fly, they're on their own.
Sasha muted the channel. You know who we're talking to? Jesus of fucking Nazareth, that's who.
Spindle looked at Bates. Bates shrugged, palms up.
You didn't get it? Sasha shook her head. That last exchange was the informational equivalent of
should we render taxes unto Caesar. Beat for beat. Thanks for casting us at the Pharisees,
Spindle grumbled. Hey, if the Jew fits, Spindle rolled his eyes.
That was when I first noticed it. A tiny imperfection in Sasha's topology, a fly speck of doubt marring
one of her facets. We're not getting anywhere, she said. Let's try a side door. She winked out.
Michelle reopened the outgoing line. These is to Rorschach, open to requests for information.
Cultural exchange, Rorschach said. That works for me.
Bates' brow furrowed. Is that wise? If it's not inclined to give information, maybe it would
rather get some. We could learn a great deal from the kind of question it asks. But tell us about
home, Rorschach said. Sasha resurfaced just long enough to say, relax, major. Nobody said we had
to give it the right answers. The stain on the gang's topology had flickered when Michelle took
over, but it hadn't disappeared. It grew slightly as Michelle described some hypothetical hometown
in careful terms that mentioned no object smaller than a meter across. Consensus confirmed, my guess,
the hypothetical limit of firefly eyesight. When Cruncher took a rare turn at the helm.
We don't all of us have parents or cousins. Some never did. Some come from vats.
I see. That's sad. Vats sound so dehumanizing. The stain darkened and spread across his surface
like an oil slick. Takes too much on faith, Susan said a moment later. By the time Sasha had
cycled back into Michelle, it was more than doubt, stronger than suspicion. It had become an insight,
a dark little meme infecting each of the body's minds in turn. The gang was on the trail of
something. They still weren't sure what. I was. Tell me more about your cousins, Rorschach sent.
Our cousins lie about the family tree, Sasha replied. With nieces and nephews and neanderthals,
we do not like annoying cousins. We'd like to know more about this tree.
Sasha muted the channel and gave us a look that said could it be any more obvious?
It couldn't have parsed that. There were three linguistic ambiguities in there. It just ignored
them. Well, it asked for clarification, Bates pointed out. It asked a follow-up question,
different thing entirely. Bates was still out of the loop. Spindle was starting to get it, though.
Subtle motion drew my eye. Sonosty was back, floating above the bright topography on the table.
The light show squirmed across his visor as he moved his head. I could feel his eyes behind it.
And something else behind him. I couldn't tell what it was. I could point to nothing but
a vague sense of something out of place, somewhere in the background. Something over on the far side
of the drum wasn't quite right. No, that wasn't it. Something nearer. Something amiss somewhere
along the drum's axis. But there was nothing there, nothing I could see, just the naked pipes and
conduits of the spinal bundle, threading through empty space and... and suddenly whatever had
been wrong was right again. That was what finally locked my focus, the evaporation of some anomaly.
A reversion to normalcy that caught my eye like a flicker of motion.
I could see the exact spot along the bundle where the change had occurred. There was nothing out of
place that I could see now, but there had been. It was in my head, barely subliminal, an itch so
close to the surface that I knew I could bring it back if I just concentrated. Sasha was talking to
some alien artifact at the end of a laser beam. She was going on about familial relationships,
both evolutionary and domestic. Neanderthal and Cro Magnin and Mother's Cousins twice removed.
She'd been doing it for hours now, and she had hours yet to go, but right now her chatter was
distracting me. I tried to block her out and concentrate on the half-perceived image teasing
my memory. I'd seen something there just a moment ago. One of the conduits had... yes,
too many joints on one of the pipes. Something that should have been straight and smooth but
was somehow articulated instead. But not one of the pipes, I remembered. An extra pipe. An extra
something anyway. Something bony. That was crazy. There was nothing there. We were half a light
year from home talking to unseen aliens about family reunions and my eyes were playing tricks on me.
Have to talk to Spindle about that if it happened again.
A lull in the background chatter brought me back. Spindle had... stopped talking.
Darkened facets hung around her like a thunder cloud. I pulled the last thing she said. We usually
found our nephews with telescopes. They are as hard as hoblinites. More calculated ambiguity,
and hoblinites wasn't even a word. Imminent decisions reflected in her eyes.
Sasha was poised at the edge of a precipice, gauging the depth of dark waters below.
You haven't mentioned your father at all, Rorschach remarked.
That's true, Rorschach. Sasha had admitted softly, taking a breath and stepping forward.
So why don't you just suck my big fat hairy dick?
The drum fell instantly silent. Bates and Spindle stared open mouth.
Sasha killed the channel and turned to face us, grinning so widely I thought the top of her
head would fall off. Sasha, Bates breathed. Are you crazy? So what if I am? Doesn't matter that
thing. It doesn't have a clue what I'm saying. What? It doesn't even have a clue. What it's saying
back, she added. Wait a minute, you said—Susan said they weren't parrots, they knew the rules.
And there Susan was, melting to the fore. I did, and they do, but pattern matching doesn't equal
comprehension. Bates shook her head. You said whatever we're talking to, it's not even intelligent?
Oh, it could be intelligent, certainly, but we're not talking to it in any meaningful sense.
So what is it, voicemail?
Actually, Spindle said slowly, I think they call it a Chinese room. About bloody time, I thought.
I knew all about Chinese rooms. I was one. I didn't even keep it a secret. I told anyone who was
interested enough to ask. In hindsight, sometimes that was a mistake. How can you possibly tell the
rest of us what you're bleeding edges up to if you don't understand it yourself?
Chelsea demanded back when things were good between us, before she got to know me.
I shrugged. It's not my job to understand them. If I could, they wouldn't be very bleeding edge
in the first place. I'm just, you know, a conduit. Yeah, but how can you translate something if you
don't understand it? A common cry outside the field. People simply can't accept that patterns
carry their own intelligence, quite apart from the semantic content that clings to their services,
if you manipulate the topology correctly, that content just comes along for the ride.
You ever hear of the Chinese room? I asked. She shook her head. Only vaguely. Really all, right?
Hundred years at least. It's a fallacy, really. It's an argument that supposedly puts the lie
deterring tests. You stick some guy in a closed room, sheets with strange squiggles come in through
a slot in the wall. You've got access to this huge database of squiggles just like it, and a bunch
of rules to tell him how to put those squiggles together. Grammar, Chelsea said, syntax. I nodded.
The point is, though, he doesn't have any idea what the squiggles are or what information they
contain. He only knows that when he encounters squiggle delta, he's supposed to extract the
fifth and sixth squiggles from the file theta and put them back together with another squiggle from
gamma. So he builds this response string, puts it on the sheet, slides it back out the slot and
takes a nap until the next iteration. Repeat until the remains of the horse are well and thoroughly
beaten. So he's carrying on a conversation, Chelsea said. In Chinese, I assume, or they would have
called it the Spanish Inquisition. Exactly. Point being, you can use basic pattern matching algorithms
to participate in a conversation without having any idea what you're saying. Depending on how
good the rules are, you can pass a Turing test. You can be a wit and wreck on tour in a language
you don't even speak. That's synthesis? Only the part that involves downscaling semiotic protocols
and only in principle. And I'm actually getting my input in Cantonese and replying in German,
because I'm more of a conduit than a conversant, but you get the idea. How do you keep all the
rules and protocols straight? There must be millions of them. It's like anything else,
once you learn the rules, you do it unconsciously, like riding a bike or pinging the new sphere.
You don't actively think about the protocols at all, you just imagine how your targets behave.
A subtle half-smile played at the corner of her mouth. But the argument's not really a fallacy,
then is it? It's spot on. You really don't understand Cantonese or German.
The system understands. The whole room, with all its parts. The guy who does the scribbling is just
one component. You wouldn't expect a single neuron in your head to understand English, would you?
Sometimes one's all I can spare, Chelsea shook her head. She wasn't going to let it go.
I could see her sorting questions in order of priority. I could see them getting increasingly
personal. To get back to the matter at hand, I said, preempting them all. You were going to show
me how to do that thing with the fingers. A wicked grin swiped or wiped the questions off her face.
Oh, that's right. It's risky getting involved. Too many confounds. Every tool in the shed goes
dull and rusty the moment you get entangled with the system you're observing. Still serviceable
in the pinch, though.
It hides now, Sadasti said. It's vulnerable now. Now we go in. It wasn't news so much as review.
We've been straight-lining towards Ben for days now, but perhaps the Chinese room hypothesis
had strengthened his resolve. At any rate, with war shock and eclipse once more, we were prepared
to take intrusiveness to the next level. Theseus was perpetually gravid, a generic probe incubated
in her fabrication plant. Its development arrested just short of the birth of anticipation of
unforeseen mission requirements. Sometime between briefings, the captain had brought it to
part tuition, customized for close contact and groundwork. It burned down the well at high G
a good 10 hours before war shock's next scheduled appearance, inserted itself into the rock string,
and went to sleep. If our calculations were in order, it would not be smashed by some errant
piece of debris before it woke up again. If all went well, an intelligence that had precisely
orchestrated a cast of millions would not notice one extra dancer on the floor. If we were just
plain lucky, the myriad high divers that happened to be a line of sight at the time were not programmed
as tattletales. Acceptable risks. If we hadn't been up for them, we might as well have stayed home.
And so we waited. Four optimized hybrids somewhere past the threshold of mere humanity,
one extinct predator who'd opted to command us instead of eating us alive.
We waited for war shock to come back around the bend. The probes fell smoothly around the well,
an ambassador to the unwilling. Or if the gang was right, maybe just a backdoor artist set to
a B&E and empty condo. Spindle had named it Jack in a Box after some antique child's toy that
didn't even rate a listing in consensus. We fell in its wake, nearly ballistic now. Momentum and
inertia carefully pre-calculated to thread us through the chaotic minefield of Ben's accretion
belt. Kepler couldn't do it all, though. Thesias grumbled briefly now and then, the intermittent
firing of her attitude jets rumbling softly up the spine as the captain tweaked our descent into
the maelstrom. No plan ever survives first contact with the enemy, I remembered. But I didn't know
from where. Got it, Bates said. A speck appeared at Ben's edge. The display zoomed instantly to
close up. Proximity boot. Roar shock remained invisible to Thesias, close as we were, close as
we were to coming. But parallax stripped at least some of the scales in the probes' eyes.
It woke to spikes and spirals of smoky glass flickering in and out of view.
Ben's flat endless horizon sent me visible through the inter-reading translucent.
The view trembled. Waveforms rippled across consensus.
Quite the mechantic field, Spindle remarked.
Breaking, Bates reported. Jack turned slowly retrograde and fired its torch. On tactical,
Delta Veef swung to red. Sasha was driving the gang's body this shift.
Incoming signal, she recorded. Same format.
Sudosti clicked. Biped.
Roar shocked Thesias.
Hello again, Thesias. The voice was female this time and middle-aged.
Sasha grinned.
See? She's not offended at all. Big hairy dick, notwithstanding.
Don't answer, Sudosti said.
Burn complete, Bates supported.
Coasting now, Jack sneezed.
Silver chaff shot into the void towards the target. Millions of compass needles,
brilliantly reflective, fast enough to make Thesias seem slow. They were gone in an instant.
The probe watched them flee, swept laser eyes across every degree of arc, scanned its sky
twice a second, and took careful note of each and every reflective flash.
Only at first did those needles shoot anything along approaching a straight line.
Then they swept abruptly into lorant spirals, twisting into sudden arcs and corkscrews,
shot away along new and intricate trajectories bordering on the relativistic.
The contours of Rorschach's magnetic field resolved in consensus,
at first glance looking like nested layers of a glass onion.
Sprawling, Spindle said.
At second glance, the onion grew wormy.
Invignations appeared, long snaking tunnels of energy proliferating fractally at every side.
Roar shocked Thesias.
Hello, Thesias. You there?
A holographic inset beside the main display plotted the points of a triangle in flux.
Thesias at the apex, Rorschach and Jack defining the narrow base.
Rorschach to Thesias. I see you.
She's got a more casual affect than he ever did.
Sasha glanced up at Sotosti and did not add, you sure about this?
She was starting to wonder herself, though.
Starting to dwell on the potential consequences of being wrong now that we were committed.
As far as sober second thought was concerned, it was too little, too late.
But for Sasha, that was progress.
Besides, it had been Sotosti's decision.
Great hoops were resolving in Rorschach's magnetosphere.
Invisible to human eyes, their outlines were vanishingly faint even on tactical.
The chaff had scattered so thinly across the sky that even the captain was resorting to guesswork.
The new macro structures hovered in the magnetosphere like the nested gimbals of some greater phantom gyroscope.
I see you haven't changed your vector, Rorschach remarked.
We really wouldn't advise continuing your approach.
Seriously, for your own safety.
Spindle shook his head.
Hey, Mandy, Rorschach talking to Jack at all?
If it is, I'm not seeing it.
No incident lied, no direct DM of any kind.
She smiled grimly.
Seems to have snuck in under the radar and don't call me Mandy.
Thesias groaned, twisting.
I staggered in the low pseudograph, reaching out to steady myself.
Course correction, baits replied, unplotted rock.
Rorschach to Thesias, please respond.
Your current heading is unacceptable.
Repeat, your current heading is unacceptable.
Strongly advise you change course.
By now the probe coasted just a few kilometers off of Rorschach's leading edge.
That close it served way more than magnetic fields.
It presented Rorschach itself in bright tactical color codes.
Invisible curves and spikes iridesced in consensus across any number of on-demand pigment schemes.
Gravity, reflectivity, black body emissions, massive electrical bolts erupting from the
tips of thorns rendered in lemon pastels.
User-friendly graphics had turned Rorschach into a cartoon.
Rorschach to Thesias, please respond.
Thesias growled to stern fish-tailing.
On tactical, another just-plotted piece of debris swept by a discreet 6000 meters to port.
Rorschach to Thesias, if you are unable to respond, please...
HOLY SHIT!
The cartoon flickered and died.
I'd seen what had happened in the last instant, though.
Jack passing near one of those great phantom hoops.
A tongue of energy flicking out, quick as a frog's.
A dead feed.
I see what you're up to now, you cocksuckers.
Do you think we're fucking blind down here?
Sasha clenched her teeth.
We... no, Sotosti said.
But it fit...
Sotosti hissed from somewhere in the back of his throat.
I had never heard a mammal make a noise quite like that before.
Sasha fell immediately silent.
Bates negotiated with her controls.
I've still got... just a sec.
You pull that thing back right fucking now, you hear us?
Right fucking now!
Got it.
Bates gritted as the feed came back up.
Just had to re-acquire the laser.
The probe and bid kicked wildly off course,
as if someone fording a river had been caught in sudden undertow
and thrown over a waterfall.
But it was still talking and still mobile.
Barely.
Bates struggled to stay the course.
Jack staggered and wobbled uncontrollably
through the tightly wound folds of Rorschach's magnetosphere.
The artifact loomed huge in its view.
The feeds strobed.
Maintain approach, Sotosti said calmly.
Love to, Bates gritted, trying.
Thiesi is skitted again, corkscrewing.
I could have sworn I heard the bearings in the drum grind for a moment.
Another rock sailed past on tactical.
I thought you'd plotted those things, spindle grumbled.
You want to start a war, Thiesius?
Is that what you're trying to do?
You think you're up for it?
It doesn't attack, Sotosti said.
Maybe it does.
Bates kept her voice low.
I could see the effort it took.
If Rorschach can control the trajectory of these,
normal distribution, insignificant corrections,
he must have meant statistically.
The torque and grind of the ship's hull felt pretty significant to the others.
Oh, right, Rorschach said suddenly.
We get it now.
You don't think there's anyone here, do you?
You've got some high-priced consultant telling you there's nothing to worry about.
Jack was deep in the forest.
We'd lost most of the tactical overlays to reduced bod.
In dim visible light, Rorschach's great ridged spines,
each the size of a skyscraper, hash'd a night-veer view on all sides.
The feed stuttered as Bates struggled to keep the beam aligned.
Consensus painted walls and airspace with arcane telemetry.
I had no idea what any of it meant.
You think we're nothing but a Chinese room, Rorschach sneered.
Jack stumbled towards collision, grasping for something to hang onto.
Your mistake, Theseus.
It hit something.
It stuck.
And suddenly Rorschach snapped into view.
No refractory composites.
No profiles or simulations in false color.
There it was at last, naked even to human eyes.
Imagine a crown of thorns, twisted, dark and unreflective,
grown too thickly tangled to ever rest on any human head.
Put in orbit around a failed star whose own reflected half-light
does little more than throw in satellites into silhouette.
Occasional bloody highlights glinted like dim embers from its twists and crannies.
They only emphasize the darkness everywhere else.
Imagine an artifact that embodies the very notion of torture.
Something so wrenched and disfigured that even across uncounted light years
and unimaginable differences in biology and outlook,
you can't help feel that somehow the structure itself is in pain.
Now make it the size of a city.
It flickered as we watched.
Lightning arced from recursed spines a thousand meters long.
Consensus showed us a strobe-lit hellscape, huge and dark and twisted.
The composites had lied.
It was not the least bit beautiful.
Now it's too late, said something from deep inside.
Now every last one of you is dead.
And Susan, you there Susan?
We're taking you first.
Life's too short for chess, Byron.
They never sealed the hatch behind them.
It was too easy to get lost up there in the dome.
Naked infinite space stretching 180 degrees on every axis.
They needed all that emptiness, but they needed an anchor in its midst.
Soft stray light from a stern.
A gentle draft from the drum.
The sounds of people and machinery close by.
They needed to have it both ways.
I lay in wait.
Reading a dozen blatant cues in their behavior,
I was already squirreled away in the forward airlock when they passed.
I gave them a few minutes and crept forward to the darkened bridge.
Of course they called her by name, Spindle was saying.
That was the only name they had, and she told them, remember?
Yes.
Some Michelle didn't seem reassured.
Hey, it was you guys said we were talking to a Chinese room.
You saying you were wrong?
We... no, of course not.
Then it wasn't really threatening, Susan, was it?
It wasn't threatening any of us.
It had no idea what it was saying.
It's rule-based, Isaac.
It was following some kind of flowchart it drew up by observing human languages in action,
and somehow those rules told it to respond with threats of violence.
But if it doesn't even know what it's saying, it doesn't.
It can't.
We parsed the phrasing 19 different ways,
tried out conceptual units of every different length.
A long, deep breath.
But it attacked the probe, Isaac.
Jack just got too close to one of those electrode thingies is all.
It just arched.
So you don't think Rorschach is hostile?
Long silence.
Long enough to make me wonder if I'd been detected.
Hostile, Spindle said at last.
Friendly.
We learn those words for life on Earth, eh?
I don't know if they even apply out here.
Is left smacked faintly.
But I think it might be something like hostile.
Michelle sighed.
Isaac, there's no reason for...
I mean, it just doesn't make sense that it would be.
We can't have anything at once.
It says it wants to be left alone, Spindle said.
Even if it doesn't mean it.
They floated quietly for a while.
Up there past the bulkhead.
At least the shielding held, Spindle said finally.
That's something.
He wasn't just talking about Jack.
Our own carapace was coated with the same stuff now.
It had depleted our substrate stockpiles by two-thirds,
but no one wanted to rely on the ship's usual magnetics
in the face of anything that could play so easily
with the electromagnetic spectrum.
If they attack us, what do we do?
Michelle said.
Learn what we can while we can.
Fight back while we can.
If we can, look out there, Isaac.
I don't care how embryonic that thing is.
Tell me we're not hopelessly outmatched.
Outmatched for sure.
Hopelessly. Never.
That's not what you said before.
Still, there's always a way to win.
If I said that, you'd call it wishful thinking.
If you said that, it would be.
But I'm saying it, so it's game theory.
Game theory again.
Jesus, Isaac.
No, listen.
You're thinking about the aliens
like they were some kind of mammal.
Something that cares.
Something that looks after its investments.
How do you know they aren't?
Because you can't protect your kids
when they're light years away.
They're on their own,
and it's a big, cold, dangerous universe,
so most of them aren't going to make it, eh?
The most you can do is crank out millions of kids,
take comfort in knowing that a few always luck out
through random chance.
It's not mammal mindset, Mish.
You want an earthbound simile?
Think of dandelion seeds.
Or herring.
A soft sigh.
So, they're interstellar herring.
That hardly means they can't crush us.
But they don't know about us, not in advance.
Dandelion seed doesn't know what it's up against
before it sprouts.
Maybe nothing.
Maybe some spastic weed that goes over like straw in the wind.
Or maybe something that kicks its ass
halfway to the Magellanic clouds.
It doesn't know,
and there's no such thing as a one size fits all survival strategy.
Something that aces against one player
blows goats against a different one.
So the best you can do is mix up your strategies
based on the odds.
It's a weighted dice roll,
and it gives you the best mean payoff over the whole game.
But you're bound to crap out
and choose the wrong strategy at least some of the time.
Price of doing business.
And that means...
THAT means...
that weak players not only can win against stronger ones,
but they're statistically bound to win against stronger ones.
But they're statistically bound to in some cases.
Michelle Snorted.
That's your game theory?
Rock, paper, scissors with statistics?
Manebeek Spindle didn't know the reference.
He didn't speak.
Long enough to call out a subtitle.
Then he braided like a horse.
Rock, paper, scissors, yes!
Michelle digested that for a moment.
You're sweet for trying,
but that only works if the other side is just blindly playing the odds,
and they don't have to do that
if they know who they're going up against in advance.
And my dear, they have so very much information about us.
They threaten Susan.
By name.
They don't know everything, Spindle insisted.
And the principle works for any scenario
involving incomplete information,
not just the ignorant extreme.
Not as well.
But some, and that gives us a chance.
Doesn't matter how good you are at poker when it comes to the D.I.A.
Cards still deal out with the same odds.
So that's what we're playing, poker.
Be thankful it's not chess.
We wouldn't have a hope in hell.
Hey, I'm supposed to be the optimist in this relationship.
You are.
I'm just fatalistically cheerful.
We all come into the story halfway through.
We all catch up as best we can,
and we're all going to die before it ends.
That's my Isaac, master of the no-win scenario.
You can win.
Winner's the guy who makes the best guess on how it all comes out.
So you ARE just guessing.
Yep.
And you can't make an informed guess without D.I.A., eh?
And we could be the very first to find out
what's going to happen to the whole human race.
I'd say that puts us into the semifinals easy.
Michelle didn't answer for a long time.
When she did, I couldn't hear her words.
Neither could Spindle.
Sorry?
Covert to invulnerable, you said, remember?
Uh-huh.
Rorschach's graduation day.
How soon, you think?
No idea, but I don't think it's the kind of thing that's going to slip by unnoticed,
and that's why I don't think it attacked us.
She must have looked a question.
Because when it does, it won't be some debatable,
candy-ass bitch-slap, he told her.
When that fucker rises up, we're going to know.
A sudden flicker from behind.
I spun in the cramped passageway and bit down on a cry.
Something squirmed out of sight right around a corner.
Something with arms.
Barely glimpsed.
Gone in an instant.
Never there.
Couldn't be there.
Impossible.
Did you hear that?
Spindle asked.
But I'd fled to Stern before Michelle could answer him.
We'd fallen so far that the naked eye didn't see a disc.
Barely even saw curvature anymore.
We were falling towards a wall.
A vast, roiling expanse of dark,
thunder-clouds that extended in all directions to some new,
infinitely distant horizon.
Ben filled half the universe, and still we fell.
Far below, Jack clung to Rorschach's ridged surface with
bristly gecko-feet fenders and set up camp.
It sent X-rays and ultrasound into the ground, tapped
inquiring fingers and listened to the echoes, planted tiny
explosive charges and measured the resonance of their detonations.
It shed seeds like pollen, tiny probes and sensors
by the thousands, self-powered, nearsighted, stupid and expendable.
The vast majority were sacrificial offerings to random chance.
Only one in a hundred lasted long enough to return usable telemetry.
While our advanced scout took measure of its local neighborhood,
thesius drew larger-scale bird's-eye maps in the closing sky.
It spat out thousands of its own disposable probes,
spread them across the heavens and collected stereoscopic data from
a thousand simultaneous perspectives.
Pachwork insights assembled in the drum.
Rorschach's skin was 60% superconducting carbon nanotube.
Rorschach's guts were largely hollow.
At least some of these hollows appeared to contain an atmosphere.
No earthly life would have lasted a second in there, though.
Intricate topographies of radiation and electromagnetic
force seethe around the surface, seethe within it.
In some places, the radiation was intense enough to turn
unshielded flesh to ash in an instant.
Calmer backwaters would merely kill in the same span of time.
Charged particles raced around invisible race tracks at relativistic speeds,
erupting from jagged openings, hugging curves of magnetic force strong enough for neutron stars,
arcing through open space and plunging back into black mass.
Occasional protuberances swelled and burst and released clouds of microparticulates,
seeding the radiation belts like spores.
Rorschach resembled nothing so much as a nest of half-naked cyclotrons, tangled with each other.
Neither Jack below nor Thesias above could find any points of entry.
Beyond these impossible gaps that spat out streams of charged particles,
just swallowed them back down, no airlocks or hatches or viewports resolved with increasing
proximity. The fact that we'd been threatened by a laser beam implied some kind of optical
antennae or tight-cast array, we weren't even able to find that much.
A central hallmark of von Neumann machines was self-replication.
Whether Rorschach would meet that criterion, whether it would germinate or divide or give
birth when it passed some critical threshold, whether it had done so already, remained an open
question. One of a thousand. At the end of it all, after all the measurements, the theorizing
and deduction and outright guesswork, we settled into orbit with a million trivial details and no
answers. In terms of the big questions, there was only one thing we knew for sure. So far,
Rorschach was holding its fire.
It sounded to me like it knew what it was saying, I remarked.
I guess that's the whole point, Bates said. She had no one to confide in, partook of no
intimate dialogues that could be overheard. With her I used the direct approach. Thesias
was birthing a litter, two by two. They were nasty-looking things, armored, squashed egg shapes,
twice the size of a human torso, and studded with gardening implements, antennae, optical ports,
retractable thread saws, weapons muzzles. Bates was summoning her troops. We floated before
the primary fab port at the base of Thesias' spine. The plant could just as easily have
disgorged the grunts directly into the hold beneath the carapace. That was where they'd be stored
anyway until called upon. But Bates was giving each a visual inspection before sending it through
one of the airlocks a few meters up the passageway. Ritual, perhaps. Military tradition. Certainly,
there was nothing she could see with her eyes that wouldn't be glaringly obvious to the most basic
diagnostic. Would it be a problem, I asked, running without your interface? Run themselves just fine.
Response time actually improves without spamming the network. I'm more of a safety precaution.
Thesias growled, giving us more attitude. The plating trembled a stern, another piece of local
debris no longer in our path. We were angling towards an equatorial orbit just a few minuscule
kilometers above the artifact. Insanely, the approach curved right through the accretion belt.
It didn't bother the others. Like surviving high traffic in a high speed lane, Sasha had said,
disdainful of my misgivings. Try creeping across on your roadkill. Gotta speed up, go with the flow.
But the flow was turbulent. We hadn't gone five minutes without a course correction since
Warshaw could stop talking to us. So do you buy it? I asked. Pattern matching, empty threats,
nothing to worry about? Nobody's fired on us yet, she said. Meaning, not for a second.
What's your take on Susan's argument? Different niches, no reason for conflict.
Makes sense, I guess. Out of bullshit.
Can you think of any reason why something with different needs would attack us?
That depends, she said, on whether the fact that we are different is reason enough.
I saw playground battlefields reflected in her topology. I remembered my own and wondered if
there was another kind. Then again, that only proved the point. Humans didn't really fight over
skin tone or ideology. Those were just handy cues or kin selection purposes.
Ultimately, it always came down to bloodlines and limited resources.
I think Isaac would say this is different. I guess. Bates sent one grunt humming off to the hold,
two more emerged in formation, spine light glinting off their armor.
How many of these are you making, anyway? We're breaking an entering series, not wise to leave
our own house unguarded. I inspected her services as she inspected theirs.
Doubt and resentment simmered just beneath. You're in a tough spot, her marked. We all are.
But you're responsible for defending us against something we don't know anything about.
We're only guessing that...
Sadasti doesn't guess, Bates said. The man's in charge for a reason. Doesn't make much sense
to question his orders, given we're all about a hundred IQ points short of understanding the
answer, anyway. And yet he's got that whole predatory side nobody talks about, I remarked.
It must be difficult for him, all that intellect coexisting with so much instinctive aggression.
Make sure the right part wins. She wondered in that instant whether Sadasti might be listening in.
She decided in the next that it didn't matter. Why should he care what the cattle thought as
long as they did what they were told? All she said was, I thought you jargonauts weren't supposed
to have opinions. That wasn't mine. Bates paused, returned to her inspection.
You do know what I do, I said. Uh-huh. The first of the current pair passed muster and
hummed up off the spine. She turned to the second. You simplify things, so the folks back home can
understand what the specialists are up to. That's part of it. I don't need a translator, Ciri.
I'm just a consultant assuming things go well. A bodyguard if they don't.
You're an officer and a military expert. I'd say that makes you more qualified when it comes to
assessing Warshawk's threat potential. I'm muscle. Shouldn't you be simplifying Yuka or Isaac?
That's exactly what I'm doing. She looked at me.
You interact, I said. Every component of the system affects every other. Processing Sadasti
without factoring you in would be like trying to calculate acceleration while ignoring mass.
She turned back to her brood. Another robot passed muster.
She didn't hate me. What she hated was that what my presence implied.
They don't trust us to speak for ourselves, she wouldn't say. No matter how qualified we are,
no matter how far ahead of the pack, maybe even because of that, or contaminated, or subjective.
So they send Ciri Keaton to tell them what we really mean.
I get it, I said after a moment. Do you? It's not about trust, major. It's about location.
Nobody gets a good view of a system from the inside no matter who they are. The view is distorted.
And yours isn't. I'm outside the system. You're interacting with me now.
As an observer only, perfection's unattainable, but it isn't unapproachable, you know?
I don't play a role in decision making or research. I don't interfere in any aspect of the mission
that I'm assigned to study. But of course I ask questions. The more information I have,
the better my analysis. I thought you didn't have to ask. I thought you guys could just
read the signs or something. Everybody helps. It all goes into the mix. You're doing it now,
synthesizing? I nodded. And you do this without any specialized knowledge at all.
I'm as much of a specialist as you. I specialize in processing informational topologies
without understanding their content. Understanding the shapes is enough.
Bates seemed to find some small imperfection in the battle bot under scrutiny,
scratched a shell with a fingernail. Software couldn't do that without your help.
Software can do a lot of things. We've chosen to do some for ourselves. I nodded at the grunt.
Your visual inspections, for example. She smiled faintly, conceding the point.
So I'd encourage you to speak freely. You know I'm sworn to confidentiality.
Thanks, she said. Meaning, on this ship, there's no such thing.
Thesias chimed. Sadasti spoke in its wake. Orbital insertion in 15 minutes. Everyone
to the drum in five. Well, Bates said, sending one last grunt on its way. Here we go.
She pushed off and sailed up the spine. The newborn killing machines clicked at me.
They smelled like new cars.
By the way, Bates called over her shoulder. You missed the obvious one. Sorry.
She spun 180 degrees in the passageway, landed like an acrobat beside the drum hatch.
The reason? Why, something would attack us even if we didn't have anything it wanted.
I read it off her. If it wasn't attacking at all, if it was defending itself.
You asked about Sadasti. Smart man, strong leader. Maybe you could spend a little bit more time with
the troops. Vampire doesn't respect command. Doesn't listen to advice. Hides away half the time.
I remember to transient killer whales. Maybe he's being considerate. He knows he makes us nervous.
I'm sure that's it, Bates said. Vampire doesn't trust himself.
It wasn't just Sadasti. They all hid from us, even when they had the upper hand.
They always stayed just to the other side of myth. It started pretty much the same way it did for
anything else. Vampires were far from the first to learn the virtues of energy conservation.
Shrews and hummingbirds, saddled with tiny bodies and overclocked metabolic engines,
would have starved to death overnight if not for the torpor that overtook them at sundown.
Cometose elephant seals lurked at the bottom of the sea, rousing only for passing prey or red
line lactate levels. Bears and chipmunks cut costs by sleeping away the impoverished winter months
and lungfish, Devonian black belts in the art of estivation, could curl up and die for years waiting
for the rains. With vampires it was a little different. It wasn't the shortness of breath
or metabolic overdrive or some blanket of snow that locked the pantry every winter.
The problem wasn't so much the lack of prey as the lack of difference from it. Vampires were
such a recent split from the ancestral baseline that the reproductive rates hadn't diverged.
There was no woodland variety, Link's hair dynamic, or prey outnumbered predators 101.
Vampires fed on things that bred fairly faster than they did.
They would have wiped out their own food supply in no time if they hadn't learned how to ease off
the throttle. By the time they went extinct, they'd learned to shut down for decades.
It made two kinds of sense. It not only slashed their metabolic needs while prey bred itself back
to harvestable levels, it gave us time to forget that we were prey. You were so smart by the pleous
cysteine, smart enough for easy skepticism. If you hadn't seen any night-stalking demons in
all your years on the savannah, why would you believe some senile campfire ramblings passed down
by your mother's mother? It was murder on our ancestors, even if those same enemy genes co-opted
now served us so well when we left the sun a half million years later. But it was almost
heartening, I guess, to think that maybe Sadasti felt the tug of other genes,
some aversion to prolonged visibility shaped by generations of natural selection.
Maybe he spent every moment in our company fighting voices that urged him to
hide, hide, let them forget. Maybe he retreated when I got too loud. Maybe we made him as uneasy
as he made us. We could always hope.
Our final orbit combined discretion and valor in equal measure. Rorschach described a perfect
equatorial circle 87,900 kilometers from Big Bend center of gravity. Sadasti was unwilling to let
it out of sight, and you didn't have to be a vampire to mistrust relay sats when swinging the
irradiation-soaked blizzard of rock and machinery. The obvious alternative was to match orbits.
At the same time, all the debate over whether or not Rorschach had meant or even understood the
threats it made was a bit beside the point. Counter intrusion measures were a distinct
possibility either way. An ongoing proximity increased the risk. So Sadasti had derived some
optimum compromise, a mildly eccentric orbit that nearly brushed the artifact at perigee,
but kept a discrete distance the rest of the time. It was a longer trajectory than Rorschach's
and higher. We had to burn on the descending arc to keep in sync, but the end result was continuously
line of sight, and only brought us within striking distance for three hours of either side, bottoming
out. Our striking distance, that is. For all we knew, Rorschach could have reached out and swatted
us from the sky before we even left the solar system. Sadasti gave the command from his tent.
A consensus carried his voice into the drum as thesius coasted to apogee. Now.
Jack had erected a tent about itself. A blister glued to Rorschach's hull, and blown semi-tod
against vacuum with the mere swift of nitrogen. Now it brought lasers to bear and started digging.
If we read the vibrations right, the ground should only be 34 centimeters deep beneath its feet.
The beams stuttered as they cut, despite six millimeters of dope shielding.
Son of a bitch, spindle murmured. It's working.
We burned through tough fibrous epidermis. We burned through veins of insulation that might
have been some sort of programmable asbestos. We burned through alternating layers of super
conducting mesh, and then strata of flaking carbon separating them. We burned through.
The lasers shut down instantly. Within seconds, Rorschach's intestinal gases had blown taut the
skin of the tent. Black carbon smoke swirled and danced in sudden thick atmosphere. Nothing shot
back at us. Nothing reacted. Partial pressures piled up on consensus. Methane, ammonia, hydrogen,
lots of water vapor freezing as fast as it registered. Spindle grunted. Reducing atmosphere.
Pre-snowball. He sounded disappointed.
Maybe it's a work in progress, James suggested, like the structure itself.
Maybe. Jock stuck out its tongue, a giant mechanical sperm with a myo-optical tail.
Its head was a thick-skinned lozenge, at least half ceramic shielding by cross-section. The tiny
payload of sensors at its core was rudimentary, but small enough for the whole assembly to thread
through the pencil-thin hole the laser had cut. It unspooled down the hole, rimming Rorschach's
newly torn orifice. Dark down there, James observed. Bates, but warm. 281 degrees Kelvin, above freezing.
The endoscope emerged in darkness. Infrared served up a great grainy gray scale of
a tunnel it looked like, replete with mist and exotic rock formations.
The walls curved up like a honeycomb, like the insides of a fossilized intestine.
Cold as sacks and branches proliferated down the passage. The basic substrate appeared to be a dense
pastry of carbon fiber leaves. Some of the gaps between those layers are barely as thick as fingernails.
Others looked wide enough to stack bodies.
Ladies and gentlemen, Spindle said softly, the Devil's baklava.
I could have sworn I saw something move. I could have sworn it looked familiar. The camera died.
Rorschach.
Mothers are fonder than fathers of their children, because they are more certain they are their own.
Aristotle.
I couldn't say goodbye to dad. I didn't even know where he was.
I didn't want to say goodbye to Helen. I didn't want to go back there. That was the problem. I
didn't have to. There was nowhere left in the world where the mountain couldn't simply pick up and
move to Muhammad. Heaven was merely a suburb of the global village, and the global village left
me no excuse. I linked for my own apartment. My new inlays, mission-specific slid into my head
just the week before, shook hands with the new sphere and knocked upon the pearly gates.
Some tame spirit more plausible than St. Peter, if no less ethereal, took a message and disappeared.
And I was inside.
There was no antechamber, no visiting room. Heaven was not intended for the casual visitor.
Any paradise in which the flesh constrained would feel at home would have been intolerably
pedestrian to the disembodied souls who lived there. Of course, there was no reason why visitor
and resident had to share the same view. I could have pulled any conventional world view off the
shelf if I'd wanted, seeing this place rendered in any style I chose. Except for the ascended
themselves, of course. That was one of the perks of the afterlife. Only they got to choose the face
we saw. But the thing my mother had become had no face, and I was damned if she was going to see
me hide behind some mask. Hello, Helen. Siri, what a wonderful surprise! She was an abstraction within
an abstraction, an impossible intersection of dozens of bright pains, as if the disembezzled
tiles of a stained glass window had each been set aglow and animated. She swirled before me like a
school of fish. Her world echoed her body. Lights and angles and three-dimensional escher
impossibilities piled like bright thunderheads. And yet somehow I would have recognized her anywhere.
Heaven was a dream. Only upon waking do you realize the characters you encountered look
nothing like they do in real life. There was only one familiar landmark anywhere in the whole
sensorium. My mother's heaven smelled of cinnamon. I beheld her luminous avatar and imagined the
corpus soaking in a tank of nutrient deep underground. How are you doing? Very well,
very well. Of course, it takes a little getting used to knowing your mind isn't quite yours anymore.
Heaven didn't just feed the brains of its residents. It fed off them. Used the surplus power of idle
synapses to run its own infrastructure. You have to move in here sooner rather than later. You'll
never leave. Actually, I am leaving, I said. We're shipping out tomorrow. Shipping out?
The Kuiper. You know, the Fireflies? Oh yes, I think I heard something about that. We don't get
much news from the outside world, you know. Anyway, just thought I'd call in and say goodbye.
I'm glad you did. I've been hoping to see you without, you know, without what?
You know, without your father listening in. Not again. Dad's in the field, Helen.
In her planetary crisis. You might have heard something. I certainly have. You know,
I haven't always been happy about your father's extended assignments, but maybe it was really
a blessing in disguise. The less he was around, the less he could do. Do? To you. The apparations
stilled for a few moments. Feigning hesitation. I've never told you this before, but no, I shouldn't.
Shouldn't what? Bring up, well, old hurts. What old hurts?
Right on cue. I couldn't help myself. The training went too deep. I always barked on command.
Well, she began. Sometimes you'd come back. You were so very young, and your face would be so set
and hard, and I'd wonder, why are you so angry, little boy? What can someone so young have to
be so angry about? Helen, what are you talking about, back from where?
Just from the places he'd take you. Something like a shiver passed across her facets.
He was still around back then. He wasn't so important. He was just an accountant with a karate
fetish. Going on about forensics and game theory and astronomy until he put everyone to sleep.
I tried to imagine it. My father, the chatterbox. That doesn't sound like Dad.
Well, of course not. You were too young to remember, but he was just a little man then.
He still is, really, under all the secret missions and classified briefings. I've never
understood why people saw that. But even back then he liked to, well, it wasn't his fault, I suppose.
He had a very difficult childhood, and he never learned to deal with the problems like an adult.
Well, he would throw his weight around, I guess you'd say. Of course, I didn't know that before
we married. If I had, I... but I made a commitment. I made a commitment and I never broke it.
What, are you saying you were abused? Back from the places he'd take you.
Are you... are you saying I was? There are all kinds of abuse, Siri. Words can hurt more than
bullets sometimes, and child abandonment. He didn't abandon me. He left me with you.
He abandoned us, Siri. Sometimes for months at a time, and I... and we never knew if he was coming
back, and he chose to do that to us, Siri. He didn't need that job. There were so many other
things he was qualified to do. Things that had been redundant for years. I shook my head,
incredulous, unable to say it aloud. She hated him because he hadn't had the good grace to grow
unnecessary. It's not Dad's fault that planetary security is still an essential service, I said.
She continued as if she hadn't heard. Now, there was a time when it was unavoidable,
when people our age had to work just to make ends meet. But even back then, people wanted to spend
time with their families. Even if they couldn't afford to. To choose to stay working when it
isn't even necessary, that's... she shattered and reassembled at my shoulder. Yes, Siri, I believe
that's a kind of abuse. And if your father had been as half as loyal to me as I've been to him
all these years, I remember Jim, the last time I'd seen him, snorting Vasopressin under the
restless eyes of robot sentries. I don't think Dad's been disloyal to either of us.
Hell inside. I don't really expect you to understand. I'm not completely stupid. I've seen how it
played out. I pretty much had to raise you myself all these years. I've always had to play the heavy,
always had to be the one to hand out the discipline because your father was off on some
secret assignment, and then he'd come home for a week or two and he was the golden-haired boy
just because he'd seen fit to drop in. I don't really blame you for that anymore than I blame him.
Blame doesn't solve anything at this stage. I just thought, well, really, I thought you ought to know.
Take it for what it's worth. A memory, unbidden. Called into Helen's bed when I was nine,
her hand stroking my scar, her stale, sweet breath stirring against my cheek. You're the man of the
house now, Ciri. We can't count on your father anymore. It's just you and me. I didn't say anything
for a while. Finally, didn't it help at all? What do you mean? I glanced around at all the
customized abstraction. Internal feedback, lucidly dreamed. You're omnipotent in here.
Desire anything? Imagine anything? There it is. I thought it would have changed you more.
Rainbow tiles danced and forced to laugh. This isn't enough of a change for you?
Not nearly. Because heaven had a catch. No matter how many constructs and avatars Helen built in
there, no matter how many empty vessels sang her praises or commiserated over the injustices she'd
suffered, when it came right down to it she was only talking to herself. There were other realities
over which she had no control, other people who didn't play by her rules. And if they thought
of Helen at all, they thought of, then they thought as they damn well pleased. She could go the rest
of her life without ever meeting any of them, but she knew they were out there and it drove her crazy.
Taking my leave of heaven, it occurred to me that unimpeted though she was,
there was only one way my mother would ever be truly happy in her own personal creation.
The rest of creation would have to go.
This shouldn't keep happening, Bates said. The shielding was good.
The gang was up across the drum, squaring away from something in their tent.
Sadasti lurked off stage today, monitoring the proceedings from his quarters.
That left me with Bates and Spindle in the commons.
Maybe against Direct-EM, Spindle Stretch, Stifle Yon.
Ultrasound boots up magnetic fields through shielding sometimes and living tissue at least.
Any chance something like that could be happening with your electronics?
Bates spread her hands. Who knows, might as well be black magic and elves down there.
Well, it's not a total wash. We could make a few smart guesses, eh?
Such as, Spindle raised one finger, the layers we cut through couldn't result from any metabolic
process I know of. So it's not alive, not in the biological sense. Not that that means anything
these days, he added, glancing around the belly of our beast. What about life inside the structure?
Anoxic atmosphere probably rules out complex multicellular life. Microbe is maybe, although if
so, I wish to hell they'd show it in the samples. But anything complex enough to think, let alone
build something like that, a wave at the image in consensus, is going to need a high energy
metabolism, and that means oxygen. So you think it's empty? Didn't say that, did I? I know aliens
are supposed to be all mysterious and everything, but I still don't see why anyone would build a
city-sized wildlife refuge for anaerobic microbes. It's gotta be a habitat for something.
Why any atmosphere at all if it's just some kind of terraforming machine?
Spindle pointed up at the gang's tent. What Susan said, atmosphere still under construction and we
get a free ride until the owners show up. Free? Free-ish. And I know we've only seen a fraction
of a fraction of what's inside, but something obviously saw us coming. It yelled at us if I recall.
If they're smart and they're hostile, why aren't they shooting? Maybe they are.
If something's hiding down the hall wrecking your robots, it's not frying them any faster
than the baseline environment do anyway. What you call a baseline environment might be an active
counter intrusion measure. Why else would a habitat be so uninhabitable? Spindle rolled his eyes.
Okay, I was wrong. We don't know enough to make a few smart guesses.
Not that we hadn't tried. Once Jack's sensor head had been irreparably fried, we'd relegate it to
surface excavation. It had widened the bore in infinitesimal increments, patiently burning back
the edges of our initial peephole until it measured almost a meter across. Meanwhile, we'd customized
bait's grunts, shield them against nuclear reactors in the insides of cyclotrons, and
compared we'd thrown them at Rorschach like stones chucked into a haunted forest. Each had gone
through Jack's portal, unspooling, whisper-thin fiber-op behind them to pass intelligence through
charged atmosphere. They'd sent glimpses mostly, a few extended vignettes. We'd seen Rorschach's
walls move, slow, lazy waves of periostellis rippling along its gut. We'd seen treocally
invignations in progress, painstaking constrictions that would presumably, given time, seal off a
passageway. Our grunts had sailed through some quarters, staggered through others where the
magnetic ambience threw them off balance. They'd passed through strange throats lined with razor
thin teeth, thousands of triangular blades in parallel rows, helically twisted. They'd edged
cautiously around clouds of mists sculpted into abstract fractal shapes, shifting and endlessly
recursive, their charged droplets strung along the myriad converging lines of electromagnetic force.
Ultimately, every one of them had died or disappeared. Any way to increase the shielding,
I wondered. Spindle gave me a look. We've shielded everything except the sensor heads,
Bates explained. If we shield those, we're blind. But visible light's harmless enough,
what about purely optical light? We're using optical links, Commisar, Cyndall snapped.
And you may have noticed the shits getting through anyway. But aren't there, you know,
I groped for the word, bandpass filters? Something that lets visible light wavelengths through,
cuts out lethal stuff on both sides? E snorted. Sure, it's called an atmosphere,
if we brought one with us about 50 times deeper than Earth's, it might block some of the soup down
there. Of course, Earth also gets a lot of help from its magnetic field, but I'm not betting my life
on any EM we can set up in that place. If we didn't keep running into these spikes, Bates said,
that's the real problem. Are they random? I wondered. Spindle shrugged was a half shiver.
I don't think anything about that place is random, but who knows? We need more data.
Which we're not likely to get, James said, walking around the ceiling to join us,
if our drones keep shorting out. The conditional was pure formality. We tried playing the odds,
sacrificing drone after drone in the hope that one of them would get lucky. Survival rates
tailed exponentially to zero with distance in the base camp. We tried shielding the fiber
op to reduce aperture leakage. The resulting tethers were stiff and unwieldly, wrapped in so
many layers of ferroceramic they were virtually waving the bots around on the end of a stick.
We tried cutting the tethers entirely, sending the machines out to explore on their own,
squinting against the radiant blizzard and storing their findings for later download.
None had returned. We tried everything.
We can go in ourselves, James said. Almost everything.
Right. Spindle replied in a voice that couldn't meet anything but wrong.
It's the only way to learn anything useful. Yeah, like how many seconds it would take
your brain to turn it a synchrotron soup. Our suits can be shielded. Oh, you mean like
Mandy's drones? I really prefer you didn't call me that, Bates remarked.
The point is Rorschach kills you whether you're meat or mechanical.
My point is that it kills me differently. James replied. It takes longer. Spindle shook his head.
You'd be good as dead in 50 minutes, even shielded, even in the so-called cool zones.
And be completely asymptomatic for three hours or more. And even after that,
it would take days for us to actually die. And we'd be back here long before then,
and the ship could patch us up just like that. We even know that much, Isaac. It's right there in
consensus. And if we know it, you know it. So we shouldn't even be having this argument.
That's your solution. We saturate ourselves with radiation every 30 hours,
and I get to cut out the tumors and stitch everyone's cells back together.
The pods are automatic. You wouldn't have to lift a finger.
Not to mention what those magnetic fields would do to your brain.
We'd be hallucinating from the moment we fair data suits.
Ah, so we go in deft, dumb, and blind. Good idea. We can let light pass. Infrared. It's all EM, Suze.
Even if we blacked out our helmets completely and used a camera feed,
we'd get leakage where the wire went through. Sure, yes, but it'd be better than Jesus,
a tremor-sense spittle sailing from the corner of Spindle's mouth.
Let me talk to M-
I've discussed it with the rest of the gang, Isaac. We're all agreed.
All agreed? You don't have a working majority in there, Suze. Just because you cut your brain
into pieces doesn't mean they each get a vote. I don't see why not. We're at least
as sentient as you are. They're all you, just partitioned. You don't seem to have any trouble
treating Michelle as a separate individual. Michelle's, I mean, yes, you're all different
facets, but there's only one original. Your altars don't call us that.
Sasha erupted with a voice as cold as locks. Ever. Spindle tried to pull back.
I didn't mean you know I didn't, but Sasha was gone.
What are you saying? said the softer voice in her wake. Do you think I'm just- I'm just mom play
acting? Do you think we're together? You're alone with her?
Michelle, Spindle said miserably. No, what I think-
Doesn't matter, Sir Asti said. We don't vote here.
He floated above us, visor'd and unreadable in the center of the drum. None of us had seen him
arrive. He turned slowly on his axis, keeping us in view as we rotated around him.
Prepping Silla. Amanda needs two untethered grunts with precautionary armament. Cams from
one to a million angstroms, shielded in panics, no autonomous circuitry.
Played lid boosters. Diamond hydranate and potassium iodide for everyone by 1350.
Everyone, Bates asked. Sir Asti nodded.
Window opens four hours 23. He turned back down the spine.
Not me, I said. Sir Asti paused.
I don't participate in field ops, I reminded him. Now you do.
I'm a synthesis. He knew that. Of course he knew everyone did. You can't observe the system unless
you say outside the system. On earth, you're a synthesis, he said. In the Kuiper, you're a synthesis.
Hear your mass, do what you're told. He disappeared.
Welcome to the big picture, Bates said softly. I looked at her as the rest of the group broke up.
You know I, we're a long way out, Siri. Can't wait 14 months or feedback from your bosses and you know it.
She leapt from a standing star, arc smoothly through holograms into the weightless core of the drum,
but then she stopped herself as if distracted by some sudden insight.
She grabbed a spinal conduit and swung back to face me.
You shouldn't sell yourself short, she said. Or Sir Asti, either. You're an observer, right?
It's a safe bet there's going to be a lot down there worth observing.
Thanks, I said. But I already knew why Sir Asti was sending me into Rorschach and there was more
to it than observation. Three valuable agents in harm's way. A decoy about one in four odds
that an enemy would aim somewhere else. The Lord will take control of you. You will dance and shout
and become a different person. 1 Samuel 10 6
We were probably fractured during most of our evolution. James once told me back when we were
all still getting acquainted. She tapped her temple. There's a lot of room up here. A modern
brain can run dozens of sentient cores without getting too crowded. And parallel multitasking
has obvious survival advantages. I nodded. Ten heads are better than one. Our integration may
have actually occurred quite recently. Some experts think we can still revert to multiples
under the right circumstances. Well, of course, you're living proof. She shook their head.
I'm not talking about physical partitioning. We're the state of the arts, certainly, but
theoretically surgery isn't even necessary. Simple stress could do something like it if it was strong
enough. If it happened early in childhood. No kidding. Well, in theory, James admitted and
changed into Sasha, who said, bullshit in theory, there's documented cases as recently as 50 years
ago. Really? I resisted the temptation to look it up on my inlays. The unfocused eyes can be a
giveaway. I didn't know. Well, it's not like anyone talks about it now. People were fucking
barbarians about multi-cores back then, called it a disorder, treated it like some kind of disease.
And their idea of a cure was to keep one of the cores and murder all the others.
Not that they called it murder, of course, they called it integration or some shit.
That's what people did back then, created other people to suck up all the abuse and torture,
then got rid of them when they weren't needed anymore. It hadn't been the tone most of us
were looking for at an ice breaking party. James had gently eased back into the driver's
seat and the conversation had steered closer to community standards. But I hadn't heard any of
the gang use altered to describe each other than or since. It seemed innocuous enough when Spindle
had said it. I wondered why they'd taken such offense. And now floating alone in my tent with
a few pre-op minutes to kill. There was no one to see my eyes glaze. Alter carried baggage over a
sensory old, consensus told me. Sasha was right. There'd been a time when MCC was MPD, a disorder
rather than a complex, and it had never been induced deliberately. According to the experts
of that time, multiple personalities arose spontaneously from unimaginable cauldrons of abuse.
Fragmentary persona offered up to suffer rapes and beatings while the child hid behind some
unknowable sanctuary in the folds of the brain. It was both survival strategy and ritual self-sacrifice.
Powerless souls hacking themselves to pieces, offering up quivering chunks of self in the
desperate hope that the vengeful gods called mom and dad might not be insatiable.
None of it had been real as it turned out, or at least none of it had been confirmed. The experts
of the day had been little more than witch doctors dancing through improvised rituals,
mandering free-form interviews full of leading questions and non-verbal cues, scavenger hunts
through regurgitated childhoods, sometimes a shot of lithium or haloper at all when the
beads and rattles didn't work. The technology to map minds was barely off the ground. The technology
to edit them was gears away. So the therapists and psychiatrists poked at their victims and
invented names for things they didn't understand and argued over the shrines of Freud and Klein
and the Old Astrologers, doing their best to sound like practitioners of science.
Inevitably, it was science that turned them all into roadkill. MPD was a half-forgotten
fad even before the advent of synaptic rewiring. But altar was a word from that time,
and its resonance had persisted. Among those who remembered the tale,
altar was code for betrayal and human sacrifice. Altar meant cannon fodder.
Imagining the topology of the gang's co-existing souls, I could see why Sasha embraced the
mythology. I could see why Susan let her. After all, there was nothing implausible about the concept.
The gang's very existence proved that much. And when you've been peeled off from a pre-existing
entity, sculpted it from non-existence straight into adulthood, a mere fragment of personhood
without even a full-time body to call your own, you can be forgiven a certain amount of anger.
Sure, you're all equal, all in it together. Sure, no persona is better than any other.
Susan's still the only one with a surname. Better to direct that resentment at old grudges,
real or imagined, less problematic at least than taking it out on someone who shares the same flesh.
I realized something else too. Surrounded by displays documenting the relentless growth of
the Leviathan beneath us, I could not only see why Sasha had objected to the word,
I could also see why Isaac Spindle, no doubt unconsciously, had spoken it in the first place.
As far as Earth was concerned, everyone on theseas was an altar.
Sonoste stayed behind. He hadn't come with a backup.
There were the rest of us, though, crammed into the shuttle, embedded in custom spacesuits so
padded with shielding we might have been deep-sea divers in a previous century. It was a fine
balance. Too much shielding would have been worse than none at all, would split primary
particles into secondary ones just as lethal and twice as numerous. Sometimes you had to live
with moderate exposure. The only alternative was to embed yourself like a bug in lead.
We launched six hours from Paragy. Silla raced on ahead like an eager child, leaving its parent
behind. There is no eagerness in the systems around me, though, except for one. The gang of four
are almost shimmered behind her faceplate. Excited, I asked. Sasha answered.
Fucking right! Fieldwork, Keaton! First contact!
What if there's nobody there? What if there is and they don't like us?
Even better, we get a crack at their signs and cereal boxes without the traffic cops
leaning over our shoulders. I wondered if she spoke for the others. I was pretty sure she
didn't speak for Michelle. Silla's ports had all been sealed.
There was no outside view, nothing to see inside but bots and bodies and the tangled
silhouette swelling on my helmet-hud. But I could feel the radiation slicing through our armor as
if it were tissue paper. I could feel the knotted crests and troughs of Rorschach's magnetic field.
I could feel Rorschach itself drawing nearer, the charred canopy of some fire-sormed alien
forest, more landscape than artifact. I imagined titanic bolts of electricity arcing between
its branches. I imagined getting in the way. What kind of creatures would choose to live in
such a place? You really think we'll get along, I said. James' shrug was almost lost under the
armor. Maybe not at first. We may have gotten off on the wrong foot. We might have to sort through
all kinds of misunderstandings, but we'll figure each other out eventually. Evidentially, she
thought that answered my question. The shuttle slewed. We bumped up against each other like 10 pins.
Thirty seconds of micromaneuver has brought us to a solid stop. A cheery animation played
across the hut in greens and blues. The shuttle's docking seal, easing through the membrane that
served as our entrance into Rorschach's inflatable vestibule. Even as a cartoon, it looked vaguely
pornographic. Bates had been pre-packed next to the airlock. She slid back the inner door. Everybody
ducked. Not an easy maneuver, swaddled in life support and ferroceramic. Helmets tilted and
bumped. The grunts flattened overhead like lethal cockroaches, hummed to life and disengaged from
the ceiling. They scraped past in the narrow headroom, bobbing cryptically to their mistress
and exited stage left. Bates closed the inner hatch. The lock cycled, opened again on an empty
chamber. Everything normal, according to the board. The drones waited patiently in the vestibule.
Nothing had jumped out at them. We had to wait forever for the image. The bot rate was less than
a trickle. Words moved back and forth easily enough. No surprises so far. Bates reported and
distorted Jews' harp vibrato, but any picture worth a million of them and... there. Through the eyes of
the grunt behind, we saw the grunt head in motionless grainy monochrome. It was a postcard from the past.
Sight turned to sound, a thick clumsy vibrations of methane bumping against the hull. It took long
seconds for each static-ridden image to accrete on the HUD. Grunts descended into the pit,
grunts emerging from into Rorschach's duodenum, a cryptic hostile cave-scape in systematic
increments. Down in the lower left-hand corner of each image, timestamps and Teslas ran down the
clock. You gave up a lot when you don't trust the EM spectrum. Looks good, Bates reported, going in.
In a friendlier universe, machines would have cruised the boulevards, sending perfect images in
crystal resolution. Spindled and ganged would be sipping coffee back in a drum, telling the grunts
to take a sample of this or get a close-up of that. In a friendlier universe, I wouldn't even be here.
Bates appeared in the next postcard, emerging from the fistula. In the next back... er, in the next
her back was to the camera, apparently panning the perimeter. In the one after that, she was looking
right at us. Oh, okay, she said. Come on. Down. Not so fast, Spindle said. How are you feeling?
Fine. A bit odd, but odd how.
Radiation sickness announced itself with nausea, but unless we'd seriously aired in our calculations,
that wouldn't happen for another hour or two. Not until well after we'd all been lehally cooked.
Mild disorientation, Bates reported. It's a bit spooky in here, but
must be gray syndrome. It's tolerable. I looked at the gang. The gang looked at Spindle. Spindle
shrugged. It's not gonna get any better, Bates said from afar. The clock is ticking, people. Get down
here. We got. Not living. Not by a long shot. Haunted.
Not living. Not by a long shot. Haunted. Even when the walls didn't move, they did.
Always at the corner of the eye, that sense of crawling motion.
Always at the back of the mind, the sense of being watched, the dread certainty of malign and
alien observers just out of sight. More than once I turned, expecting to catch one of those
plantems in the open. All I ever saw was a half-blind grunt floating down the passageway,
or a wide-eyed and jittery crewmate returning my stare, and the walls of some glistening
black lava tube with a hundred embedded eyes all snapped shut just the instant before.
Our lights pushed the darkness back, perhaps twenty meters in either direction,
beyond mist and shadows seethe, and the sounds, roar-shock creaked around us like some ancient
wooden hull trapped in pack ice, electricity hissed like rattlesnakes. You tell yourself,
it's mostly in your head. You remind yourself it's well-documented and inevitable consequence of
meetin' magnetism brought too close together. High energy fields released the ghosts and the
grays from your temporal lobe, dredge up paralyzing dread from the midbrain to saturate the conscious
mind. They fuck with your motor nerves and make even dormant inlays sing like fine fragile crystal.
Energy artifacts. That's all they are. You repeat that to yourself. You repeat it so often it loses
any pretense of rationality and devolves into rodent cantation, a spell to ward off evil spirits.
They're not real, these whispering voices just outside your helmet. Those half-seen
creatures flickering at the edge of vision. They're tricks of the mind, the same neurological
smoke and mirrors that convinced people throughout the ages that they were being haunted by ghosts,
abducted by aliens, hunted by vampires. And you wonder whether Soastie really stayed behind,
or if he was here all along, waiting for you. Another spike, Bates warned as Tesla and Sea
Virts surged on my hood. Hang on. I was installing the Faraday bell, trying to. It should have been
simple enough. I'd already run the main anchor line down from the vestibule to the flaccid
sack floating in the middle of the passageway. I was, that's right, something about a spring line
to keep the bell centered. The wall glistened in my headlamp like wet clay. Satanic runes
sparkled in my imagination. I jammed at the spring line's pad against the wall. I could have sworn
the substrate flinched. I fired my thrust pistol, repeating back to the center of the passage.
They're here, James whispered. Something was. I could feel it always behind me no matter where
I turned. I could feel some great roaring darkness swirling just out of sight, a ravenous mouth as
wide as the tunnel itself, any moment now it would lunge forward at impossible speed and engulf us all.
They're beautiful, James said. There was no fear in her voice at all. She sounded awestruck.
What? Where? Bates never stopped turning. Keep trying to keep the whole 360 in sight at once.
The drones under her command wobbled restlessly to either side, armored parentheses pointing down
the passageway in opposite directions. What do you see? Not out there, in here, everywhere. Can't you see it?
I can't see anything, Spindle said, his voice shaking.
It's in the E.M. fields, James said. That's how they communicate. The whole structure is full of
language. It's... I can't see anything, Spindle repeated. His breath echoed loud and fast over
the link. I'm blind. Shit. Bates swung on Spindle. How can that... the radiation... I... I don't think
that's it. Nine Tesla and the ghosts were everywhere. I smelled asphalt and honeysuckle.
Keaton, Bates called. You with us? Yeah. Barely. I was back at the bell, my hand on the ripcord,
trying to ignore whatever kept tapping me on the shoulder. Leave that, get him inside. No.
Spindle floated helplessly in the passage, his pistol bouncing against its wrists tether.
No, throw me something. What? It's all in your head. It's all in your... throw something, anything.
Bates hesitated. You said you were blind. Just do it.
Bates pulled a spare suit battery off her belt and lobbed it. Spindle reached, fumbled.
Battery slipped from his grasp and bounced dust off the wall.
I'll be okay, he asked. Just get me into the tent.
I yanked the cord. The bell inflated like a great gun-ventil marshmallow.
Everyone inside. Bates ran her pistol with one hand, grabbed Spindle with the other. She handed
him off to me and slapped a sensor pod onto the skin of the tent. I pulled back the shield and
entrance flap as though pulling a scab from a wound. The single molecule beneath, infinitely long,
endlessly folded against itself, swirled and glistened like a soap bubble.
Get him in. James, get down here. I pushed Spindle through the membrane.
It split around him with airtight intimacy, hugged each tiny crack and contour as he passed through.
James, are you... get it off me!
Harsh voice, raw and scared and scary, as male as female could sound.
Cruncher in control. Get it off!
I looked back. Susan James' body tumbled slowly in the tunnel, grasping its right leg with both
hands. James, Bates sailed over to the other woman. Keaton, help out. She took the gang by the arm.
Cruncher, what's the problem?
That! You blind? He wasn't just grasping at the limb I realized as I joined them. He was
tugging at it. He was trying to pull it off. Something laughed hysterically, right inside
Take his arm. Bates told me, taking his right one, trying to pry the fingers from their death
grip on the gang's leg. Cruncher, let go. Now. Get it off me!
It's your leg, Cruncher. We wrestled our way towards the diving bell. It's not my leg. Just
look at it. How could it? It's dead. It's stuck to me. Almost there.
Cruncher, listen. Bates snapped. Are you with me? Get it off!
We stuffed the gang into the tent. Bates moved aside as I dove in after them.
Amazing the way she held it together. Somehow she kept the demons at bay,
herded us to shelter like a border calling in a thunderstorm. She was...
She wasn't following us in. She wasn't even there. I turned to see her body floating outside the
tent, one gloved hand grasping the edge of the flap, but even under all those layers of captain
and chromel and polycarbonate, even behind the distorted half reflections on her face plate,
I could tell that something was missing. All her services had just disappeared.
That couldn't be Amanda, Bates. The thing before me had no more topology than a mannequin.
Amanda? The gang givered at my... at my back softly hysteric.
It's Bindle. What's happening?
I'll stay out here, Bates said. She had no affect whatsoever.
I'm dead anyway.
What? Spindle had lots. You will be if you don't.
You leave me here, Bates said. That's an order. She sealed us in.
It wasn't the first time, not for me. I'd had invisible fingers poking through my brain before,
stirring up the muck, ripping open the scabs. It was far more intense when Rorschach did it to me,
but Chelsea was more... precise, I guess you'd say.
Macrame, she called it. Glieljum starts, cascade effects, the splice and dice of critical ganglia.
While I trafficked in the reading of human architecture,
Chelsea changed it, finding the critical nodes and nudging them just so,
dropping a pebble into some trickle at the headwaters of memory, and watching the ripples,
they'll do a great rolling cascade deep in the downstream psyche.
She'd get hotwire happiness in the time it took to fix a sandwich, reconcile you with
your whole childhood in the course of a lunch hour or three.
Like so many other domains of human invention, this one had learned to run without her.
Human nature was becoming an assembly line edit, humanity itself increasingly relegated
from production to product. Still, for me, Chelsea's skill set recast a strange old world
in an entirely new light. The cut and paste of mine's not for the greater good of some abstract
society, but for the simple selfish wants of the individual.
Let me give you the gift of happiness, she said. I am pretty happy. I'll make you happier, a TAT on me.
TAT? Transient, attitudinal tweak. I've got privileges at Sacks.
I've been tweaked plenty, changed one more synapse and I might turn it to someone else.
That's ridiculous and you know it, or every experience you had would turn you into a different
person. I thought about that. Maybe it does. But she wouldn't let it go, and even the strongest
anti-happiness argument was bound to be an uphill proposition. Some one afternoon,
Chelsea fished around in her cupboards and dredged up a hairnet studded with greasy gray washers.
The net was a superconducting spider web fine as mist that mapped the fields of
mirrored thought. The washers were ceramic magnets that bathe the brain in fields of their own.
Chelsea's inlay is linked to a base station that played with the interference patterns between the
two. They used to need a machine the size of a bathroom just to house the magnets.
She laid me back on the couch and stretched the mesh across my skull.
That's the only outright miracle you get with a portable setup like this.
We can find hotspots and we can even zap them if they need zapping.
But TMS effects fade after a while. We'll have to go to a clinic for anything permanent.
So we're fishing for what exactly? Repressed memories? No such thing. She grinned in a toothy
reassurance. They're only memories we choose to ignore or kind of think around if you know what I mean.
I thought this was a gift of happiness. Why? She laid a fingertip across my lips.
Believe it or not, Sigur's, some people sometimes choose to ignore even good memories.
Like say if they enjoyed something they didn't think they should or
she kissed my forehead. If they don't think they deserve to be happy.
So we're going for potluck. You can never tell till you get a bite. Close your eyes.
A soft hum started up somewhere between my ears.
Chelsea's voice led me through the darkness. Now keep in mind, memories aren't historical archives.
They're improvisations really. A lot of the stuff you associate with a particular event
might be factually wrong no matter how you clearly remember it. The brain has a funny habit of
building composites. Inserting details after the fact. But that's not to say your memories aren't
true, okay? They're an honest reflection of how you saw the world and every one of them went into
shaping how you see it. But they're not photographs. More like impressionist paintings, okay?
Okay. Ah, she said. There's something. What? Functional cluster. Getting a lot of low level
use but not enough to intrude into conscious awareness. Let's just see what happens when we,
and I was 10 years old and I was home early and I just let myself into the kitchen and the smell
of burned butter and garlic hung in the air. Dad and Helen were fighting in the next room.
The flip top on our kitchen catcher had been left up which was something
sometimes enough to get Helen going all by itself. But they were fighting about something else.
Helen only wanted what was best for us all and dad said there were limits and this was not the
way to go about it. And Helen said you don't know what it's like. You hardly ever see him.
And then I knew they were fighting about me. Which in and of itself was nothing unusual.
What really scared me was that for the first time ever dad was fighting back.
You do not force something like that onto someone, especially without their knowledge.
My father never shouted. His voice was low and level as ever. But it was colder than I'd ever
heard and heart as iron. That's just garbage Helen said. Parents always make decisions for
their children and their best interests. Especially when it comes to medical issues.
This is not a medical issue. This time my father's voice did rise. It's not a medical issue. That's
a new height of denial even for you. They would cut out half his brain in case you missed it.
Do you think he could recover from that without help? Is that more of your father's tough love
shining through? Why not just deny him food and water while you're at it? If Muops were called
for they'd have been prescribed. I felt my face scrunching at an unfamiliar word. Something small
and white beckoned from the open garbage pail. Jim be reasonable. He's so distant he barely even
talks to me. They said it would take time. But two years there's nothing wrong with helping nature
a little. We're not even talking black market. It's over the counter for God's sake. That's not the
point. An empty pill bottle. That's what one of them had thrown out before forgetting to close the
lid. I salvaged it from the kitchen discards and sounded out the label in my head. Maybe the point
should be that someone who's barely home three months of the year has got his bloody nerve passing
judgment on my parenting skills. If you want to say in how he's raised then you can damn well pay
some dues first. Until then just fuck right off. You will not put that shit into my son ever again.
My father said. Bonfast formula is for Mu opioid receptor promoters maternal response stimulant
strengthening ties between mother and child since 2042. Yeah and how are you gonna stop me you little
geek? You can't even make the time to find out what's going on in your own family. You think you
can control me all the way from fucking orbit you think? Suddenly nothing came from the living
room with soft choking sounds. I peeked around the corner. My father had hell in by the throat.
I think he growled that I can stop you from doing anything to Siri ever again if I have to and I
think you know that. Then she saw me and then he did and my father took his hand from around my
mother's neck and his face was utterly unreadable but there was no mistaking the triumph on hers.
I was up off the couch the skull cat clenched in one hand. Chelsea stood wide-eyed before me the
butterfly still is death on her cheekbone. She took my hand. Oh god I'm so sorry. You you saw that?
No of course not it can't read minds but that obviously wasn't a happy memory. It wasn't all that
bad. I felt sharp disembodied pain from somewhere nearby like an ink spot or on a white tablecloth.
After a moment I fixed it, teeth in my lip. She ran her hand up my arm. It really stressed you out.
Your vitals were are you okay? Yeah of course no big deal tasting salt. I am curious about something
though. Ask me why would you do this to me? Because we can make it go away Cygnus that's the whole
point. Whatever that was whatever you didn't like about it we know where it is now. We can go back
and damp it out just like that and then we've got days to get it removed permanently if that's what
you want. Just put the cap back on and she put her arms around me drew me close. She smelled like
sand and sweat. I love the way she smelled. For a while I could feel a little bit safe.
For a while I could feel like the bottom wasn't going to drop out at any moment.
Somehow when I was with Chelsea I mattered. I wanted her to hold me forever.
I don't think so I said. No she blinked look up at me. Why ever not? I shrugged.
You know what they say about people who don't remember the past.
Predators run for their dinner. Pray run for their lives. Old ecologists proverb.
We were blind and helpless jammed into a fragile bubble behind enemy lines. But finally the
whispers were silent. The monsters just stayed behind the covers. And a man of bates was out there
with them. What the fuck? Spindle breathed. The eyes behind his faceplate were active and searching.
You can see I asked. He nodded. What happened to Bates? Her soup breach? I don't think so.
Then why'd she say she was dead? What? She meant it literally I told him. Not as I'm as good as dead
or I'm going to die. She met dead now like she was a talking corpse. How did you know? Stupid question.
His face ticked and trembled in the helmet. That's crazy eh? Define crazy. The gang floated
quietly. Cheek to jowl behind Spindle in the cramped enclosure. Cruncher had stopped obsessing
about the leg as soon as we'd sealed up. Or maybe he'd simply been overridden. I thought I saw facets
of Susan in the twitching of those thick-fingered gloves. Spindle's breath echoed second hand over
the link. If Bates is dead then so are we. Maybe not. We wait out the spike we get out of here.
Besides, I added, she wasn't dead. She only said she was.
Fuck. Spindle reached out and pressed his gloved palm against the skin of the tent.
He felt back and forth along the fabric. Someone did put out a transducer.
Eight o'clock, I said, about a meter. Spindle's hand came to rest about across the wall from the pod.
My HUD floated with second hand numbers, vibrated down his arm and relayed to our suits.
Still five Tesla out there, falling though. The tent expanded around us as if breathing,
shrank back in the next second as if some transient low pressure front moved past.
When did your sight come back, I wondered. Soon as we came inside.
Sooner. You saw the battery. Fumbled it, he grunted.
Not that I'm much less of a spaz even when I'm not blind, eh? Bates, you out there?
You reached for it. You almost caught it. That wasn't blind chance.
Not blind chance, blind sight. Amanda, respond please. Blind sight?
Nothing wrong with the receptors, he said distractedly. Brain processes the image,
but I can't access it. Brainstem takes over. Your brainstem can see, but you can't.
Something like that. Shut up and let me- Amanda, can you hear me? No.
No. Not from anyone in the tent, that voice. It had shivered down Spindle's arm,
barely audible with the rest of the data. From outside.
Major Mandy, Spindle exclaimed. You're alive.
No. A whisper like white noise. Well, you're talking to us so you sure as shit ain't dead.
No. Spindle and I exchanged looks. What's the problem, Major?
Major?
Silence. The gang bumped gently against the wall behind us, all fast and opaque.
Major Bates, can you hear me? No.
It was a dead voice, sedated, trapped in the fishbowl, transmitted through limbs and led at
a three digit bod rate, but it was definitely Bates' voice.
Major, you've gotta get in here, Spindle said. Can you come inside?
No. Are you injured? Are you pinned by something?
No. Maybe not her voice, after all. Maybe just her vocal cords.
Look, Amanda, it's dangerous. It's too damn hot out there. Do you understand? You...
I'm not out here, said the voice. Where are you?
Nowhere. I looked at Spindle. Spindle looked at me. Neither of us spoke.
James did. At long last and softly. And what are you, Amanda?
No answer. Are you Rorschach? Here in the belly of the beast, it was so easy to believe.
No. Then what?
Nothing. The voice was flat and mechanical. I'm nothing.
You're saying you don't exist, Spindle said slowly.
Yes. The tent breathed around us.
Then how can you speak, Susan asked the voice. If you don't exist, what are we talking to?
Something else.
A sigh. A breath of static. Not me.
Shit, Spindle muttered. His service has brightened with resolve and sudden insight.
He pulled his hand from the wall. My head thinned instantly.
Her brain's frying. We gotta get her inside. He reached for the release.
I put out my own hand. The spike,
sequestered already, Commisar, and we're past the worst of it.
Are you saying it's safe? It's lethal. It's always lethal, and she's out there in it,
and she could do some serious damage to herself and oppress something bumped the tent from the
outside. Something grabbed the outer catch and pulled. Our shelter opened like an eye.
Amanda Bates looked into this through the exposed membrane.
I'm reading 3.8. She said, that's tolerable, right?
Nobody moved. Come on, people. Breaks over.
I met. Spindle stared. Are you okay? In here? Not likely. We've got a job to do.
Do you exist? I asked. What kind of stupid question is that? Spindle, how's the field
strength? Can we work in it? He swallowed audibly. Maybe we should abort, major. That spike was,
according to my readings, the spike is pretty much over, and we've got less than two hours to
finish setting up, run our ground truths, and then get out of here. Can we do that without
hallucinating? I don't think we'll shake the heebie-jeebies, Spindle admitted, but we shouldn't
have to worry about extreme effects until another spike hits. Good. Which could be at any time.
We weren't hallucinating, James said quietly. We can discuss it later, Bates said. Now,
there was a pattern there, James insisted. In the fields, in my head, Rorschach was talking.
Maybe not to us, but it was talking. Good. Bates pushed herself back to let us past.
Maybe now we can all learn to talk back. Maybe we can learn to listen, James said.
We fled like frightened children with brave faces. We left the base camp behind.
Jack, still miraculously functional in his vestibule, a tunnel into the haunted mansion,
for alluring magnometers left to die in the faint hope they might not.
Crude pyrometers and thermographs, antique radiation-proof devices that measured the
world through the flex and stretch of metal tabs and etched their findings on rolls of plastic.
Glow globes and diving bells and guide ropes strung to one another.
We left it all behind. It promised to return in 36 hours if we lived so long.
Inside each of us, infinitesimal lacerations were turning our cells to mush. Plasma membrane
sprang countless leaks, overwhelmed repair enzymes clung desperately to shredded genes,
and barely delayed the inevitable. Anxious to avoid the rush, patches of my intestinal lining
began flaking away before the rest of the body had a chance to die. By the time we docked with
Theseus, both Michelle and I were feeling nauseous. The rest of the gang, oddly, was not. I had no
idea how that was possible. The others would be presenting the same symptoms within minutes.
Without intervention, we would all be vomiting our guts out for the following two days.
Then the body would pretend to recover. Perhaps a week, we would feel no pain and have no future.
We would walk and talk and move like any living thing and perhaps convince ourselves we were
immortal after all. Then we would collapse into ourselves, rotted from the inside out.
We would bleed from our eyes and mouths and assholes, and if any god was merciful, we would
dive before splitting out open like rotten fruit. But of course, Theseus, our redeemer, would save
us from such a fate. We filed from the shuttle into a great balloon that Sarashti had erected to
capture our personal effects. We shed our contaminated spacesuits and clothing and emerged naked into
the spine. We passed single file through the drum, the flying dead in formation. Yuka Sarashti,
discreetly distant on the turning floor, leapt up in our wake and disappeared aft to feed our
radioactive castoffs into the decompiler. Into the crypt, our coffins lay across the rear bulkhead.
We sank gratefully and wordlessly into their embrace. Bates coughed blood as the lids came down.
My bones hummed as the captain began to shut me off. I went to sleep a dead man. I had only theory
and the assurances of fellow machinery that I would ever be born again. Keaton, come forth.
I woke up ravenous. Faint voices drifted forward from the drum. I floated in my pod for a few moments,
eyes closed, savoring absences. No pain, no nausea, no terrifying subliminal sense of one's own
body sloughing incrementally to mush. Weakness and hunger, otherwise I fell fine. I opened my eyes.
Something like an arm. Gray and glistening, far too, too attenuate to be human. No hand at its tip.
Too many joints, a limb broken in a dozen places. It extended from a body barely visible over the
lip of the pod, a suggestion of dark bulk and other limbs in disjoint motion. It hovered motionless
before me, as if it startled in the midst of some shameful act. By the time I had breath enough to
cry out, it had whipped back out of sight. I erupted from the pod, eyes everywhere. Now they
saw nothing. An empty crypt, a naked note-taker. The mirrored bulk had reflected vacant pods to
either side. I called up consensus, all systems nominal. It didn't reflect, I remembered. The
mirror didn't show it. I headed aft, heart still pounding. The drum opened up around me, spindle
in the gang conversing in low tones aft. Spindle glanced up and waved a trembling hand and greeting.
You need to check me out, I called. My voice wasn't nearly as steady as I'd hoped.
Admitting you have a problem is the first step, spindle called back. Just don't expect miracles.
He turned back to the gang. James on top, they sat in a diagnostic couch, staring at some test
pattern shimmering on the rear bulkhead. I grabbed the tip of a stairway and pulled myself down.
Coriolis pushed me sideways like a flag in the breeze. I'm either hallucinating or there's
something on board. You're hallucinating. I'm serious. So am I. Take a number. Wait your turn.
He was serious. Once I forced myself to calm down and read the signs, I could see he wasn't
even surprised. Guess she's pretty hungry after all that exhausting lying around, eh? Spindle
waved at the galley. Eat something, be with you in a few minutes. I forced myself to work up my
latest synopsis while I ate, but that only took half a mind. The others still shivered in residual
thrall to fight flight. I tried to distract it by tapping the bio med feed. It was real,
James was saying. We all saw it. No, couldn't have been. James cleared his throat. Tried this one.
The feed showed what she saw, a black triangle on a white background.
In the next instant, it shattered into a dozen identical copies and a dozen dozen.
The proliferating brood rotated around the center screen, geometric primitives ballroom dancing in
precise formation, each sprouting smaller triangles from its tip, fractalizing, rotating,
evolving into an infinite intricate tilework. That sketch pad, I realized. An interactive eye
witness reconstruction without the verbiage. Susan's own pattern matching wetwear reacted to what she
saw. No, there were more of them. No, the orientation's wrong. Yes, that's it, but bigger.
And spindle's machine picked those reactions right out of her head and amended the display in real
time. It was a big step up from the half-assed workaround called language. Easily impressed,
mind had even called it mind reading. It wasn't, though. It was all just feedback and correlation.
It doesn't take a telepath to turn one set of patterns into another, fortunately.
That's it, that's it! Susan cried. The triangles had iterated out of existence.
Now the display was full of interlocking asymmetrical pedigrams, a spider web of fish scales.
Don't tell us that's random noise, she said triumphantly.
No, spindle said. It's a clover constant.
Uh, it's a hallucination, Seuss. Of course, but something planted in our head, right? And
it was in your head all along. It was in your head the day you were born. No,
it's an artifact of deep brain structure. Even congenitally blind people see them sometimes.
None of us have ever seen them before, ever. I believe you, but there's no information there,
eh? That wasn't Rorschach talking, it was just interference, like everything else.
But it was so vivid. Not that flickering corner of your eye stuff we saw everywhere,
this was solid. It was realer than real. That's how you can tell it wasn't.
Since you don't actually see it, there's no SE eyeball optics to limit resolution.
Oh, James said, and then softly. Shit. Yeah, sorry. And then, anytime you're ready.
I looked up. Spindle was waving me over. James rose from her chair, but it was Michelle who gave
him a quick disconsolate squeeze, and Sasha who grumbled past me on her way out of the tent.
By the time I reached him, Spindle had unfolded the couch to a half-caught.
Lie down. I did. I wasn't talking about back on Rorschach, you know. I meant here.
I saw something right now when I woke up.
Raise your left hand, he said. Then, just your left, eh? I lowered my right,
winced at the pinprick. That's a bit primitive. He eyed the blood-filled cuvette between his thumb
and forefinger, a shivering ruby teardrop the size of a fingernail. Wet samples still the best for
some things. Aren't the pods supposed to do everything? Spindle nodded. Call it a quality
control test. Keep the ship on its toes. He dropped the sample onto the nearest countertop.
The teardrop flattened and burst. The surface drank my blood as if parched. Spindle spacked his
lips. Elevated, glowing... Koleynester ace inhibitors in the ret. Yum.
For all I knew, my blood results actually did taste good to the man.
Spindle didn't just read the results, he felt them. He smelled and saw and experienced each datum,
like drops of citrus on the tongue. The whole Biomed sub-drum was a part of the...
was but a part of the spindle prostheses. An extended body with dozens of different sensory
modes. Forced to talk to a brain that only knew five. No wonder he'd bonded with Michelle.
He was almost synthetic himself. You spent a bit longer in there than the rest of us, he remarked.
That significant? A jerking shrug. Maybe your organs got a bit more cooked than ours.
Maybe you just got a delicate constitution. Your pod would have caught anything...
imminent, so I figured... ah. What? Some cells along your brain pan going into overdrive,
more on your bladder and kidney. Tumors? What you expect? Or a shock's no reduce, ba.
But the pod... Spindle grimaced, his idea of a reassuring smile. Repairs 99.9% of the damage,
sure. By the time you get to the last 0.1 you're into diminishing returns. These are small, commissar.
Chances are your own bodily would take care of them. If not, we know where they live.
The ones in my brain, could they be causing? Not a chance. He chewed on his lower lip for a moment.
Of course, cancer is not all that thing did to us. What I saw up in the crypt,
it had these multi-jointed arms from a central mass, big as a person maybe.
Spindle nodded. Get used to it. The others are seeing these things?
I doubt it. Everyone is a different take, like... his twitching face conveyed, dare I say it? Rorschach
bots. I was expecting hallucinations in the field, I admitted, but up here. TMS effects.
Spindle snapped his fingers. They're sticky, eh? Neurons get kicked into one state, take a while
to come unstuck. You never got a TAT? Well, just a boy like you? Once or twice, I said. Maybe. Same
principle. So I'm gonna keep seeing this stuff. Party line is they fade over time, week or two,
you're back to normal. But out here with that thing, he shrugged. Too many variables, not the least of
which is, I assume we'll keep going back until Siddasti says otherwise. But they're basically
magnetic effects. Probably, although I'm not betting on anything where that fucker's concerned.
Could something else be causing them? I asked. Something on this ship? Like what?
I don't know. Leakage, enthusiast, magnetic shielding maybe? Not normally. Of course,
we've all got little implanted networks in our heads, eh? And you've got a whole hemisphere
of prosthetics up there. Who knows what kinds of side effects those might let you in for? Why?
Rorschach, not a good enough reason for you? I saw them before, I might have said. And this
spindle would say, oh, when? Where? And then maybe I'd reply, when I was spying on your private life,
and any chances of non-invasive observation be flushed down to the atoms. It's probably nothing.
I've just been jumpy lately. I thought I saw something weird in the spinal bundle back before
we landed on Rorschach. Just for a second, you know, and it disappeared as soon as I focused on it.
One multi-jointed arms with a central mass? God, no. Just a flicker, really. If it was anything at
all, it was probably just a man-as-rubber ball floating around up there. Probably, spindle seemed
almost amused. Couldn't hurt to check for leakage into the shielding, though, just in case. Not like
we need something else making us see things, eh? I shook my head and remembered nightmares.
How are the others? Gang's fine if a bit disappointed. Haven't seen the major. He shrugged.
Maybe she's avoiding me. It hit her pretty hard. Though worse than the rest of us, really. She
might not even remember it. How could she possibly believe she didn't even exist?
Spindle shook his head. Didn't believe it. Knew it. For a fact. But how...
charge gauge in your car, right? Sometimes the contacts corrode. Readout freezes unempty,
so you think it's empty. What else are you supposed to think? Not like you can go in and
count the electrons. You're saying the brain's got some kind of existence gauge? Brain's got all
kinds of gauges. You can know you're blind even when you're not. You can know you can see even
when you're blind. And yeah, you can know you don't exist even when you do. It's a long list, Commissar.
Kotards, Antons, Damascus disease just for starters. He hadn't said blindsight.
What was it like? I asked. Like? Although I knew exactly what I meant.
Did your arm move by itself when it reached for that battery? Oh, no. You're still in control.
You just... you get a feeling, that's all. A sense of where to reach. One part of the brain playing
charades with another, eh? He gestured at the couch. Get off. Seen enough of your ugly guts for now.
And send Bates up here if you can find where she's hiding. Probably back at FAB building a bigger
army. The misgivings glinted off of him like sunlight.
You have a problem with her, I said. He started to deny it then remembered who he was talking to.
Not personally, just human-node running mechanical infantry. Electronic reflexes,
slaved or meat reflexes. You'd tell me where the weak spot is.
Down in Rorschach, I'd have to say all the links are pretty weak.
Not talking about Rorschach, Spindle said. We go there. What stops them from coming here?
Them. Maybe they haven't arrived yet, he admitted. But when they do,
I'm betting we're going up against something bigger than anaerobic microbes.
When I didn't answer, he continued, his voice lowered. And anyway, Mission Control didn't know
shit about Rorschach. They thought they were sending us some place where drones could do
all the heavy lifting. But they just hate not being in command, eh? Can't admit the grunts are
smarter than the generals. So our defenses get compromised for political appearances. Not like
that's any kind of news. And I'm no jarhead, but it strikes me as real bad strategy. I remember
it Amanda Bates, midwifing the birth of her troops. I'm more of a safety precaution. Amanda, I began.
Like Mandy Fine. Nice mammal. But if we're cruising into a combat situation, I don't want my ass
covered by some network held back by its weakest link. If you're going to be surrounded by a swarm
of killer robots, maybe. Yeah, people keep saying that, can't trust the machines. Luddites love to
go on about computer malfunctions and how many accidental wars we might have prevented because
a human had the final say. But funny thing, Commissar, nobody talks about how many intentional wars
got started for the same reason. You still writing those postcards to posterity?
I nodded and didn't wince inwardly. It was just spindle. Well, feel free to stick in this conversation
or the next one for all the good it'll do. Imagine you are a prisoner of war. You've
got to admit you sought coming. You've been crashing tech and seeding biosoles for solid
18 months. That's a good run by anyone's standards. Realist saboteurs do not as a rule enjoy long
careers. Everyone gets caught eventually. It wasn't always thus. There was a day you might have even
hoped for a peaceful retirement. But then they brought the vampires back from the Pleistocene and
great grieving Ganga. Did that ever turn the balance of power upside down? Those fuckers are
always 10 steps ahead. It only makes sense after all hunting people is what bloodsuckers evolved to
do. There's this line from an early pop dine textbook, really old, maybe even Twensen. It's
something of a mantra. Maybe prayer would be a better word among those in your profession.
Predators run for their dinner, it goes. Prey run for their lives. The moral is supposed to be that
on average the hunted escape the hunters because they're more motivated. Maybe that was true when
it all came down to who ran faster. Doesn't seem to hold when the strategy involves tactical force
sight and double reverse mind fucks though. The vampires win every time. And now you're caught.
And while it may have been vampires that set the trap, it was regular turncoat baseline humans who
pulled the trigger. For six hours now you've been gecko to the wall of some unnamed, unlisted,
underground detention facility watching as some of those self sane humans played games with your
boyfriend and co-conspirator. These are not your average games. They involve pliers and glowing
wires and body parts that were not designed to detach. You wish by now that your lover were dead
like the two others in your cell whose parts are scattered around the room. But they're not letting
that happen. They're having too much fun. That's what it all comes down to. This is not an interrogation.
They're less invasive ways to get reliable answers. These are simply a few more sadistic thugs with
authority killing time and other things. And you can only cry and squeeze your ice tight and whimper
like an animal even though they haven't laid a hand on you yet. You can only wish they hadn't saved
you for last because you know what that means. Suddenly your tormentors stop in mid game and
cock their heads as if listening to some collective inner voice. Presumably it tells them to take you
off the wall bring you to the next room and sit you down for in one of two gel padded chairs on
opposite sides of a smart desk because this is what they do far more gently than you'd expect
before retiring. You can also assume that whoever has given these instructions is both powerful and
displeased because all the arrogant sadistic cockiness has drained from their faces in the
space of a heartbeat. You sit and wait. The table glows with soft cryptic symbols that would be of no
earthly interest to you even if you could understand them even if they contain the very secret of the
vampires themselves. Some small part of you wonders if this last development might be cause for hope.
The rest of you doesn't dare believe it. You hate yourself for caring about your own survival when
chunks of your friends and allies are still warm on the other side of the wall. A stocky emmer and
woman appears in the room with you clad in nondescript military weave. Her hair is buzzed short.
Her throat veined with the faint mesh of a sub-q antenna. Your brainstem sees that she is 10 meters
tall even though some impertinent gelatinous overlays insist that she is of only average height.
The name tag on her left breast says Bates. You see no sign of rank. Bates extracts a weapon from
a cheeth on her thigh. You flinch but she does not point it at you. She sets it on the desk
easily within your reach and sits across from you. A microwave pistol fully charged, unlocked.
On its lowest setting it causes sunburn and nausea. On its highest it flash boils brains
in the skull. At any setting in between it inflicts pain and injury and increments as fine as your
imagination. Your imagination has been retooled for great sensitivity along such scales. You stare
numbly at the gun trying to figure the trick. Two of your friends are dead, Bates says, as though
you hadn't just watched them die. Irrecoverably so. Irrecoverably dead. Good one. We could reconstitute
the bodies but the brain damage. Bates clears her throat as if uncomfortable, as if embarrassed.
It's a surprisingly human gesture for a monster. We're trying to save the other one. No promises.
We need information, she says, cutting the bechace. Of course. What came before was psychology,
softening up. Bates is the good cop. I've got nothing to tell you, you manage. It's 10% defiance,
90% deduction. They wouldn't have been able to catch you at all in the first place unless
they already knew everything. Then we need an arrangement, Bates says.
We need to come to some kind of accommodation. She has to be kidding. Your incredulity must be
showing. Bates addresses it. I'm not completely unsympathetic. My gut doesn't much like the idea
of swapping reality for simulation and it doesn't buy that what is truth spin the body economic
cells to get around it. Maybe there's reason to be scared. Not my problem, not my job, just my
opinion and it could be wrong. But if we kill each other in the meantime we don't find out either
way. It's unproductive. You see the dismembered bodies of your friends. You see pieces on the
floor still a little bit alive. And this has the nerve to talk about productivity.
We didn't start it, you say. I don't know and I don't care. Like I said, it's not my job.
Bates jerks a thumb over her shoulder at a door in the wall behind her, the door she
must have entered through. In there, she says, are the ones who killed your friends.
They've been disarmed. When you go through the door the room will go offline and remain
unmonitored for a period of 60 seconds. Nobody besides yourself will ever hold you accountable
for whatever happens in there during that time. It's a trick. It has to be.
What do you have to lose, Bates wonders? We can already do anything we want to you. It's not
like we need you to give us an excuse. Hezitently you take the gun. Bates doesn't stop you.
She's right, you realize. You have absolutely nothing to lose. You stand and suddenly fearless
point the weapon at her face. Why go in there? I can kill you right here.
She shrugs. You could try. Waste of an opportunity if you ask me. So why go in there and I come out
in 60 seconds and then what? Then we talk. We just think of it as a gesture of good faith,
she says. Restitution even. The door opens at your approach, closes in your wake,
and there they are, all four of them spread up across the wall like a chorus line of
Christ's on crosses. There's no gleam in their eyes now. There's only a bright animal terror
and the reflection of turntables. Two of the Christs stain their pants when you look them in the eye.
What's left? Maybe 50 seconds? It's not a lot. You could have done so much more with just a little
extra time, but it's enough and you don't want to impose on the good graces of this base woman
because she may be, she may at last be someone you can deal with.
Under other circumstances, Lieutenant Amanda Bates would have been court-martialed and executed
within the month. No matter who died had been guilty of multiple counts of rape, torture,
and homicide. That's just what people did in wartime. It's what they'd always done. There was
nothing polite about war, no honorable code beyond the chain of command and circling the wagons.
Deal within discretions if you must, punish the guilty if you have to, for appearance of nothing
else, but for God's sake close the doors first. Never give your enemy the satisfaction of seeing
discord in the ranks. Show them nothing but unity and flinty-eyed resolve. There may be
murderers and rapists in our midst, but by God they're our murderers and rapists. You certainly
don't give right of revenge to some terrorist twat over a hundred friendly scraps on our belt.
Still, it was hard to argue with results, a negotiated ceasefire with the third largest
realist franchise in the hemisphere, an immediate 46% decline in terrorist activities throughout
the affected territories, the unconditional cancellation of several in-progress campaigns
which could have seriously compromised three major catacombs and taken out the deluth staging
grounds entirely, all because Lieutenant Amanda Bates, feeling her way through her first command,
had gambled on empathy as a military strategy. It was collaborating with the enemy. It was treason.
It was a betrayal of the rank and file. Diplomats and politicians were supposed to do those things,
not soldiers. Still, results. It was all there in the record. Initiative, creativity,
a willingness to succeed by whatever means necessary at whatever cost. Perhaps those
inclinations needed to be punished, perhaps only tempered. The debate might have gone on forever
if the story hadn't leaked, but it had and suddenly the generals had a hero on their hands.
Sometime during her court-martial, Bates' death sentence turned into a rehabilitation.
The only question was whether it would take place in the Stockade or Officer's College.
As it turned out, Leavenworth had both. It took her to its bosom and squeezed hard enough that
virtually every guarantee- to virtually guarantee promotion, if it didn't kill her first. Three
years later, Major Bates was bound for the stars where she was heard to say, or breaking an entering
series. Spindle was not the first to register doubts. Others had wondered whether her assignment
owed as much to the superior qualifications as to resolution of inconvenient PR. I, of course,
had no opinion one way or the other, but I could see how she might strike some as a double-edged
sword. When the fate of the world hangs in the balance, you want to keep an eye on anyone whose
career-defining moment involves consorting with the enemy. If you can see it, chances are it
doesn't exist. Kate Coe, Grounds for Suicide. Five times we did it. Over five consecutive
orbits we threw ourselves between the monster's jaws, let it chew at us with a trillion microscopic
teeth until Thesias reeled us in and stitched us back together. We crept through Rorschach's belly
in fits and starts, focusing as best we could on the tasks at hand, trying to ignore the ghosts
that tickled our midbrains. Sometimes the walls flecked subtly around us. Sometimes we only
thought they did. Sometimes we took refuge in our diving bell while waves of charge and magnetism
spiraled languidly past, like bullises of ectoplasm coursing down the intestine of some poltergeist
god. Sometimes we got caught in the open. The gang would squabble amongst itself, uncertain which
persona was which. Once I fell into a kind of waking paralysis, while alien hands dragged me
away down the hall. Fortunately, other hands brought me home, and voices that claimed to be real
told me I'd made the whole thing up. Twice, a man debates found God, saw the fucker right there in
front of her, knew beyond any shadow of a doubt that the creator not only existed but spoke to her,
and her alone. Both times she lost her faith once we got her into the bell, but it was touch
and go for a while. Her warrior drones, drunk on power but still under line of sight control,
staggered from their perimeters and pointed their weapons along bearings too close for comfort.
The grunts died fast. Some barely lasted into a single foray. A few died in minutes.
The longest lived were the slowest on the draw. Half blind, thick-witted, every command and
response bottlenecked by raw high-frequency sound buzzing across their shielded eardrums.
Sometimes we backed them up with others that spoke optically, faster but nervous and even more
vulnerable. Together they guarded against an opposition that had not yet shown its face.
It hardly had to. Our troops fell even in the absence of enemy fire.
We worked through it all, through fits and hallucinations and occasional convulsions.
We tried to watch each other's backs while magnetic tendrils tugged our inner ears and made
a seasick. Sometimes we vomited into our helmets. Then we'd just hang on, white-faced, sucking sour
air through clenched teeth while the recyclers filtered chunks and blobs in our headspace.
And we'd give silent thanks for the small mercy of non-stick, static-repellent faceplates.
It rapidly became obvious that my presence served more than cannon fodder.
It didn't matter that I lacked the gang's linguistic skills or spindle's expertise in biology.
I was another set of hands in a place where anyone could be laid out at a moment's notice.
The more people Sarasthi kept in the field, the greater the odds that at least one of them
would be halfway functional at any given moment. Even so, we were in barely any condition to
accomplish anything. Every incursion was an exercise in reckless endangerment.
We did it anyway. It was that or go home.
The work proceeded in infinitesimal increments, hamstrung on every front. The gang wasn't finding
any evidence of signage or a speech to decipher, but the gross mechanics of this thing were easy
enough to observe. Sometimes Rorschach partitioned itself, extruded ridges around its passageways,
like the cartonagia's hoops encircling a human trachea. Over hours, some of them might develop
into contracting irises, into complete septa, lazy as warm candle wax. We seemed to be witnessing the
growth of the structure in discrete segments. Rorschach grew mainly from the tips of its thorns.
We had made our incursion hundreds of meters from the nearest, but evidently the process
extended at least this far back. If it was part of the normal growth process, though,
it was a feeble echo of what must have been going on in the heart of the apical zones.
We couldn't observe those directly, not from inside, barely a hundred meters towards the
thorn the tube grew too lethal even for suicidal flesh. But over those five orbits, Rorschach grew
by another eight percent, as mindless and mechanical as a growing crystal.
Through it all, I tried to do my job. I compiled and collated,
massaged data I would never understand. I watched the systems around me as best I could,
factored each tick and trait into the mix. One part of my mind produced synapses and
synthesis, while another watched, incredulous and uncomprehending. Neither part could trace
where those insights had come from. It was difficult, though. So, Oste wouldn't let me back
outside the system. Every observation was contaminated by my own confounding presence in
the mix. I did my best. I made no suggestions that might affect critical decisions.
In the field, I did what I was told to, and no more. I tried to be like one of Bates' drones,
a simple tool with no initiative and no influence on the group dynamic.
I think I pulled it off, for the most part. My insights accumulated on schedule and piled up
enthusiast transmission stack, unsent. There was too much local interference to get a signal through
to Earth. Spindle was right. The ghosts followed us back. We began to hear voices other than
Sarastis, whispering up the spine. Sometimes even the brightly-lip-wrapped world of the drum would
warp and jiggle from the corner of my eye, and more than once I saw bony, headless phantoms with
too many arms nested in the scaffolding. They seemed solid enough from the corner of my eye
that any spot I focused on faded to shadow, to a dark translucent stain against the background.
They were so very fragile, these ghosts. The mere act of observation drilled holes through them.
Spindle had rattled off to menches like raindrops. I went to consensus for enlightenment and found
a whole other self buried below the limbic system, below the hindbrain, below even the cerebellum.
It lived in the brainstem, and it was older than the vertebrates themselves.
It was self-contained. It heard and saw and felt, independent of all those other parts,
layered over top like evolutionary afterthoughts. It dwelt on nothing but its own survival.
It had no time for planning or abstract analysis, spared effort for only the most rudimentary
sensor processing. But it was fast, and it was dedicated, and it could react to threats in a
fraction of the time it took for its smarter roommates to even become aware of them.
And even when it couldn't, when the obstinate, unyielding neocortex refused to let it off the
leash, still it tried to pass on what it saw, and Isaac Spindle experienced an inevitable sense of
where to reach. In a way, he had a stripped-down version of the gang in his head. Everyone did.
I looked further and found God itself in the meat of the brain, found the static that had
sent baits into rapture and Michelle into convulsions. I tracked Grey's syndrome to its headwaters in
the temporal lobe. I heard voices ranting in the brains of Schizophrenics. I found cortical infarcts
that inspired people to reject their own limbs. Imagine the magnetic fields that must have acted
in their stead when Cruncher tried to dismember himself. An often some half-forgotten pest-hole
of 20th-century case studies, filed under Katard's syndrome. I found a man to baits and others of
her kind, their brains torqued into denial of the very self. I used to have a heart, one of them
said listlessly from the archives. Now I have something that beats in its place. Another demanded
to be buried because his corpse was already stinking. There was more, a whole catalogue of
finely-tuned dysfunctions that Rorschach had not yet inflicted on us. Some nambulism. Agnosias.
Heminegalact. Consensus served up a freak show to make any mind real at its own fragility.
A woman dying of thirst with an easy reach of water, not because she couldn't see the faucet,
but because she couldn't recognize it. A man for whom the left side of the universe did not exist,
who could neither perceive nor conceive of the left side of his body, of a room, of a line of
text. A man for whom the very concept of leftness had become literally unthinkable. Sometimes we
could conceive of things and still not see them, although they stood right before us.
Skyscrapers appeared out of thin air, and the person talking to us changed into something else
during a momentary distraction, and we didn't notice. It wasn't even magic. It was barely even
misdirection. They called it inattentional blindness, and it had been well known for a
century or more. Tendency for the eye to simply not notice. Things that evolutionary experience
classed as unlikely. I found the opposite of Spindle's blind sight. A malady not in which
the sighted believe they are blind, but one in which the blind insist they can see. The very
idea was absurd unto insanity, and yet there were, there they were, retinas detached,
optic nerves burned away, any possibility of vision denied by the laws of physics,
bumping into walls, stripping over furniture, inventing endless ludicrous explanations for
their clumsiness. The lights unexpectedly turned off by some other party. A colorful bird glimps
through the window, distracting attention from the obstacle ahead. I can see perfectly well,
thank you. Nothing wrong with my eyes. Gages in the head, Spindle called them. But there were other
things in there too. There was a model of the world, and we didn't look outward at all. Our
conscious selves saw only the simulation in our heads, an interpretation of reality, endlessly
refreshed by input from the senses. What happens when those senses go dark, but the model, throw
it off kilter by some trauma or tumor, fails to refresh? How long do we stare in at that obsolete
rendering, recycling and massaging the same old data and desperate subconscious active, utterly
honest denial? How long before it dawns on us that the world we see no longer reflects the world
we inhabit, that we are blind? Months sometimes, according to the case files, for one poor woman
a year and more, appeals to logic fail entirely. How could you see the bird when there is no window?
How do you decide where your seen half world ends and you can't see the other half to wait
against? If you are dead, how can you smell your own corruption? If you do not exist, Amanda,
what is talking to us now? Useless. When you're in the grip of Katara's syndrome or having neglect,
you cannot be swayed by argument. When you're enthralled to some alien artifact, you know the
self is gone, that reality ends at the midline. You know it with the same unshakable certainty of
any man regarding the location of his own limbs, with that hard-wired awareness that needs no
other confirmation. Against that conviction, what is reason? What is logic? Inside Rorschach,
they had no place at all. On the sixth orbit, it acted. It's talking to us, James said. Her eyes
were wide behind the faceplate, but not bright, not manic. Around us, Rorschach's guts oozed and
crawled at the corner of my eye. It still took effort to ignore the illusion. Foreign words
scrambled like small animals below my brainstem as I tried to focus on a ring of finger-sized
protrusions that picketed a patch of wall. It's not talking, Spindle said from across the artery.
You're hallucinating again. Bates said nothing. Two grunts hovered in the middle of the space,
panning across three axes. It's different this time, James insisted. The geometry, it's not so
symmetrical, looks almost like the Feistos disc. She spun slowly, pointing down the passage.
I think it's stronger down here. Bring Michelle out, Spindle suggested. Maybe she can talk some
sense into you. James laughed weakly. Never say die, do you? She tweaked her pistol and
coasted it into the deeper gloom. Yes, it's definitely stronger here. There's content super
opposed on... quick as a blink. Rorschach cut her off. James laughed weakly. Never say die, do you?
She tweaked her pistol and coasted it into deeper gloom. Yes, it's definitely stronger here. There's
content superimposed on... quick as a blink. Rorschach cut her off. I'd never seen anything move so
fast before. There was none of the languor we'd grown accustomed to from Rorschach's septa,
no lazy drift of contraction. The iris snapped shut in an instant. Suddenly the artery just
ended three meters ahead with a matte black membrane filigree in fine spiral. And the
gang of four was on the other side. The grunts were on it immediately, lasers crackling through
the air. Bates was yelling, get behind me, stick to the walls, kicking herself into space like
an acrobat and fast forward, taking some tactical high ground that must have been obvious to her,
at least. I edged towards the perimeter. Threads of superheated plasma sliced the air, shimmering.
Spindle at the corner of my eye hugged the opposite side of the tunnel. The walls crawled.
I could see the lasers taking it all. The septum peeled back from their torch like burning paper,
black oily smoke writhing in its crisping edges and sudden brightness everywhere. A riot of
fractured light flooded the artery, a thousand shifting angles of incidence and reflection.
It was like being trapped in the belly of a kaleidoscope pointed at the sun,
light, and a needle-sharp pain in my side, in my left arm, the smell of charred meat, a scream cut
off. Susan, you there, Susan? We're taking you first. Around me the light died. Inside us
me a swarm of floaters mixed it up to the chronic half-visions Rorschach had already planted in my
hedge. Alarms chirped irritatingly in my helmet, breech, breech, breech, until the small fabric
of the suit softened and congealed where the holes had been. Something stung maddeningly in my left
side. I felt as if I had been branded. Kaden, check spindle! Bates had called off the lasers.
The grunts closed for hand-to-hand, reaching with fiery nozzles and diamond-tip claws to grapple
with some prismatic material glowing softly behind that burnt black skin. The fibrous reflector, I
realized. It had shattered the laser light, termed it to luminous shrapnel and thrown it back at our
faces. Clever. But its surface was still light, even with the lasers down. A diffuse glow,
dipping and weaving, filtered from the far side of the barrier while the drones chewed doggedly
through the near one. After a moment and struck me, James headlamp.
Kaden! Right, spindle. His faceplate was intact. The laser had melted the Faraday mesh laminated
onto the crystal, but the suit was sealing a tiny hole even now. The hole behind,
drilled neatly through his forehead, remained. The eyes beneath stared at infinity.
Well, Bates asked. She could read the vitals as easily as I, but Thesias was capable of post-mortem
rebuilds. Barring brain damage. No. The whine of drills and shredders stopped. The ambience
brightened. I looked away from spindle's remains. The grunts had cut a hole in the septum's fibrous
underlayer. One of them nosed its way through the other side. A new sound rose into the mix.
A soft animal keening haunted and dissonant. For a moment I thought Rorschach was whispering to us
again. Its walls seemed to contract slightly around me. James? Bates snapped. James!
Not James. A little girl in a woman's body in an armored space suit, scared out of her wits.
The grunt nudged her curled-up body back into our company. Bates took it gently.
Susan? Come back, Suze. You're safe. The grunts hovered restlessly,
alert in every direction, pretending everything was under control. Bates spared me a glance.
Take Isaac and turn back to James. Susan?
No. Whispered a small voice. A little girl's voice.
Michelle? Is that you?
There was a thing, the little girl said. It grabbed me. It grabbed my leg.
We're out of here. Bates pulled the gang back along the passage.
One grunt lingered, watching the whole. The other took point.
It's gone, Bates said gently. There's nothing there now. See the feed?
You can't see it, Michelle whispered. It's in... it's invisible.
The septum receded around a curve as we retreated. The whole torn through its center watched us,
like the ragged pupil of some great unblinking eye. It stayed empty as long as it had
stayed in sight. Nothing came out after us, nothing we could see.
A thought began cycling through my head. Some half-assed eulogy stolen from an eavesdropped
confessional. Tries I might, I couldn't shut it down. Isaac Spindle hadn't made the semi-finals after all.
Susan James came back to us on the way up. Isaac Spindle did not.
We stripped wordlessly in the Deacon Balloon. Bates, first out of her suit, reached for Spindle,
but the gang stopped her with a hand and a head shake. Persona segwayed into one another as
they stripped the body. Susan removed helmet and backpack and breastplate. Cruncher peeled away
the silvery-ledded skin from collar to toe. Sasha stripped the jumpsuit and left the pale
flesh naked and exposed. Except for the gloves. They left his feedback gloves in place, their
fingertips forever tactile, the flesh inside forever numb. Through it all Spindle stared
unblinking beneath the hole in his forehead. His glazed eyes focused on distant quasars.
I expected Michelle to appear in her turn and close them, but she never did.
You have eyes, but you do not see. Jesus then Azorian.
I don't know how to feel about this, I thought. He was a good man. He was decent. He was kind to me,
even when he didn't know I was listening in. I didn't know him long. He wasn't a friend exactly,
but still. I should miss him. I should mourn. I should feel more than this sick, sinking fear
that I could be next. So Dosty hadn't wasted any time. Spindle's replacement met us as we emerged,
freshly thawed Nicotine sent him. The rehydration of his flesh was ongoing.
Saline bladders clung to each thigh, although it would never erase the sharpness of his features.
His bones cracked when he moved. He looked past me and took the body.
Susan, Michelle, I… the gang turned away. He coughed, began fumbling a body condom over the corpse.
Sldosty wants everyone in the drum.
We're hot, Bates said. Even cut short, the excursion had piled up a lethal seaward count.
Faint nausea tickled the back of my throat. Decontaminate later.
One long pull of a zipper and Spindle was gone, engulfed in an oily gray shroud.
You, he turned in my direction, pointed at the scorched holes in my dump suit, with me.
Robert Cunningham. Another prototype. Dark-haired, hollow-cheeked, a jaw you could use as a ruler.
Both smoother and harsher than the man he'd replaced.
Where Spindle had ticked and jerked as if static-charged, Cunningham's face held
all the expression of a waxed dummies. The wet-wear that ran those muscles had been
press-gangued into other pursuits. Even the tremors that afflicted the rest of the body were muted,
soothed by the nicotine he drew with every second breath.
He held no cigarette now. He held only the shrouded body of his hard luck primary in his
ongoing, fleshly thawed distaste for the ship's synthesis.
His fingers trembled.
Bates and the gang moved silently up the spine. Cunningham and I followed,
guiding the shroud of Spindle between us. My leg and side were stinging again now that Cunningham
had reminded them to. There wouldn't be much he could do about them, though. The beams would
have cauterized the flesh on their way through. And if they'd hit anything vital, I'd have been
dead already. At the hatch we broke into single file. Spindle first, Cunningham pushing at his heels.
By the time I emerged into the drum, Bates and the gang were already down on deck and taking
their usual seats. Siddhasthi, in the flesh, watched them from the end of the conference table.
His eyes were naked. From this angle, the soft, full-strecked-room light of the drum
washed the shine from them. If you didn't look too closely for too long, you might almost think
those eyes were human. Biomed had been spun down from my arrival. Cunningham pointed to a
diagnostic couch on a section of the still deck that had served as our infirmary. I floated over
and strapped myself in. Two meters away, past a waist-high guardrail that had been risen from
the deck, the rest of the drum rolled smoothly past. It slung Bates and the gang and Siddhasthi
around like weights on a string. I tapped consensus to hear them. James was speaking,
quietly without expression. I noticed a new pattern in the form constant, something in the
grating. It looked like a signal. It got stronger as I went down the tunnel. I followed it. I blacked
out. I don't remember anything more until we were on our way back. Michelle filled me in as much as
she could. That's all I know. Sorry. A hundred degrees away in the no-G zone, Cunningham maneuvered
his predecessor into a coffin with different options than those up front.
I wondered if it would embark on an autopsy during the debriefing. I wondered if we'd be able to hear
the sounds it made. Sasha, Siddhasthi said. Yeah? Sasha's trademark drawl infected the voice.
I was writing, Mom. Went deaf dumb and stark fucking blind when she passed out. I tried to take over
but something was blocking me. Michelle, I guess. Never thought she had it in her. I couldn't even see.
But you don't lose consciousness. I was awake the whole time, far as I know, just completely in the
dark. Smell, tactile. I could feel it when Michelle pissed in the suit, but I didn't notice anything
else. Cunningham was back at my side. The inevitable cigarette had appeared between his lips.
Nothing touches you, the vampire surmised. Nothing grabs your leg.
No, Sasha said. She didn't believe Michelle's stories about invisible monsters. None of us did.
Why bother when dementia could so easily explain anything we experienced?
Cruncher. Don't know anything. I still wasn't used to the maleness of the voice now emanating from
James Throat. Cruncher was a workaholic. He hardly ever surfaced in mixed company.
You're there, Sadastia reminded him. You must remember some...
Mom sent me patterns to parse. I was working on them. I'm still working on them, he added
pointedly. I didn't notice anything. Is that all? I'd never been able to get a good read on him.
Sometimes Cruncher seemed to have more in common with the dozens of non-conscious modules working
in James' head than the sentient hubs comprising the rest of the gang.
You feel nothing? Sadastia pressed. Just the patterns.
Anything significant? Standard phenomath spirals and gradings, but I haven't finished. Can I go now?
Yes, call Michelle, please. Cunningham stabbed at my wounds with anabolizers,
muttering to himself. Faint blue smoke curled between us.
Isaac found some tumors, he observed. I nodded and coughed. My throat was sore.
The nausea had grown heavy enough to sink below my diaphragm.
Michelle, Sadastia repeated.
I see some more here, Cunningham continued, along the bottom of your brain pan. Only a few
dozen cells so far, they're not worth burning yet. Here, Michelle's voice was barely audible,
even through consensus. But at least it was the voice of an adult. I'm here.
What do you remember, please?
I... I felt... I was just writing mom, and then she was gone, and there was no one else,
so I had to take over. Do you see the septum close?
Not really. I felt it going dark, but when I turned around we were already trapped,
and then I felt something behind me. It wasn't loud or harsh, it just sort of bumped,
and it grabbed me and... and... I'm sorry, she said after a moment. I'm a bit woozy.
Sadastia waited. Isaac, Michelle whispered, he... yes, a pause.
We're very sorry about that. Maybe... can he be fixed? No, there's brain damage.
There was something like sympathy in the vampire's voice, the practice defection of an
accomplished mimic. There was something else too, an all but imperceptible hunger,
a subtle edge of temptation. I don't think anyone heard it but me. We were sick and getting sicker.
Predators are drawn to the weak and injured.
Michelle had fallen silent again, when she continued her voice only faltered a little.
I can't tell you much, it grabbed me, it let me go. I went to pieces and I can't explain why
except that fucking place just does things to you and I was... weak. I'm sorry, there's not much
else to tell you. Thank you, Sadastia said after a long moment. Can I... I'd like to leave if that's
okay? Yes, Sadastia said. Michelle sank below the surface as the commons rotated past. I didn't see
who took her place. The grunts didn't see anything, Bates remarked. By the time we broke through the
septum the tunnel behind was empty. Any bogey would have had plenty of time to hightail, Cunningham
said. He planted his feet on the deck and grabbed a handhold, the sub-drum began to move. I drifted
obliquely against my restraints. I don't disagree, Bates said, but if there's anything we've learned
about that place it's that we can't trust our senses. Trust Michelle's, Sadastia said. He opened
a window as I grew heavier, a grunt's eye view of a fuzzy bright blob weaving behind the translucent
waxed paper fibers of the skin septum. James headlight from the wrong side of the barrier.
The image wobbled a bit as the drone staggered through some local pocket of magnetism then
replayed. Wobbled, replayed. A six second loop. See something next to the gang.
Non-vampires saw no such thing. Sadastia froze the image evidently realizing as much.
Diffraction patterns aren't consistent with a single light source in open space.
I see dimmer elements, reflective elements. Two dark objects close together, similar size,
scattering light here. A cursor appeared, two utterly nondescript points on the image,
and here. One's the gang, the other's unaccounted for.
Just a minute, Cunningham said. If you can see through all that, why didn't Su-
why didn't Michelle see anything?
Th-Synthesiac, Sarastia reminded him. You see. She feels.
Biomed jerked slightly, locking into sink spin with the drum.
The guardrail sank back onto the deck. Often some far off corner, something without eyes,
watched me with it and watching it.
Shit, Bates whispered. There's someone home.
They never really talked like that, by the way. You'd hear gibberish.
Half dozen languages, whole battle of personal idioms, if I spoke in their real voices.
Some of the simpler ticks make it through. Sasha's good-natured belligerence,
Sarastia's aversion to past tense. Cunningham lost most of his gender pronouns to an
unforeseen glitch during the work on his temporal lobe, but it went beyond that.
The whole of them threw English and Hindi and Hadzane into every sing- every second sentence.
No real scientist would allow their thoughts to be hamstrung by the conceptual limitations
of a single language. Other times they acted almost as synthesis in their own right,
conversing in grunts and gestures that would be meaningless to any baseline.
It's not so much that the bleeding edge lacks social skills, it's just that once you get past
a certain point, formal speech is too damn slow. Except for Susan James. The walking contradiction,
the woman so devoted to communication as unifier that she'd cut her own brain into disunified
chunks to make the point. She was the only one who ever seemed to care who she was talking to.
The other spoke only for themselves, even when they spoke to each other. Even James's other
cores would speak their own minds in their own way and let everyone else translate as best they
could. It wasn't a problem, any of her own enthusiasts could read everyone else. But that
didn't matter to Susan James. She fit each of her words to their intended recipient. She accommodated.
I am a conduit. I exist to bridge the gap and I'd bridge nothing if I only told you what these
people said. So I am telling you what they meant and it will mean as much to you as you can handle.
Except for Susan James, linguist and ringleader, who I trust to speak for herself.
Fifteen minutes to Apogee, maximum safe distance in case Rorschach decided to hit back.
Far below the artifacts magnetic field pressed into Ben's atmosphere like God's little finger.
Great dark thunderheads converged behind it. Turbulent moon-sized curlicues collided in its
wake. Fifteen minutes to Apogee and Bates was still hoping Sarasthi would change his mind.
In a way this was her fault. If she had just treated this new travail as one more cross to bear,
perhaps things would have gone on more or less as before. There would have been some faint hope
that Sarasthi would let us grit our teeth and keep on going, besieged now by spring-loaded
trap doors as well as the usual gauntlet of sieverts and magnets and monsters from the Id.
But Bates had made an issue out of it. It wasn't just another piece of shit in the sewer to her.
It was the one that clogged the pipe. We're on the brink as it is, just surviving the baseline
environment of this thing. If it started taking deliberate countermeasures, I don't see how we
can risk it. Fourteen minutes to Apogee and Amanda Bates was still regretting those words.
On previous expeditions we'd charted 26 septa in various stages of development.
We'd X-rayed them. We'd done ultrasound. We'd watched them ooze their way across passages
or ebb slowly back into the walls. The iris that had snapped shut behind the gang of four had been
a whole different animal. And what are the odds that the first one with a hair trigger just happened
also come with anti-laser prismatics? That was no routine growth event. That thing was set for us.
Set by, that was the other thing, 13 minutes to Apogee and Bates was worried about the tenants.
It had always been breaking and entering, of course. That much hadn't changed. But when we'd
jimmied the lock, we thought we were vandalizing an empty summer cottage still under construction.
We thought the owners would be out of the picture for a while. We hadn't been expecting one of them
to catch us on his way to take a late night piss. And now that one had and vanished into the labyrinth,
we're not sure what weapons it might keep stashed under the pillow. Those septic could spring on us at any time.
How many are there? Aren't they fixed or portable? We can't proceed without knowing these things.
At first, Bates had been surprised and delighted when Sarashti agreed with her.
12 minutes to Apogee. From this high ground, well above the static, Thesias peered down through
war shocks, wrenched and twisted anatomy to keep rock-steady eyes on the tiny wound we'd burned
in its side. Our limpid tent covered it like a blister. Inside, Jack fetus a second first-person
view of the unfolding experiment. Sir, we know roar shock is inhabited. Do we want to risk further
provoking the inhabitants? Do we want to risk killing them? Sarashti hadn't quite looked at her and
hadn't quite spoken. If he had, he might have said, I do not understand how meat like you survive to
adulthood. 11 minutes to Apogee and Amanda Bates was lamenting the fact, not for the first time,
that this mission was not under military jurisdiction. We were waiting for maximum
distance before performing the experiment. Roar shock might interpret this as a hostile act,
Sarashti had conceded in a voice that contained no trace of irony whatsoever.
Now he stood before us, watching consensus play on the table. Reflections rived across his naked
eyes, not quite masking the deeper reflections behind them. 10 minutes to Apogee. Susan James
was wishing that Cunningham would put out that goddamn cigarette. The smoke stank on its way to
the ventilators, and anyway it wasn't necessary. It was just an anachronistic affectation, an
attention-getting device. If he needed the nicotine, a patch could have soothed his tremors just as
easily without the smoke and the stink. That wasn't all she was thinking, though. She was wondering
why Cunningham had been summoned to Sarashti's quarters earlier in the shift, why he'd looked
at her so strangely afterwards. I wondered about that myself. A quick check on the consensus timestamps
showed that her medical file had been accessed during that period. I checked those stats,
let the shapes bounce between hemispheres, part of my brain locked on elevated oxytocin,
as the probable reason for that conference. There was an 82% chance that James had become too
trusting for Sarashti's liking. I had no idea how I knew that. I never did.
9 minutes to Apogee. Barely a molecule of Rorschach's atmosphere had been lost on our account.
That was about to change. Our view of base camp split like a dividing bacterium.
One window now focused on the limpet tent, the other on a wide-angle tactical enhance of the
space around it. 8 minutes to Apogee. Sarashti pulled the plug. Down on Rorschach, our tent
burst like a bug beneath a boot. A geyser erupted from the wound. A snowstorm swirled its edges.
Its charged curlicues intricate as lace. Atmosphere gushed into vacuum, spread thin, crystallized.
Briefly, the space around base camp sparkled. It was almost beautiful.
Bates didn't think it was beautiful at all. She watched that bleeding wound with a face as
expressionless as Cunningham's, but her job was cleansed onto tetanus. Her eyes darted
between views, watching for things gasping in the shadows. Rorschach convulsed.
Vast trunks and artery shuttered, a seismic tremor radiating out along the structure.
The epicenter began to twist, a vast segment rotating on its axis,
the breach midway along its length. Stress lines appeared, where the length rotated sheared against
the lengths to either side that didn't. The structure seemed to soften and stretch there,
constricting like a great elongate balloon, torquing itself into sausage links.
Sarashti clicked. Cats made something like that sound when they spied a bird on the far
side of a window pane. Consensus groaned with the sound of world scraping against each other,
telemetry from the on-site sensors, their ears to the ground.
Jack's camera controls had frozen again. The image it sent was canted and grainy. The pick-up
stared blankly at the edge of the hole we'd bored into the underworld. The groaning subsided.
A final faint cloud of crystal and stardust dissipated into space, barely visible even on
max enhance. No bodies, none visible anyway. Sudden motion at base camp. At first I thought it was
static on Jack's feed, playing along lines of high contrast, but no, something was definitely
moving along the edges of the hole we'd burned. Something almost wriggled there, a thousand
degree mycelia extruding from the cut surface and writhing slowly into the darkness.
It's... huh, Bates said. Triggered by the pressure drop, I guess. That's one way to seal a breach.
Two weeks after we wounded it, Rorschach had begun to heal itself.
Apigee behind us now. All downhill from here. Thesias began the long drop back into enemy
territory. Doesn't use scepta, Sarasti said.
My genes done gone and tricked my brain by making fucking feel so great. That's how the little creeps
attain their plan to fucking replicate. But brains got tricks itself, you see. To get the bang, but
not the bite. I got this here vasectomy. My genes can fuck themselves tonight. The arselectors
trunclade. First person sex, real sex, as Chelsea insisted on calling it, was an acquired taste.
Jagged breathing, the raw slap and stink of sweaty skin full of pores and blemishes,
a whole other person with a whole other set of demands and dislikes. There was definite
animal peel, no doubt about it. This was, after all, how we'd done it for millions of years.
But this, the third world calamity, had always carried an element of struggle,
of asynchronous patterns and conflict. There was no convergence here. There was only the rhythm of
bodies and collision, a struggle for dominance, each trying to force the other into sync.
Chelsea regarded it as love in its purest form. I came to think of it as hand to hand combat.
Before, whether fucking creations from my own menu or slip on skins from someone else's,
I had always selected the contrast and the res, the texture and the attitude,
the bodily functions, the resistance of competing desires, the endless foreplay that wears your
tongue to the root and leaves your face sticky and glistening. Just kinks today. Options for the
masochistic. But there were no options with Chelsea. With her everything came standard.
I indulged her. I guess I was no more patient with her perversions than she was with my
ineptitude at them. Other things made it worth the effort. Chelsea would argue about anything under
the sun. Ryan insightful and curious as a cat. She would pounce without warning. Retired to the
redundant majority, she still took such simple joy in the very act of being alive. She was impulsive
and impetuous. She cared about people. Pag. Me. She wanted to know me. She wanted in. That was proving
to be a problem. We could try it again. She said once in an aftermath of sweat and pheromones.
And you won't even remember what you were so upset about. You won't even remember you were upset if
you don't want to. I smiled and looked away. Suddenly the planes of her face were coarse and
unappealing. How many times is that now? Eight? Nine? I just want you to be happy, Sig. True happiness
is one hell of a gift. And I can give it to you if you'll let me. You don't want me happy, I said
pleasantly. You want me customized. She mmmed into the hollow of my throat for a moment. Then
what? You just want to change me into something more more accommodating.
Chelsea lifted her head. Look at me. I turned my head. She'd shut down the chromatophores in
her cheek. The tattoo transplanted, fluttered now on her shoulder.
Look at my eyes, Chelsea said. I looked at the imperfect skin around them, at the capillaries
wriggling across the whites. I felt distant amusement that such flawed decaying organs were
still able to hypnotize me on occasion. Now, Chelsea said, what do you mean by that? I shrugged.
You keep pretending this is a partnership. We both know it's a competition.
A competition. You're trying to manipulate me into playing by your rules. What rules?
The way you want the relationship run. I don't blame you, Chelsea, not in the least.
We've been trying to manipulate each other for as long as, hell, it's not even human nature,
it's mammalian. I don't believe it, she shook her head. Ropey tendrils of hair swung across her face.
It's the middle of the 21st century and you're hitting me with this war of the sexes bullshit?
Granted, your tweaks are a pretty radical iteration. Get right in there and reprogram
your mate for optimum servility. You actually think I'm trying to housebreak you. You think
I'm trying to train you like a puppy. You're just doing what comes naturally.
I can't believe you'd pulled a shit on me. I thought you valued honesty in relationships.
What relationship? According to you, there's no such thing. This is just
mutual rape or something. That's what relationships are. Don't pull that shit on me.
She sat up, swung her feet over the edge of the bed, putting her back to me. I know how I feel.
If I know anything, I know that much. And I only wanted to make you happy.
I know you believe that, I said gently. I know it doesn't feel like a strategy.
Nothing does when it's wired that deeply. It just feels right. It feels natural.
It's nature's trick. It's someone's fucking trick. I sat up next to her, let my shoulder brush hers.
She leaned away. I know this stuff, I said after a while. I know how people work. It's my job.
It was hers too, for that matter. Nobody who sliced brains for a living could possibly be
unaware of all that basic wiring in the subbasement. Chelsea had simply chosen to ignore it. To have
admitted anything would have compromised her righteous anger. I could have pointed that out too,
I suppose, but I knew how much stress the system could take and I wasn't ready to test it to
destruction. I didn't want to lose her. I didn't want to lose that feeling of safety. That sense
that it made a difference whether I lived or died. I only wanted her to back off a bit. I only wanted
room to breathe. You can be such a reptile sometimes, she said. Mission accomplished.
Our first approach had been all caution and safety margins. This time we came in like a
strike force. Silla burned towards a workshop at over two Gs, its trajectory a smooth and predictable
arc ending at the ruptured base camp. It may have even landed there for all I know. Perhaps Sotosti
had too burdened the mission, programmed the shuttle for some collecting of its own. If so,
it wouldn't land with us on board. Silla spat us into space almost 50 kilometers short of the new
beachhead, left us naked and plummeting on some wireframe contraption with barely enough reaction
mass for a soft landing and a quick getaway. We didn't even have control over that. Success
depended on unpredictability and how better to ensure than to not even know ourselves that we
were doing. Sotosti's logic. Vampire logic. We could follow it partway, the colossal deformation
that had sealed Warshawk's breach was so much slower, so much more expensive than the drop gate
that had trapped the gang. The fact that drop gates hadn't been used implied that they took
climb to deploy. To redistribute necessary mass perhaps, or spring load its reflexes.
That gave us a window. We could still venture into the den so long as the lions couldn't predict
our destination and set traps in advance. So long as we got out again before they could set them
afterwards. 37 minutes, Sotosti had said, and none of us could fathom how he'd come to that number.
Only Bates stared to ask aloud and he merely glinted at her. You can't follow. Vampire logic.
From an obvious premise to an opaque conclusion. Our lives depended on it.
The retros followed some pre-programmed algorithm that made it Newton with the role of the dice.
Our vector wasn't completely random. Once we'd eliminated raceways and growth zones,
areas without line of sight escape routes, dead ends and unbranched segments,
boring, Sotosti had said, dismissing them. Barely 10% of the artifact remained in the running.
Now we dropped towards a warren of brambles eight kilometers from our original landing site.
Here in the midst of our final approach, there was no way that even we could predict our precise
point of impact. If Rorschach could, it deserved to win. We fell. Ridged spires and gnarled limbs
sectioned the sky wherever I looked, cut the distance darscape and the imminent super-Jovian
into a jagged mosaic vein in black. Three kilometers away or 30, the tip of some swollen
extremity burst in a silent explosion of charged particles, a distant fog of ruptured,
freezing atmosphere. Even as it faded, I could make out wisps and streamers swirling into complex
spirals, Rorschach's magnetic field sculpting the artifact's very breath into radioactive sleet.
I'd never seen it with naked eyes before. I felt like an insect on starry midwinter's night,
falling through the aftermath of a forest fire. The sled fired its brakes. I snapped back against
the webbing of my harness, bumped against the rebounding armored body next to me.
Sasha. Only Sasha, I remembered. Cunningham had sedated the rest of them, left this one core
lonely and alone in the group body. I hadn't even realized that was possible with multiple personalities.
She stared back at me from behind her faceplate. None of her services showed through the suit.
I could see nothing in her eyes. This was happening so often these days.
Cunningham was not with us. Nobody asked why when Sadastia signed the births.
The biologist was first among equals now, a backup restored with no other behind him,
the second least replaceable of our irreplaceable crew. It made me a better bargain. The odds I
bought had increased to one in three. A silent bump shuttered up the frame. I looked forward again,
passed baits on the front pallet, passed the anchored drones that flanked her two to each side.
The sled had launched its assault, a prefab inflatable vestibule, mounted on an explosive
injection assembly that would punch through Rorschach's skin like a virus penetrating a host cell.
The spindle-legged contraption dwindled and disappeared from my sight.
Moments later a pinpoint sodium sun flared and died against the adony landscape ahead.
Anti-meta charge, so small you could almost count the atoms shot directly into the hull.
A lot rougher than the tentative foreplay of our first date.
We landed hard while the vestibule was still inflating.
The grunts were off the sled an instant before contact, spitting tiny puffs of gas in their
nozzles, arranging themselves around us in a protective rosette. Bates was up next,
leaping free of her restraint since sailing directly towards the swelling hab.
Sasha and I unloaded the fiber off hub, a clamshell drum half a meter thick and three times as wide,
lugging it between us while one of the grunts slipped through the vestibule's membranous airlock.
Let's move, people. Bates was hanging off one of the inflatable's handholds.
Thirty minutes to... she fell silent. I didn't have to ask why. The advanced grunt had positioned
itself over the newly blasted entrance and sent back its first postcard. Light from below.
You'd think that would have made it easier. Our kind has always feared the dark. For millions
of years we huddled in caves and burrows while unseen things snuffled and growled,
or just waited, silent and undetectable, in the night beyond. You'd think that any light,
no matter how meagre, might strip away some of the shadows, leave fewer holes to the mind to
fill with worst imaginings. You'd think. We followed the grunt down into a dim soupy glow like blood
curdled milk. At first it seemed as though the atmosphere itself was a light, a luminous fog
that obscured anything more than ten meters distant. An illusion, as it turned out, the tunnel we
emerged into was about three meters wide and lit by rows of raised glowing dashes, the size and
approximate shape of human fingers, wound in a loose triple helix around the walls. We'd recorded
similar ridges at the first sight, although the breaks had not been so pronounced and the ridges
had been anything but luminous. Stronger than an near-infrared, Bates reported, flashing a spectrum
to our huds. The air would have been transparent to pit-fipers. It was transparent to sonar.
The lead grunt sprayed the fog with click-trains and discovered the tunnel widened into some kind
of chamber 17 meters further along. Squinting in that direction, I could just make out subterranean
outlines of the mist. I could just make out jawed things, pulling back out of sight.
Let's go, Bates said. We plugged in the grunts, left one guarding the way out. Each of us took
another as a guardian angel on point. The machine spoke to our huds via laser link. They spoke to
each other along stiffened lengths of shielded fiber-op that unspooled from the hub trailing in
our wake. It was the best available compromise in an environment without any optima. Our tethered
bodyguards would keep us all in touch during lone excursions around corners or down dead ends.
Yeah. Lone excursions. Forced to either split the group or cover less ground, we were to split the
group. We were speed cartographers panning for gold. Everything we did here was an act of faith.
Faith that the unifying principles of Rorschach's internal architecture could be derived from the
raw dimensions we'd grab on the run. Faith that Rorschach's internal architecture even had unifying
principles. Earlier generations had worshipped malign and capricious spirits. Ours put its faith
in an ordered universe. Here in the Devil's Baklava, it was easy to wonder if our ancestors
hadn't been closer to the mark. We moved along the tunnel. Our destination resolved to merely
humanize. Not so much chamber as nexus, a knot of space formed by the convergence of a dozen
tunnels angling in from different orientations. Ragged meshes of quick silver dots gleamed
along several glistening surfaces. Shiny protrusions poked through the substrate like a scattershot
blast of ball bearings pressed into wet clay. I looked at Bates and Sasha. Control panel?
Bates shrugged. Her drones panned the throats around us, spraying sonar down each.
My HUD sketched a patchy 3D model from the echoes. Swaths of paint thrown against invisible walls.
We were dots near the center of a ganglion, a tiny swarm of parasites infesting some great
hollowed host. Each tunnel curved away in a gradual spiral, each along a different orientation.
Sonar could peep around those bends a few meters further than we could.
Neither eyes nor ultrasonics saw anything could distinguish one choice from another.
Bates pointed down one of the passageways, Keaton, and another, Sasha, before turning to
coast off down her own unbeaten path. I looked uneasily down mine. Any particular 25 minutes,
she said. I turned and jetted slowly down my assigned passageway. The passage curved clockwise,
a long unremarkable spiral. After 20 meters, that curvature would have blocked any view of its
entrance, even if the foggy atmosphere hadn't. My drone kept point across the tunnel. It's
sonar clicking like the chattering of a thousand tiny teeth, its tether unspooling back to the
distant drum in the nexus. It was a comfort, that leash. It was short. The grunts could stray 90
meters and no further, and we were under strict orders to stay under their wings at all times.
This dim infested burrow might lead all the way to hell, but I would not be expected to follow it
nearly so far. My cowardice had official sanction. 50 meters to go. 50 meters and I could turn and run
with my tail between my legs. In the meantime, all I had to do was grip my teeth and focus and
record. Everything you can see, Sadastiy had said. As much as possible of what you can't.
And I hoped that this new reduced time limit would expire before Rorschach spiked this into a
gibbering dementia. The walls around me twitched and shivered like the flesh of something just
killed, something darted in and out of sight with a faint cackle of laughter. Focus. Record.
If the grunt doesn't see it, it's not real. 65 meters in, one of the ghosts got inside my helmet.
I tried to ignore it. I tried to look away. But this phantom wasn't flickering at the edge of vision.
It hovered near the center of my faceplate, floating like a spot of swirling dizziness between
me and the HUD. I gritted my teeth and tried to look past, stared into the dim bloody haze in
the middle distance, watched the jerky unfolding travelogues in the little windows labeled Bates
and James. Nothing out there. But in here, floating before my eyes, Rorschach's latest
head fuck smeared a fuzzy thumbprint right in front of the sonar feed. New symptom, I called in.
Non-peripheral hoose nation. Stable, pretty formless though, no spiking that I can...
the inset marked Bates skitted hard about. Keat. Window and voice cut out all together.
Not just Bates's window, either. Sasha's inset and the drone's eyes sonar
escape flickered and died at the same moment, stripped my HUD bare except for in-suit feeds
and the little readout flashing, link down. I spun, but the grunt was still there,
three meters off my right shoulder. Its optical port was clearly visible, a ruby thumbnail set
into the plastering. Its gun ports are visible too, pointing at me. I froze. The drone shivered
in some local electromagnetic nod as if terrified of me or of something behind me.
I started to turn. My helmet filled with sudden static and with what sounded faintly like a voice.
Fucking move, Keat. Not...
Bates? Bates?
Another icon had bloomed in place of link down. The grunt was using radio for some reason,
and although almost close enough to touch, I could barely make out the signal.
A hash of bake speed. To your right in front of, and Sasha a bit more clearly,
he see it.
See what? Sasha, someone tell me what? See what?
Read, Keaton, do you read? Somehow Bates had boosted the signal, static roared like an ocean,
but I could hear the words behind it. Yes, what? Keep absolutely still. Do you understand?
Absolutely still. Acknowledge. Acknowledged. The drone kept me in its shaky sights,
dark stereocam irises spasming wide, stuttering into pinpoints. What? There's something in front
of you, Keaton, directly between you and the grunt. Can't you see it? No, my HUD's down.
Sasha broke in. How can he not see it? It's right there. Bates barked over her.
It's man-sized, radially symmetrical, eight, nine arms, like tentacles, but segmented. Spiky.
I don't see anything, I said, but I did. I saw something reaching for me in my pod
back aboard Thesias. I saw something curled up motionless in the ship's spine, watching as we
laid our best plans. I saw Michelle, the Synthesia, curled into a fetal ball. You can't see it, it's
invisible. What's it doing, I called. Why can't I see it? Why can't I see it?
Just floating there, kind of waving. Oh sh- Keat! The grunt skidded sideways as if
slapped by a giant hand. It bounced off the wall and suddenly the laser link was back,
filling the HUD with intelligence. First-person perspectives of Bates and Sasha racing along
alien tunnels, a grunt's eye view of a space suit with Keaton stenciled across its breastplate,
and there, right beside it, something like a rippling starfish with too many arms.
The gang barreled around a curve, and now I could almost, could see something with my own eyes,
flickering like heat lightning off to one side. It was large, it was moving, but somehow my eyes
just slid off every time they tried to get a fix. It's not real, I thought, giddy with hysterical
relief. It's just another hallucination. But then Bates sailed into view and it was right there,
no flickering, no uncertainty, nothing but a collapsed probability wave and a solid undeniable
mass. Exposed, it grabbed the nearest wall and scrambled over our heads, segmented arms flailing
like whips, a sudden crackling buzz in the back of my head and it was drifting free again, charred
and smoking. A stuttering click. The whine of machinery gearing down. Three grunts hovered
in formation in the middle of the passageway. One faced the alien. I glimpsed to the tip of some
lethal proboscis sliding back into its sheath. Bates shut down the grunt before it had finished
closing its mouth. Optical links and three sets of lungs filled my helmet with a roar of heavy
breathing. The offline grunt drifted in the murky air. The alien carcass bumped gently off the wall,
twitching. A hydra of human backbone scorched and fleshless. It didn't look much like my on-board
visions after all. For some reason that I couldn't put my finger on, I almost found that reassuring.
The two active grunts panned the fog until Bates gave them new orders. Then one turned to secure
the carcass. The other is steady, it's fallen comrade. Bates grabbed the dead grunt and unplugged
its tether. Fall back. Slowly, I'm right behind you. I tweaked my jets. Sasha hesitated. Coils of
shielded cable floated about us like umbilical cords. Now, Bates said, plugging a feed from her own
suit directly into the offline grunt. Sasha started after me. Bates took up the rear. I watched my
head. A swarm of multi-armed monsters would appear there any moment. They didn't. But the blackened
thing against the belly of Bates' machine was real enough. Not a hallucination. Not even some
understandable artifact of fear and synthesia. Rorschach was inhabited. Its inhabitants were
invisible. Sometimes. Sort of. And oh yeah, we just killed one.
Bates threw the deactivated grunt into the sky as soon as we'd made vacuum.
Its comrades used it for target practice while we strapped in, firing and firing until there
was nothing left but cooling vapor. Rorschach spun even that faint plasma into filigree before it faded.
Halfway back to Thesias, Sasha turned to the Major. You know. But they do that shit on their own,
right? Autonomous. Not when they're slaved. Malfunction? Spike? Bates didn't answer. She
called ahead. By the time we made it back, Cunningham had grown another little tumor on Thesias' spine,
a remote surgery packed with telops and sensors. One of the surviving grunts grabbed the carcass
and jumped ship as soon as we passed beneath the carapace, completing the delivery as we docked.
We were born again to the fruits of a preliminary necropsy. The holographic ghost of the dissected
alien rose from consensus like some flayed and horrific feast. Its splayed arms looked like
human spinal columns. We sat around the table and waited for someone else to take the first bite.
Did you have to shoot it with microwaves? Cunningham sniped, tapping the table.
You completely cooked the animal. Every cell was blown out from the inside.
Bates shook her head. There was a malfunction. He gave her a sour look. A malfunction that
just perhaps to involve precise targeting of a moving object. It doesn't sound random to me.
Bates looked back evenly. Something flipped autonomous targeting from off to on. A coin toss.
Random. Random is, give it a rest, Cunningham. I don't need this shit from you right now.
His eyes rolled in that smooth, dead face focused suddenly on something overhead. I followed his gaze.
Solasty stared down at us like an owl, panning for meadow voles, drifting slowly in the Coriolis
breeze. No visor this time either. I knew he hadn't lost it. He fixed Cunningham. Your findings?
Cunningham swallowed. Bits and pieces of alien anatomy flickered with color-coded
highlights as he tapped his fingers. Right then, I'm afraid I can't give you much at the cellular
level. There's not much left inside the membranes. Not many membranes left for that matter. In terms
of gross morphology, the specimens d-dorse eventually compressed and radially symmetrical,
as you can see. Calcarus exoskeleton, keratinized plasticutical, nothing special.
Bates looked skeptical. Plastic skin is nothing special? Given the environment,
I was half expecting a sendoviciu plasma. Plastic simply refined petroleum. Organic
carbon. This thing is carbon-based. It's even protein-based, although its proteins are a great
deal tougher than ours. Numerous sulfur cross bonds for lateral bracing. As far as I could tell
from what your grunts did in de-nature. Cunningham's eyes looked past it as all. His consciousness was
obviously far aft, haunting remote sensors. The thing's tissues are saturated with magnetite.
On Earth, you find that material in dolphin brains, migratory birds, even some bacteria.
Anything that navigates or orients using magnetic fields. Moving up the macros to macro structures,
we've got a pneumatic internal skeleton, which as far as I can tell doubles as musculature.
Contractal tissue squeezes gas through a system of bladders that stiffen or relax each segment of
the arms. The light came back into Cunningham's eyes long enough to focus on his cigarette.
He brought it to his mouth, dragging deeply and set it down again.
Note the invaginations around the base of each arm.
Flaccid balloons glowed orange on the virtual carcass.
Cloaca, you could call them. Everything opens into them. They eat, breathe, and defecate through
the same little compartment. No other major orifices. The gang made a face that said,
Sasha, grossed out. Don't things get clogged up? Seems inefficient. If one gets plugged,
there's eight other doors into the same system. You'll wish you were so inefficient the next time
you choke on a chicken bone. What does it eat? Bates asked. I couldn't say. I found
gizzard-like contractiles around the cloaca, which implies they chew on something, or did at some
point in their history. Other than that, he spread his hands, the cigarette left faint streamers in
its wake. Inflate those contractiles enough and you create an airtight seal, by the way.
In conjunction with the cuticle, this would allow this organism to survive briefly in vacuum.
And we already know it can handle the ambient radiation, although don't ask me how.
Whatever it uses for genes must be a great deal tougher than ours.
So it can survive in space, Bates mused. In the sense that a dolphin survives under water,
limited time only. How long? I'm not certain. Central nervous system, Sudasti said.
Bates and the gang grew suddenly, subtly still. James's affect seeped out over her body, supplanting
sashes. Smoke curled from Cunningham's mouth and nose. There's nothing central about it as it
transpires. No sephalization, not even clustered sense organs. The bodies covered with something
like eye spots or chromatophores are both. There are satay everywhere. As far as I can tell, if all
those little cooked filaments I've been able to put back together after your malfunction really are
nerves and not something completely different, every one of those structures is under independent
control. Bates sat up straight. Seriously? He nodded. It would be akin to independently controlling
the movement of each individual hair on your head, although this creature is covered with little
hair from tip to tip. The same thing applies to the eyes. Hundreds of thousands of eyes all over
the cuticle. Each one is barely more than a pinhole camera, but each is capable of independent
focus and I'm guessing all the different inputs integrate somewhere up the line. The entire body
acts like a single diffuse retina. In theory, that gives it enormous visual acuity. A distributed
telescope array, Bates murmured. A chromatophore underlies each eye. The pigment's some kind of
cryptochrome, so it's probably involved in vision, but it can also diffuse or contract through the
local tissue. That implies dynamic pigment patterns like a squid or chameleon.
Background pattern matching, Bates asked. Would that explain why Siri couldn't see it?
Cunningham opened a new window and played a grainy looped imagery of Siri Keaton and his
unseen dance partner. The creature I hadn't noticed was ominously solid to the cameras.
A floating discoid twice as wide as my own torso, arms extending from its edges like
thick knotted ropes. Patterns rippled across its surface and waves, sunlight and shadow playing
on a shallow seabed. As you can see, the background doesn't match the pattern, Cunningham said.
It's not even close. Can you explain Siri's blindness to it? Sardasti said.
I can't, Cunningham admitted. It's beyond ordinary crypts. But Rorschach makes you see
all sorts of things that aren't there. Not seeing something that is there might come down to
essentially the same thing. Another hallucination, I asked. Another shrug while Cunningham stuck
smoke. There are many ways to fool the human visual system. It's interesting that the illusion
failed when multiple witnesses were present. But if you want a definitive mechanism, you'll have
to give me more to work with than that. He stabbed a cigarette at the crisp remains. But James took
a breath bracing herself. We're talking about something sophisticated at least, something
very complex, a great deal of processing power. Cunningham nodded again. I'd estimate nervous
tissue accounts for about 30% of body mass. So it's intelligent. Her voice was almost a whisper.
Not remotely. But 30%! 30% motor and sensory wiring. Another drag. Much like an octopus,
an enormous number of neutrons, but half of them used up running the suckers.
My understanding is that Occupy are quite intelligent, James said.
By Maluskan standard, certainly. But do you have any idea how much extra cabling you'd need if the
photoreceptors in your eye were spread out across your entire body? You'd need about 300
million extension cords to begin with, ranging from half a millimeter to two meters long.
Which means all your signals are staggered and out of sync. Which means billions of additional
logic gates to go here the input. And that just gets you a single static image with no filtering,
no interpretation, no time series integration at all. Shiver. Drag. Now multiply all that by
the extra wiring needed to focus all those eye spots on an object or to send information
back to individual chromatophores and then add in the processing power you need to drive
those chromatophores one at a time. 30% might do all that, but I strongly doubt you have much
left over for philosophy and science. He waved his hand in the general direction of the hold.
That... that scrambler, James suggested. Cunningham rolled his tongue around it.
Very well. That scrambler is an absolute miracle of evolutionary engineering.
It's also as dumb as a stick. A moment's silence.
So what is it? James asked at last. Somebody's pet? Canary in a coal mine, they'd suggested.
Perhaps not even that, Cunningham said. Perhaps no more than a white blood cell with
walldoze. Maintenance bought maybe. Tele-operated or in-string driven. But people, we've been
ignoring far greater questions here. How could an anorob even develop complex multi-cellular
anatomy, much less move as fast as this thing did? That level of activity burns a great deal of ATP.
Maybe they don't use ATP, Bain said as I thumbnailed. Adenosine dry phosphate. Cellular energy source.
It was crammed with ATP, Cunningham told her. You can tell that much even with these remains.
The question is, how can it synthesize this stuff fast enough to keep up with demand?
Purely anaerobic pathways wouldn't suffice. Nobody offered any suggestions.
Anyway, he said. So end of the lesson. If you want gory details, check consensus.
He wiggled the fingers of his freehand. The spectral dissection vanished. I'll keep working,
but if you want any real answers, go get me a live one. He butted out his cigarette against
the bulkhead and stared defiantly around the drum. The others hardly reacted. Their topologies
still sparkled from the revelations of a few minutes before. Perhaps Cunningham's pet peeve
was more important to the big picture. Perhaps in a reductionist universe, biochemical basics
should always take priority over the finer points of ETI and interspecies etiquette.
But Bates and the gang were time lagged, processing earlier revelations. Not just processing either,
wallowing. They clung to Cunningham's findings like convicted felons who just discovered they
might have been freed on a technicality. Because the scrambler was dead at our hands, no doubt about
it. But it wasn't an alien. Not really. It wasn't intelligent. It was just a blood cell with
wall-dose. It was dumb as a stick. And property damage is so much easier to live with than murder.
Problems cannot be solved at the same level of awareness that created them. Einstein.
Robert Poglino had set me up with Chelsea in the first place. Maybe he felt responsible when
the relationships started jumping arrails. Or maybe Chelsea, Madam Fix-It that she was,
had approached him for an intervention. For whatever reason, it was obvious the moment we
took our seats at Cubits that his invitation had not been entirely social.
He went for some neurotrope cocktail on the rocks. I stuck with records.
Still old school, Pag said. Still into foreplay, I observed.
That obvious, huh? He took a sip. That'll teach me to try the subtle approach with a professional
jargonaut. Jargonaut's got nothing to do with it. You wouldn't a fool to border collie.
Truth be told, Pag's topology never really told me much that I didn't already know.
I never really had much of an edge in reading him. Maybe we just knew each other too well.
So, he said, spill. Nothing to spill. She just got to know the real me. That is bad.
What did she tell you? Me? Nothing at all. I gave him a look over the top of my glass.
He sighed. She knows you're cheating on her.
I'm what? Cheating. With the skin. It's based on her. But it isn't her.
No, it isn't. It doesn't fart or fight or break into tears every time you don't want to be dragged
off to meet its family. Look, I love the woman dearly, but come on. When was the last time you
tried first person fucking? 74, he said. You're kidding. I'd have guessed never.
Did some third world medical missionary work between gigs? They still bump and grind in Texas.
Pag's wigged his trope. Actually, I thought it was alright. The novelty wears off. Evidently.
And it's not like I'm doing anything unusual here, Pag. She's the one with the kink. And it's not
just the sex. She keeps asking about... She keeps wanting no things. Like what? Irrelevant stuff.
My life as a kid. My family. Nobody's fucking business. She's just taking an interest. Not
everyone considers childhood memories off limits, you know? Thanks for the insight.
As if people had never taken an interest before. As if Helen hadn't taken an interest when she
went through my drawers and filtered my mail and followed me from room to room, asking the drapes
and furniture why I was always so sullen and withdrawn. She'd taken an interest that she
wouldn't let me out of the door until I confided in her. At 12, I'd been stupid enough to throw
myself on her mercy. It's personal, Mom. I'd just rather not talk about it. And then I'd made my
escape into the bathroom when she demanded to know if it was trouble online, trouble at school,
was it a girl, was it... was it a boy? What was it? Why couldn't I just trust my own mother?
Don't I know I can trust her with anything? I laid it out the persistent knocking and the
insistent concerned voice through the door and the final grudging silence that followed.
I waited until I was absolutely sure she'd gone away. I'd waited for five fucking hours before
I came out and there she was, arms folded in the hall, eyes brimming with reproach and disappointment.
That night she took the lock off the bathroom door because family should never shut each other out.
Still taking an interest.
Siri, Pag said quietly. I slowed my breathing, tried again.
She doesn't just want to talk about family. She wants to meet them. She keeps trying to drag
me to meet hers. I thought I was hooking up with Chelsea, you know? Nobody ever told me I'd have
to share airspace with... you do it? Once. Reaching, grasping things, feigning acceptance,
feigning friendship.
It was great. If you like being ritually pawed by a bunch of play acting strangers who can't
stand the sight of you and don't have the guts to admit it. Pag shrugged unsympathetic.
Sounds like typical old school family. You're a synthesis man. You deal with way walkier dynamics
than that. I deal with other people's information. I don't vomit my own personal life into the public
sphere. Whatever hybrids and the constructs I work with, they don't... touch. Interrogate, I finished.
You knew Chelsea was an old fashioned girl right off the top.
Yeah, when it suits her, I gulped ale. But she's cutting edge when she's got a splicer in her hand,
which isn't to say that her strategies couldn't use some work. Strategies. It's not a strategy
for God's sake. Can't you see I'm hurting? I'm on the fucking floor, Siri. I'm curled up in the
ball because I'm hurting so much and all you can do is criticize my tactics. What do I have to do?
Slash my goddamn wrists? I shrugged and turned away. Nature's trick. She cries, I said now.
High blood lactic levels make it easier for her. It's just chemistry, but she holds it up like it
was some kind of IOU. Pag pursed his lips. Doesn't mean it's an act. Everything's an act.
Everything's strategy. You know that. I snorted. And she's miffed because I base a skin on her?
I don't think it's so much the actual skin as the fact that you didn't tell her.
You know how she feels about honesty and relationships. Sure, she doesn't want any.
He looked at me. Give me some credit, Pag. You think I should tell her that sometimes the side
of her makes me shudder? The system called Robert Poglino sack quietly, sipped his drugs,
and set the things he was about to say in order. He took a breath.
I can't believe you could be so fucking dumb, he said. Yeah, enlighten me. Of course,
she wants you to tell her you only have eyes for her. You love her pores and her morning breath.
And why stop at one tweak? How about ten? But that doesn't mean she wants you to lie, you idiot.
She wants all that stuff to be true. And, well, why can't it be?
It isn't, I said. Jesus, Siri, people aren't rational. You aren't rational. We're not thinking
machines. We're feeling machines and happen to think. He took a breath and another hit.
And you already know that, or you couldn't do your job, or at least, he grimaced. The system knows.
The system. Me and my protocols, he meant. My Chinese room. I took a breath.
It doesn't work with everyone, you know. So I've noticed. Can't read systems you two entangled
with, right? Observer effect? I shrugged. Just as well, he said. I don't think I'd like you all
that much in that room of yours. It came out before I could stop it. Chell said she'd prefer a real one.
He raised his eyebrows. Real what? Chinese room. She says it would have better comprehension.
The cube murmured and clattered around us for a few moments.
I can see why she'd say that, bag said at last. But you, you did okay, pod man.
I don't know. He nodded empathetic. You know what they say about the road less traveled?
Well, you carved your own road. I don't know why. It's like learning calligraphy using your toes,
you know, or proprioseceptive polyneuropathy. It's amazing you can do it at all. It's mind
boggling that you actually got good at it. I squinted at him. Proprio, there used to be people
without any sense of, well, themselves physically. They couldn't feel their bodies in space, had no
idea of their own limbs, were arranged or if they hadn't had limbs. Some of them said they felt pithed,
disembodied. It sent a motor signal to the hand and just have to take it on faith that it arrived.
So they'd use vision to compensate. They couldn't feel where their hand was, so they'd look at it
while it moved. Use sight as a substitute for normal force feedback that you and I take for granted.
They could walk if they kept their eyes focused on their legs and concentrate on every step.
They'd get pretty good at it. But even after years of practice, if you distracted them in
mid-step, they'd go over like a beanstalk without a counterweight. You were saying I'm like that?
You use your Chinese room the way they used vision. You've reinvented empathy almost from scratch and
in some ways, not all obviously, or I wouldn't have to tell you this, but in some ways yours
is better than the original. So why are you so good at synthesis? I shook my head. I just observe,
that's all. I watch what people do and then I imagine what it would make them do that.
Sounds like empathy to me. It's not. Empathy is not so much about imagining how the other guy feels.
It's more about imagining how you'd feel in the same place.
Pag frowned. So?
So what if you don't know how you'd feel? He looked at me and his surfaces were serious and
completely transparent. You're better than that friend. You may not always act like it, but I know
you. I knew you before. You knew someone else. I'm pod man, remember? Yeah, that was someone else.
And maybe I remember him better than you do, but I'll tell you one thing. He leaned forward.
Both of you would have helped me out that day. And maybe he would have got there with a good
old fashioned empathy while you had to cobble together some kind of improvised flowchart out of
surplus parts, but that just makes your accomplishment all the greater, which is why I continue to stick
it out with you old buddy. Even though you have a rod up your ass the size of the Rio Spire,
he held out his glass. Dutifully, I clinked it against my own. We drank.
I don't remember him. I said after a while. What, the other Siri? Prepod Siri? I nodded.
Nothing at all? I thought back. Well, he was wracked by convulsions all the time, right?
There'd be constant pain. I don't remember any pain. My glass was almost empty. I sipped to make it
last. I dream about him sometimes, though, about being him. What's it like? It was colorful.
Everything was more saturated, you know? Sounds, smells, richer than life. And now,
I looked at him. You said it was colorful. What changed? I don't know. Maybe nothing. I just,
I don't actually remember the dreams when I wake up anymore. So how do you know you still have them?
Pag asked. Fuck it. I thought. I tipped back the last of my pint in a single gulp. I know. How?
I frowned, taken aback. I had to think for a few moments before I remembered.
I wake up smiling, I said. Grunts look the enemy in the eye. Grunts know the stakes.
Grunts know the price of poor strategy. What do the generals know? Overlays and tactical plots.
The whole chain of command is upside down. Kenneth Lubin, zero sum.
It went bad from the moment we breached. The plan had called for a precise havoc along the new
beachhead, subtly arranged to entrap some blood cell with walldoze as it sought to repair the
damage. Our job admitted is set to trap and stand back, trusting Sadasi's assurances that we would
not have long to wait. We had no time at all. Something squirmed in the squirreling dust the
moment we breached. Serpentine movement down the hole that instantly kicked Bates around
Field Initiative into high gear. Her grunts dived through and caught a scrambler twitching in their
crosshairs, clinging to the wall the passageway. It must have been stunned by the blast of our
entry, a classic case of wrong place, wrong time. Bates took a split second to appraise the opportunity
and the plan was plasma. One of the grunts plugged the scrambler with a biopsy dart before I even had
a chance to blink. We would have bagged the whole animal right there if Borschak's magnetosphere
hadn't chosen that moment to kick sand in our faces. As it was, by the time our grunts staggered
back into action their quarry was already disappearing around the bend. Bates was tethered to her
troops. They yanked her down the rabbit hole. Set it up! She yelled back at Shasa the moment she
let them loose. I was tethered to Bates. I barely had a chance to exchange a wide-eyed look with
Shasa before being yanked away in turn. Suddenly I was inside again. The sated biopsy dart bounced
off my faceplate and fasht plats, still attached to a few meters of discarded monofilament.
Hopefully Shasa would pick it up while Bates and I were hunting. At least the mission wouldn't be a
total loss if we never made it back. The grunts dragged us about like bait on a hook. Bates flew
like a dolphin just ahead of me, keeping effortlessly to the center of the bore with an occasional
tweak of her jets. I careened off the walls just behind trying to stabilize myself,
trying to look as though I too might be in control. It was an important pretense. The whole point of
being a decoy is to pass yourself off as an original. They'd even give me my own gun, pure
precaution of course, more for comfort than protection. It hugged my forearm and fired
plastic slugs impervious to induction fields. Just Bates and I now. A pacifist soldier and the odds
of a coin toss. Goose flesh prickled my skin as it always had. The usual ghosts scrambled and
clawed through my mind. This time though the dread seemed muted. Distant. Perhaps it was just a matter
of timing. Perhaps we were moving so quickly through the magnetic landscape that no one phantom had a
chance to stick. Or maybe it was something else. Maybe I wasn't so afraid of ghosts because this
time we were after monsters. The scrambler seemed to have thrown off whatever cobwebs our entrance
had spun. It surged along the wall now at full speed. Its arm shooting ahead like a succession of
striking snakes slinging the body forward so fast the drones could barely keep it in sight,
arriving silhouette in the fog. Suddenly it left sideways sailing across the width of the passage
way and down some minor tributary. The grunts veered in pursuit crashing into walls, stumbling,
stopping. And suddenly Bates was breaking hard, shooting past me as I flailed with my pistol.
I was past the drones in the next instant. My leash snapped tight and snapped back,
bringing me to a dead drifting stop. For a second or two I was on the front line. For a second or
two I was the front line. Ciri Keaton, note-taker, mole, professional, uncomprehend her. I just floated
there, breath roaring in my helmet as a few meters further out of the walls squirmed.
Peristalysis, I thought at first. But this motion was utterly unlike the slow undulating waves that
usually ripple along Rorschach's passageways. So hallucination, I thought instead. And then those
writhing walls reached out with a thousand whiplike calciferous tongues that grabbed our query from
every direction and tore it to pieces. Something grabbed me and spun me around. Suddenly I was
locked against the chest of one of the grunts, its rear guns firing as we retracted back up the
tunnel at full speed. Bates was in the arms of the other. Seething motion receded behind us,
but the image stayed stuck to the backs of my eyes, lucinatory and point blank in its clarity.
Scramblers everywhere. A seething infestation squirmed across the walls, reaching out for the
intruder, leaping into the lumen of the passageway to press their counterattack. Not against us.
They had attacked one of their own. I'd seen three of its arms ripped off before it had disappeared
into a rioting ball in the center of the passageway. We fled. I turned to Bakes. Did you see,
but held my tongue. The deathly concentration on her face was unmistakable even across two
faceplates and three meters of methane. According to HUD, she'd lobotomized both grunts, bypassed
all that wonderful autonomous decision-making circuitry entirely. She was running both machines
herself, as manually as marionettes. Graney turbulent echoes appeared on the rear sonar display.
The scramblers had finished with their sacrifice. Now they were coming after us.
My grunts stumbled and creed against the side of the passage.
Shards of alien decor dug parallel gouges across my faceplate, tenderized chunks of thigh through
the shielded fabric of my suit. I clenched down on a cry. It got on anyway. Some ridiculous
in-suit alarm chirped indignantly an instant before a dozen rotten eggs broke open inside my helmet.
I coughed. My eyes stung and watered in the reek. I could barely see sea-verts on the HUD,
flashing instantly into the red. Bakes drove us on without a word.
My faceplate healed enough to shut off the alarm. My air began to clear.
The scramblers had gained. By the time I could see clearly again, they were only a few meters behind
us. Up ahead, Sasha came into view around the bend. Sasha, who had no backup, whose other
course had been shut down on Sarasi's orders. Susan had protested at first.
If there's any opportunity to communicate, there won't be, he'd said. So there was Sasha,
who was more resistant to Rorschach's influence, according to some criteria, and I never understood.
Curled up in a fetal ball with her gloves clamped against her helmet, and I could only hope to some
dusty deity that she'd set the trap before this place had got her. And here came the scramblers,
and Bates was shouting, Sasha, get out of the fucking way! And breaking hard, way too soon,
the scrambling whore nipping at our heels like a riptide, and Bates yelled, Sasha! And again,
and finally Sasha moved, kicking herself into gear and off the nearest wall, and fled right back up
the hole we'd blown in through. Bates yanked some joystick in her head, and our warrior sedan slued
and shat sparks and bullets and dove out after her. Sasha had set the trap just within the mouth
of the breach. Bates armed it in passing with a slap of one-gloved hand. Motion sensors were
supposed to do the rest, but the enemy was close behind and there was no room to spare. It went
off just as I was emerging into the vestibule. The cannon net shot out behind me in a glorious
exploding conic, caught something, snapped back up the rabbit hole and slammed it in my grunt from
behind. The recoil kicked us against the top of the vestibule so hard I thought the fabric would
tear. It held and threw us back against the scrumming things enmeshed in our midst. Riding
backbones everywhere, articulated arms lashing like bony whips, one of them entwined my leg and
squeezed like a brick python. Bates' hands waved an frantic dance before me, and that arm came apart
into dismembered segments, bouncing around the enclosure. This was all wrong. They were supposed
to be in the net, they were supposed to be contained. Sasha, launch! Bates barked. Another arm separated
from its body and careened into the wall, coiling and uncoiling. The hole had flooded with aerosome
foam core as soon as we'd pulled the net. A scrambler writhed half embedded in that matrix,
cautious to split second too late. Its central mass protruded like some great round tumor writhing
with monstrous worms. Sasha! Artillery. The floor of the vestibule iris shut quick as a leg hold
trap and everything slammed against it, grunts, people, scramblers, hole and in pieces. I couldn't
breathe. Every thimble full of flesh weighed a hundred kilograms. Something slapped us to one
side, a giant hand, batting an insect. Maybe a course correction. Maybe a collision.
But ten seconds later we were weightless again and nothing had torn us open. We floated like mites
in a ping pong ball surrounded by a confusion of machinery and twitching body parts. There was little
of anything that might pass from blood. What there was floated in clear shuttering spherules.
The cannon net floated like a shrink-wrapped asteroid in our midst. The things inside had
wrapped their arms around themselves, around each other, curled into a shivering and unresponsive ball.
Compressed methonia hissed around them, keeping them fresh for the long trip home.
Holy shit! Sasha breathed, watching them. The bloodsucker called it.
He hadn't called everything. He hadn't called a mob of multi-armed aliens ripping one of their
own to pieces before my eyes. He hadn't seen that coming. Or at least he hadn't mentioned it.
I was already feeling nauseous. Bates was carefully bringing her wrists together.
For a moment I could barely make out a taut dark thread of freak wire,
find a smoke between them. Her caution was well advised. That stuff would slice through human
limbs as easily as alien ones. One of the grunts groomed its mouthparts at her shoulder, cleaning
gore from its mandibles. The freak wire vanished from my sight. The sight itself was dimming now.
The inside of this great lead balloon was going dark around me.
You were coasting, purely ballistic. We had to trust that Scylla would swoop in and snatch us once
we'd achieved a discrete distance from the scene of the crime. We had to trust Sarasti.
That was getting harder by the hour. But he'd been right so far, mostly.
How do you know? Bates had asked when he'd first laid out the plan.
He hadn't answered. Chances are he couldn't have, not to us. A more than a baseline could have
explained a brain theory to the inhabitants of Flatland. But Bates hadn't been asking about tactics
anyway, not really. Maybe she'd been asking for a reason, something to justify this ongoing
trespass into foreign soil, with the capture and slaughter of its natives. On one level,
she already knew the reason, of course. We all did. We could not afford to merely react.
The risks were too great. We had to preempt. Sarasti, wise beyond all of us, saw this more
clearly than we. Amanda Bates knew he was right in her mind. But sure, perhaps she didn't feel it
in her gut. Perhaps, I thought, as my vision failed, she was asking Sarasti to convince her.
But that wasn't all she was doing. Imagine you are Amanda Bates. The control you wheel over your
troops would give wet dreams and nightmares to generals of ages past. You can drop instantly
into the sensorium of anyone under your command, experience the battlefield from any number of
first person perspectives. Your every soldier is loyal unto death, asking no questions, obeying
all commands of the Lackardy and dedication to which mere flesh could never even aspire.
You don't just respect a chain of command. You are one. You are a little bit scared of your own
power. You are a little bit scared of the things you've already done with it. Taking orders comes
as naturally as giving them. Oh, you've known to question policy on occasion, or seek a bigger
picture than may be strictly necessary for the job at hand. Your command initiative has become the
stuff of legends. But you have never disobeyed a direct order. When asked for your perspective,
you serve it straight up and unvarnished, until the decision is made and the order is handed down.
Then you do your job without question. Even when the questions arise, you would hardly waste time
asking them unless you expected an answer you could use. Why then demand analytical details from a
vampire? Not for information. Might as well expect the sighted to explain vision to the
congenitally blind. Not for clarification. There is no ambiguity in Sotosti's bottom line. Not even
for the benefit of poor dumb Ciri Keaton, who may have missed some salient point, but it's too
ashamed to raise his own hand. No, there is only one reason why you might ask for such details.
To challenge. To rebel. To the infinitesimal degree that rebellion is permitted once the word
is given. You argued and advocated as forcefully as you could back when Sotosti was soliciting input.
But he ignored yours, abandoned any attempt at communication and preemptively invaded foreign
territory. He knew that Rorschach might contain living beings and still he tore it open without
regard for their welfare. He may have killed hapless innocents. He may have roused an angry giant.
You don't know. All you know is you've been helping him do it. You've seen this kind of arrogance
before among your own kind. You had hopes that smarter creatures would be wiser ones. That enough
to see such arrogance, stupidity inflicted on their helpless, but to do it at these stakes begers
belief. Killing innocents is the least of the risks you're running. You're gambling with the fate of
worlds, provoking conflict with the starfaring technology whose sole offense was to take your
picture without permission. Your descent has changed nothing. So you reign it in. All that flips out
now is the occasional pointless question with no hope of an answer. It's inherent in subordination
so deeply buried you don't even see it in yourself. If you did see it, you'd keep your mouth shut
entirely. Because the last thing you want is to remind Sotosti that you think he's wrong.
You don't want him dwelling on that. You don't want him to think you're up to something.
Because you are, even if you're not quite ready to admit it to yourself.
Amanda Bates is beginning to confidently change of command.
The laceration of my suit had done a real number on the gears. It took three solid days for Thesias
to bring me back to life. But death was no excuse for falling behind the curve. I was
resurrected with a head full of updates clogging my inlays. I flipped through them climbing into
the drum. The gang of four sat at the galley below me staring at untouched portions of
nutritionally balanced sludge on her plate. Cunningham over in his inherited domain grunted
my appearance and turned back to work, the fingers of one hand tapping compulsively on the desktop.
Thesias orbit had widened during my absence and most of its eccentricities had been plain
to weigh. Now we kept our target in view for a more or less constant range of 3000 kilometers.
Our orbital period lagged rorshawks by an hour. The alien crept implacably ahead of us
along its lower trajectory. But a supplementary burn every couple of weeks would be enough to
keep it in sight. We had specimens now, things to be examined under conditions of our own choosing,
no point in risking any more close approaches until we'd rung every useful datum from what we had.
Cunningham had expanded his lab space during my time in the sepulcher. He'd built
holing pens, one for each scrambler, modules partitioned by a common wall and installed
in a whole new hab. The microwaved carcass had been sidelined like a discarded toy from a previous
birthday, although according to the access logs Cunningham still visited every now and again.
Not that he visited any part of the new wing in person, of course. Not that he was even able to,
not without suiting up and jumping across the hold. The whole compartment had been disconnected
from its spinal lock and pushed to a tethered anchorage midway between the spine and carapace,
so to us these orders, given to minimize risk of contamination. It was no skin off Cunningham's
nose. He was happier leaving his body in pseudo-gravity anyway while his consciousness flitted
between the wall-dose and sensors and brick-a-bracks surrounding his new pets.
Thesias saw me coming and pushed a squeeze-bulb of sugary electrolytes from the galley dispenser.
The gang didn't look up as I passed. One forefinger tapped ascent against their temple,
the lips pursed and twitched in the characteristic mode that said internal dialogue and progress.
I could never tell who was on top when they were like that.
I sucked on the squeeze-bulb and looked in on the pens. Two cubes suffused in pale red light.
In one, a scrambler floated center stage, waving at segmented arms like seaweed and gentle surge.
The occupant of the other cage was squeezed into a corner. Four arms splayed across the
converging walls, four others extended, waving again into open space. The bodies from which
those arms sprouted were spheroids, not flattened discs as our first sample had been.
They were only slightly compressed. Their arms sprouted and not from a single equatorial band,
from across the whole surface. Fully extended, the floating scrambler was over two meters across.
The other seemed roughly the same size, neither moved except for those drifting arms.
Navy Blue Mosaics, almost black in the long wave, rippled across their surfaces like the
patterns of wind on grass. Superimposed graphics plotted methane and hydrogen at reassuring
Worshack norms, temperature and lighting ditto. An icon for ambient electromagnetics remained dark.
I dipped into the archives, watched the arrival of the aliens from two days past,
each tumbling unceremoniously into its pen, balled up, hugging themselves as they bounced
gently around their enclosures. Fetal position, I thought. But after a few moments, the arms
uncoiled like the blooming of calciferous flowers. Robert says Worshack grows them,
Susan James said behind me. I turned. Definitely James in there, but muted somehow.
Her meal remained untouched, their surfaces were dim.
Except for those eyes. They were deep and a little hollow.
Grows, I repeated. In stacks, they have two navels each. She managed a weak smile,
touched her belly with one hand and the small of her back with the other. One in front, one behind.
He thinks they grow in a kind of column, piled up. When the top one develops to a certain point,
buds off from the stack and becomes free living. The archived scramblers were exploring their new
environment now, climbing gingerly along the walls, unrolling their arms along the corners
where the panels met. Their swollen central bodies struck me again. So that first one with the flattened
juvenile, she agreed. Fresh off the stack. These ones are older. They plump out as they mature,
Robert says. She had it after a moment. I sucked the dregs to my squeeze bulb.
The ship grows its own crew. If it's a ship, James shrugged. If they're crew.
I watched them move. There wasn't much to explore. The walls were almost bare, innocent of anything,
but a few sensor heads and gas nozzles. The pens had their own tentacles and manipulators and more
invasive research needs, but those have been carefully sheathed during introduction.
Still, the creatures covered the territory in careful increments, moving back and forth along
parallel invisible paths, almost as if they were running transects. James had noticed it too.
It seems awfully systematic, doesn't it? What does Robert say about that? He says the behavior
of honeybees and specksbloss is just as complex, and it's all road hardwiring, not intelligence.
But bees still communicate, right? They do that dance, they tell the hive where the flowers are.
She shrugged, conceding the point. So you might still be able to talk to these things.
Maybe. You'd think. So you massaged her brow between thumb and forefinger. We haven't got
anywhere, though. We played some of their pigment patterns back to them with variations.
They don't seem to make sounds. Robert synthesized a bunch of noises that they might squeeze out of
their cloaca if they were so inclined, but those didn't get us anywhere. Harmonic farts, really.
So we're sticking to the blood cells of Waldo's model. Pretty much, but you know,
they didn't go into a loop. Hardwired animals repeat themselves, even smart ones pace or chew
their fur. Stereotype behaviors. But these two, they gave everything a very careful once over,
and then just shut down. They were still at it in consensus, slithering across one wall,
than another, than another. A slow screw thread track that would leave no square centimeter
uncovered. Have they done anything since? I asked. She shrugged again. Nothing spectacular.
They squirm when you poke them. Wave their arms back and forth. They do that pretty much
constantly, but there's no information in it that we can tell. They haven't gone invisible on us or
anything. We blanked the adjoining wall for a while so they could see each other, even piped
audio and air feeds. Robert thought there might be some kind of pheromonal communication, but nothing.
They didn't even react to each other. Have you tried, well, motivating them? With what,
Siri? They don't seem to care about their own company. We can't bribe them with food unless
we know what they eat, which we don't. Robert says they're in no immediate danger of starvation
anyway. Maybe they, when they get hungry, but they can deal. I killed the archival feed and
reverted the real time. Maybe they eat, I don't know, radiation or magnetic energy. The cage can
generate magnetic fields, right? Try it. She took a breath and squared her shoulders. But I guess
these things take time. He's only had a couple of days and I only got out of the crypt myself a day
ago. We'll keep trying. What about negative reinforcement? I wondered. She blinked. Hurt
them, you mean. Not necessarily anything extreme. And if they're not sent to you in any way.
Just like that, Susan went away. Why, Keaton, you just made a suggestion. You're giving up on this
whole non-interference thing? Hello, Sasha. No, of course not. Just making a list of what's been
tried. Good. There was an edge to her voice. Hate to think you were slipping. We're going to grab
some downtime now, so maybe you could go and talk to Cunningham for a bit. Yeah, do that. And be sure
to tell him your theory about radiation-eating aliens. I bet he could use a laugh.
He stood at his post in Biomed, though his empty chair was barely a meter away. The ubiquitous
cigarette hung from between the fingers of one hand, burned down and burned out. His other hand
played with itself, fingers tapping against them in sequence, little to index, index to little.
Windows crawled with intelligence in front of him. He wasn't watching.
I approached him from behind. I watched his surfaces in motion. I heard the soft syllables
rising from his throat. Yid par, yish taba, vid par, vid romam. Not his usual litany.
Not even his usual language, Hebrew consensus said. It sounded almost like a prayer.
He must have heard me. His topology went flat and hard and almost impossible to decipher.
It was increasingly difficult getting a fix on anyone these days, but even through these topological
cataracts, Cunningham as always was a tougher read than most.
Keaton, he said, without turning.
You're not Jewish, I said.
It was. Spindle, I realized after a moment. Cunningham didn't do gender pronouns.
But Isaac Spindle had been an atheist. All of us were. We'd all started out that way, at least.
I didn't know you knew him, I said. It certainly wasn't policy.
Cunningham sank into his chair without looking at me. In his head and in mine,
a new window opened within a frame marked Electroferophoresis.
I tried again. I'm sorry, I didn't mean to intrude. What can I do for you, Siri?
I was hoping you could bring me up to speed on your findings.
A periodic chart of alien elements scrolled through the feed. Cunningham logged it and started
another sample. I have documented everything. It's all in consensus.
I made a play for ego. It would really help to know how a huge thumbnail it, though.
What you think is important can be just as vital as the data themselves.
He looked at me a moment. He muttered something repetitive and irrelevant.
What's important is what's missing, he said after a moment. I've got good samples now and I still
can't find the genes. Protein synthesis is almost prionic. Reconformation instead of the
usual transcription pathways. But I can't figure out how those bricks get slotted into the wall
once they're made. Any progress on the energy front? I asked. Energy? Aerobic metabolism on
an anaerobic budget, remember? You said they had too much ATP. That I solved. He puffed smoke,
far discerned a flak of alien tissue liquefied and banded into chemical strata.
They're sprinting. Rotate that if you can. I couldn't. How do you mean? He sighed.
Biochemistry is a trade-off. The faster you synthesize ATP, the more expensive each molecule
becomes. It turns out scramblers are a lot more energy efficient in making it than we are.
They're just extremely slow at it, which might not be a big drawback for something that spends
most of its time inactive. Rorschach, whatever Rorschach started out as, could have drifted
from millennia before it washed up here. That's a lot of time to build up an energy reserve for
bouts of high activity. And once you've laid the groundwork, glycolysis is explosive. 2000
fold boost and no oxygen demand. Scramblers sprint their whole lives. They may come preloaded with
ATP and burn it off throughout their lifespan. How long would that be?
Good question, he'd made it. Live fast, die young. If they ration it out,
stay dormant most of the time. Who knows? Huh. The free-floating scrambler had drifted away
from the center of its pen. One extended arm held a wall at bay. The others continued their
hypnotic swaying. I remembered other arms, their motion not so gentle. Amanda and I chased one into
a crowd. It... Cunningham was back at his samples. I saw the record. They tore it to pieces.
Uh-huh. Any idea why? He shrugged. Bates thought there might be some kind of civil war going on
down there. What do you think? I don't know. Maybe it's right. Or maybe scramblers are ritual
cannibals or... or they're aliens, Keaton. What do you want from me? But they're not really aliens,
at least not intelligent ones. War implies intelligence. Ants wage war all the time, proves
nothing except that they're alive. Are scramblers even alive? I asked. What kind of question is that?
You think Rorschach grows them on some kind of assembly line. You can't find any genes. Maybe
they're just biomechanical machines. That's what life is, Keaton. That's what you are.
Another hit of nicotine. Another storm of numbers. Another sample.
Life isn't either or. It's a matter of degree. What I'm asking is, are they natural? Could they be
constructs? Is a termite mound a construct? Beaver dam? Spaceship? Of course. Were they built by
naturally evolved organisms, acting naturally? They were. So tell me how anything in the whole
deep multiverse can either be anything but natural. I try to keep the irritation out of my voice.
You know what I mean. It's a meaningless question. Get your head out of the 20th century.
I gave up. After a few seconds, Cunningham seemed to notice the silence. He withdrew his
consciousness from the machinery and looked around with fleshly eyes as if searching for
some mosquito that had mysteriously stopped whining.
What's your problem with me? I asked. Stupid question. Obvious question. Unworthy of any
synthesis to be so so direct. His eyes glittered in that dead face. Processing without comprehension.
That's what you do, isn't it? That's a colossal oversimplification.
Hmm. Cunningham nodded. Then why can't you seem to comprehend how pointless it is to keep peeking
over our shoulders and riding home to our masters? Someone has to keep Earth in the loop.
Seven months each way. Long loop. Still. We're on our own out here, Keaton. You're on your own.
The game's going to be long over before our masters even know it started. He sucked smoke.
Or perhaps not. Perhaps you're talking to someone closer, hmm? That it? Is the fourth wave telling
you what to do? There is no fourth wave. Not that anyone's told me anyway. Probably not.
They'd never risk their lives out here, would they? Too dangerous even to hang back and
waft from a distance. That's why they built us. We're all self-made. Nobody forced you to get
the rewire. No, nobody forced me to get the rewire. I could have just let them cut out my
brain and pack it into heaven, couldn't I? That's the choice we have. We can be utterly useless,
or we can try and compete against the vampires and the constructs of the AIs.
And perhaps you could tell me how to do that without turning into a
another freak. So much in the voice. Nothing at all in the face. I said nothing.
See what I mean? No comprehension. You managed a tight smile.
So I'll answer your questions. I'll delay my own work and hold your hand because the last
he's told us to. I'll guess that superior vampire mind sees some legitimate reason to
indulge your constant ankle nipping, and it's in charge, so I'll play along.
But I'm not nearly that smart, so you'll forgive me if it all seems a bit naff.
I'm just... you're just doing your job, I know. But I don't like being played, Keaton.
And that's what your job is.
Even back on Earth, Robert Cunningham had barely disguised his opinion of the ship's commissar.
It had been obvious even at the topologically blind. I'd always had a hard time imagining the man.
It wasn't just his expressionless face. Sometimes, not even the subtler things behind
would show up in his topology. Perhaps he repressed them deliberately,
resenting the presence of this mole among the crew. It would hardly have been the first time
I'd encountered such a reaction. Everyone resented me to some extent. Oh, they liked me well enough,
or thought they did. They tolerated my intrusions and cooperated and gave away far more than they
thought they did. But beneath spindles, gruff camaraderie, beneath James' patient explanations,
there was no real respect. How could there be? These people were the bleeding edge,
the incandescent apex of hominid achievement. They were trusted with the fate of the world.
I was just a tattletale for small minds back home. Not even that much when home receded too deeply
into the distance. Superfluous mass. Couldn't be helped. No use getting bothered over it.
Still, spindle had only coined commissar half jokingly. Cunningham believed it and didn't laugh.
And while I'd encountered many others like him over the years,
those had only tried to hide themselves from sight. Cunningham was the first it seemed to succeed.
I tried to build a relationship all the way through the training, tried to find the missing
pieces. I watched him working the simulator's telops one day, exercising the shiny new interfaces
that spread him through the walls and wires. He was practicing his surgical skills on some
hypothetical alien the computer had conjured up to test his technique. Sensors and jointed
telops sprouted like the legs of an enormous spider crab from an overhead mount. Spirit possessed.
They dipped and weaved around some semi plausible holographic creature. Cunningham's own body
merely trembled slightly, cigarette jiggling at the corner of its mouth. I waited for him to take
a break. Eventually the tension ebbed from his shoulders. His vicarious limbs relaxed.
So I tapped my temple. Why'd you do it? He didn't turn. Above the dissection,
sensors swiveled and stared back like dismembered ice docks. That was the center of Cunningham's
awareness right now. Not this nicotine stained body in front of me. Those were his eyes or his tongue
or whatever unimaginable bastard senses he used to parse with the machine sent him. Those clusters
aimed back at me at us. As if Robert Cunningham still possessed anything that might be called vision.
He was watching himself eyes two meters outside of his own skull.
Do what exactly? He said at last. The enhancements?
Enhancements. As though he'd upgraded his wardrobe instead of ripping out his senses and
grafting new ones into the wounds. I nodded. It's vital to keep current, he said. If you
don't reconfigure you can't retrain. If you don't retrain you're obsolete within a month,
and then you're not much good for anything except heaven or dictation. I ignored the jibe.
Pretty radical transformation though. Not these days. Didn't it change you? His body dragged on
the cigarette. Targeted ventilation sucked away the smoke before it reached me. That's the whole
point. Surely he were affected personally though. Surely. Ah, he nodded at the far end of shared
motor nerves, tail ops jiggled in sympathy. Changed the eyes to look at the world, changed the me
that does the looking. Something like that. Now he was watching me with fleshly eyes.
Across the membrane those snakes and eye stocks returned to their work on the virtual carcass,
as if deciding they wasted enough time on pointless distraction. I wondered which body he was in now.
I'm surprised you'd have to ask, the meat one said. Doesn't my body language tell you everything?
Aren't jargonauts supposed to read minds? He was right of course. I wasn't interested in
Cunningham's words. Those were just the carrier wave. He couldn't hear the real conversation we
were having. All his angles and services spoke volumes, and although their voices were strangely
fizzled with feedback and distortion, I knew I'd be able to understand them eventually. I only had
to keep him talking. But Yuka Sarasti chose that moment to wander past and surgically trash my best
laid plans. Ciri is the best in the field, he remarked, but not when it gets too close to home.
Why should man expect his prayer for mercy to be heard by what is above him when he shows no
mercy to what is under him? Pierre Trobetskoy.
The thing is, Chelsea said, this whole first person thing takes effort. You have to care
enough to try, you know? I've been working my ass off on this relationship. I've been working so
hard, but you just don't seem to care. She thought she was breaking the news. She thought I hadn't
seen it coming because I hadn't said anything. I'd probably seen it before she had. I hadn't
said anything because I'd been scared of giving her an opening. I felt sick to my stomach.
I care about you, I said. As much as you care about anything, she admitted. But you, I mean,
sometimes you're fine sickness, sometimes you're wonderful to be around, and whenever anything
gets the least bit intense, you just go away and leave this battle computer running your body,
and I just can't deal with it anymore. I stared at the butterfly on the back of her hand.
Its wings flexed and folded, lazy and iridescent. I wondered how many of those tattoos she had.
I'd seen five of them on different body parts, albeit only one at a time.
I thought about asking her, but this didn't seem like the right moment.
You can be so, so brutal sometimes, she was saying. I know you don't mean to be, but I don't know.
Maybe I'm your pressure release valve or something. Maybe you have to submerge yourself
so much on the job that everything just builds up and you need some kind of punching bag.
Maybe that's why you say the things you do. She waited for me to say anything now.
I've been honest, I said. Yeah, pathologically. Have you ever had a negative thought that you
haven't said out loud? Her voice trembled, but her eyes for one stayed dry. I guess it's as much
my fault as yours, maybe more. I could tell you were disconnected from the day we met. I guess
on some level I always saw it coming. Why even try then, if you knew we were just going to crash
and burn like this. Oh, sickness. Aren't you the one who says everyone crashes and burns eventually?
Aren't you the one that says it never lasts? Mom and Dad lasted longer than this anyway.
I frowned, astonished that I'd even let the thought form in my head.
Chels read the silence as a wounded one. I guess... maybe I thought I could help, you know?
Help fix whatever made you so, so angry all the time.
The butterfly was starting to fade. I'd never seen that happen before.
Do you understand what I'm saying? She asked. Sure, I'm a fixer upper.
Siri, you wouldn't even get a tweak when I offered. You were so scared of being manipulated,
you wouldn't even try a basic cascade. You're the one guy I've met who might be truly eternally
unfixable. Maybe that's even something to be proud of. I opened my mouth and closed it.
She gave me a sad smile. Nothing, Siri, nothing at all. There was a time when you always knew
exactly what to say. She looked back at some earlier version of me.
Now I wonder if you actually meant any of it.
That's not fair. No, she pursed her lips. No, it isn't. That's not really what I'm trying to say.
I guess it's not so much that you don't mean any of it. It's more like you don't know what any of
it means. The color was gone from the wings. The butterfly was a delicate charcoal dusting,
almost motionless. I'll do it now, I said. I'll get the tweaks. If it's that important to you,
I'll do it now. It's too late, Siri. I'm used up. Maybe she wanted me to call her back.
All these words ending in question marks, all these significant silences. Maybe she was giving me
the opportunity to plead for my case, to beg for another chance. Maybe she wanted a reason to
change her mind. I could have tried. Please don't, I could have said. I'm begging you. I never meant
to drive you away completely, just a little, just to a safer distance. Please. In thirty long years,
the only time I haven't felt worthless is when we were together. But when I looked up again,
the butterfly was gone and so was she, taking all baggage with her. She carried doubt and guilt for
having led me on. She left believing that our incompatibility was no one's fault, that she
tried as hard as she could, even that I had under the tragic weight of all my issues. She left,
and maybe she didn't even blame me, and I never even knew who'd made that final decision.
I was good at what I did. I was so damned good I did it without even meaning to.
My god, did you hear that? Susan James bounced around the drum like a pranking wheeled a beast
in the half gravity. I could see the whites of her eyes from ninety degrees away.
Check your feeds, check your feeds, the pens! I checked. One scrambler afloat, the other still
jammed into its corner. James landed at my side with a two-footed thump, wobbling for balance.
Turn the sound up! The hissing of the air conditioners, the clank of distant machinery
echoing along with spine, theseus usual intestinal rumblings, nothing else. Okay, they're not doing
it now. James brought up a split-screen window and threw it into reverse.
THERE, she pronounced, replaying the record with the audio crank and filtered. In the right side
of the window, the floating scrambler had drifted so that the tip of one outstretched
arm brushed against the wall to join the other pen. In the left side, the huddled scrambler
remained unmoving. I thought I heard something. Just for an instant, the brief buzz of an insect,
perhaps if the nearest insect hadn't been five trillion kilometers away. Replay that,
slow it down. A buzz, definitely. A vibration. Way down. A click train, squirted from the dolphin's
forehead. Farting lips. No, let me. James bullied into Cunningham's headspace and yanked the slider
to the left. Tick-tick-tick, tick-tick-tick, tick-tick-tick. Doppler down near absolute zero,
it went on for almost a minute. Total elapsed real time was about half a second.
Cunningham zoomed the split-screen. The huddled scrambler had remained motionless,
except for the rippling of its cuticle and the undulation of its free arms.
But before, I'd only seen eight arms. Now I could make out the bony spur of a ninth from peaking
from behind the central mass. A ninth arm curled up and hidden from view, tick-tick-ticking while
another creature casually leaned against the other side of the wall. Now there was nothing.
The floating scrambler had drifted aimlessly back to the center of its enclosure.
James' eyes shone. We've got to check the rest of...
But Thesias had been watching and was way ahead of us. It had already searched the archives and
served up the results. Three similar exchanges over two days, ranging in duration from a tenth
of a second to almost two. They're talking, James said. Cunningham shrugged, a forgotten
cigarette burning down between his fingers. So do a lot of things, and at that rate of exchange,
they're not exactly doing calculus. You'd get as much information out of a dancing honeybee.
That's nonsense and you know it, Robert. What I know is that...
Honeybees don't deliberately hide what they're saying. Honeybees don't develop new whole new
modes of communication configured specifically to confound observers. That's flexible, Robert.
That's intelligent. And what if it is, hm? Forget for a moment the inconvenient fact that these
things don't even have brains. I really don't think you've thought this through. Of course I have.
Indeed, the more you're so happy about, don't you know what this means?
Suddenly, prickling on the back of my neck, I looked around. I looked up.
Yucca Sardosti had appeared in the center of the drum, eyes gleaming, teeth bared, watching us.
Cunningham followed my gaze and nodded. I had wager it does.
There was no way to learn what they'd whispered across that wall.
Enough. Parse every tick and tap they'd exchanged. But you can't decipher a code without some idea of
content. We had patterns of sound that could have meant anything. We had creatures whose grammar
and syntax, if their mode of communication even contained such attributes, were unknown.
And perhaps unknowable. We had creatures smart enough to talk and smart enough to hide this fact.
No matter how much we wanted to learn, they were obviously unwilling to teach us.
Not without, how had I put it, negative reinforcement.
It was Yucca Sardosti who made the decision. We did it on his orders, as we did everything else.
But after the word had come down, after Sardosti had disappeared into the night,
and Bates had retreated down the spine and Robert Cunningham had returned to his studies at the back
of the drum, I was the one Susan James was left with. The first to speak the vile thought aloud,
the official witness to posterity. I was the one she looked at and looked away from,
her surfaces hard and refractory. And then she started. This is how you break down a wall.
Start with two beings. They can be human if you like, but that's hardly a prerequisite.
All that matters is that they know how to talk among themselves. Separate them. Let them see each
other. Let them speak. Perhaps a window between their cages. Perhaps an audio feed. Let them
practice the art of conversation in their own chosen way. Hurt them. It may take a while to figure
out how. Some may shrink from fire, others some toxic gas or a liquid. Some creatures may be
invulnerable to blow torches and grenades, but shriek in terror at the threat of ultrasonic sound.
You have to experiment. And when you discover just the right stimulus,
the optimum balance between pain and injury, you must inflict it without remorse.
You leave them an escape hatch, of course. That's the very point of the exercise. Give
one of your subjects the means to end the pain, but give the other the information required to use it.
To one, you might present a single shape, while showing the other a whole selection.
The pain will stop when the being with the menu chooses the item its partner has seen.
So let the games begin. Watch your subjects squirm. If, when, they trip the off switch,
you'll know at least some of the information was exchanged.
And if you record everything that passed between them, you'll start to get some idea of how they
exchanged it. When they solve one puzzle, give them a new one. Mix things up. Switch their roles.
See how they do its circles versus squares. Try them out on factorials and fibonaches.
Continue until Rosetta Stone results. This is how you communicate with a fellow intelligence.
You hurt it and keep on hurting it until you can distinguish the speech from the screams.
Susan James, congenital optimist, high priestess of the Church of the Healing Word,
was best qualified to design and execute the protocols. Now at her command, the scramblers
writhe. They pulled themselves around their cages in elliptical loops, desperately seeking any small
corner free of stimulus. James had piped the feet into consensus, although there was no mission
critical reason for Thezi as whole crew to bear witness to the interrogation.
Let them block it at their ends, she said quietly, if they want to.
For all his reluctance to accept that these were beings intelligent and aware, Cunningham had named
the prisoners. Stretch tended to float spread eagle, clench was the bald up corner hugger.
Susan, playing her own part in this perverse role reversal, had simply numbered them one and two.
It wasn't that Cunningham's choices were too cheesy for her to stomach, or that she objected to
the slave names on principle. She'd just fallen back on the oldest trick in the torturer's handbook,
the one that lets you go home to your family after work and play with your children and sleep at
night. Never humanize your victims. It shouldn't have been such an issue when dealing with methane
breathing Medusae. I guess every little bit helped. Bio-telemetry danced across the headspace beside
each alien, luminous annotation shuddering through thin air. I had no idea what constituted normal
relings for these creatures, but I couldn't imagine these jagged spikes passing for anything but bad
news. The creatures themselves seethed subtly with fine mosaics in blue and gray, fluid patterns
rippling across their cuticles. Perhaps it was a reflexive reaction to the microwaves, for all we
knew it was a mating display. More likely they were screaming. James killed the microwaves.
In the left hand enclosure a yellow square dimmed. In the right, an identical icon nested among others
had never lit. The pigment flowed faster in the wake of the onslaught. The arms slowed but didn't
stop. They swept back and forth like listless skeletal eels. Baseline exposure, five seconds,
350 watts. She spoke for the record. Another affectation. Theseus recorded every breath on
record, every trickle of current to five decimal places. Repeat. The icon lit up. More tile patterns
flash flooding across alien skin. But this time, a nether alien moved from where it was. Their
arms continued to squirm slightly. A torqued, trembling variation on the undulation that they
affected at rest. The telemetry was as harsh as ever, though. They learned helplessness fast
enough, I reflect them. I glanced at Susan. Are you going to do this all by yourself?
Her eyes were bright and wet as she killed the current. Clenches icon dimmed. Stretches remained
dormant. I cleared my throat. I mean, who else is going to do this, Siri? Yuka? You? The rest of
the gang. Sasha could. Sasha, she stared at me. Siri, I created them. Do you think I did this so I
could hide behind them when, so I could force them to do things like this? She shook her head.
I'm not bringing them out. Not for this. I wouldn't do that to my worst enemy.
She turned away from me. There were drugs she could have taken. Neuro inhibitors to wash away
the guild. Short-sers could get right down to the molecules. Sodasti had offered them up as if he were
tempting some solitary messiah in the desert. James had refused him and would not say why.
Repeat, she said. The current flickered on and off.
Repeat, she said again. Not a twitch. I pointed. I see it, she said.
Clench had pressed the tip of one arm against the touchpad. The icon there glowed like a candle flame.
Six and a half minutes later, they'd graduated from yellow squares to time-lapse four-dimensional
polyhedrons. It took them as long to distinguish between two 26-faceted shifting solids,
differing by one facet in a single frame, as it took them to tell the difference between a yellow
square and a red triangle. Intricate patterns played across their surfaces the whole time.
Dynamic needlepoint mosaics flickering almost too fast to see.
Fuck, James whispered. Could be Splinter skills. Cunningham joined us in consensus,
although his body remained halfway around Biomed. Splinter skills, she repeated dully.
Savantism. High performance at one kind of calculation doesn't necessarily connote
high intelligence. I know what Splinter skills are, Robert. I just think you're wrong. Prove it.
So she gave up on geometry and told the scramblers that 1 plus 1 equal 2. Evidently,
they knew that already. Ten minutes later, they were predicting 10-digit prime numbers on demand.
She showed them a sequence of two-dimensional shapes. They picked the next one in the series from a menu
of subtly different alternatives. She denied them multiple choice, showed the beginning of a whole
new sequence, and taught them to draw on the touch-sensitive interface with the tips of their arms.
They finished that series in precise freehand, rendered a chain of logical descendants ending
with a figure that led inexorably back to the starting point. These aren't drones. James' voice
caught in her throats. This is all just crunching, Cunningham said. Millions of computer programs
do it without ever waking up. They're intelligent, Robert. They're smarter than us. Maybe they're
smarter than Yuka. And we're... why can't you just admit it? I could see it all over her.
Isaac would have admitted it. Because they don't have the circuitry, Cunningham insisted. How could...
I don't know how, she cried. That's your job. All I know is that I'm torturing beings that can
think rings around us. Not for much longer, at least. Once you figure out the language,
she shook her head. Robert, I haven't a clue about the language. We've been at it for
four hours, haven't we? The gang's all here. Language databases, 4,000 years, thick,
all the latest linguistic algorithms. And we know exactly what they're saying. We're watching every
possible way they could be saying it, right down to the angstrom. Precisely. So, I've got nothing.
I know they're talking through pigment mosaics. There might even be something in the way they
move those bristles, but I can't find the pattern. I can't even follow how they count, much less tell
them I'm... sorry. Nobody spoke for a while. Bates washed us from the galley on our ceiling,
but made no attempt to join the proceedings. On consensus, the reprieved scramblers floated
in their cages like multi-armed martyrs. Well, Cunningham said at last. Since this seems to
be the day for bad news, here's mine. They're dying. James put her face in her hand.
It's not your interrogation for whatever that's worth. The biologists continued.
As far as I can determine, some of their metabolic pathways are just missing.
Obviously, you just haven't found them yet. That was Bates speaking up from across the drum.
No, Cunningham said, and slowly and distinctly. Obviously, those parts are available to the
organism. Because they're falling apart pretty much the same way you'd expect one of us to, if
all the mitotic spindles in our cells just vanished out of the cytoplasm, for example.
As far as I can tell, they started deteriorating the moment we took them off Rorschach.
Susan looked up. Are you saying they left part of their biochemistry behind?
Some essential nutrient? Bates suggested. They're not eating.
Yes to the linguist, no to the major. Cunningham fell silent. I glanced across the drum to see
him sucking on a cigarette. I think a lot of the cellular processes in these things are mediated
externally. I think the reason I can't find any genes in my biopsies is because they don't have any.
So what do they have instead? Bates asked. Touring morphogens.
Blank looks. Subtitling looks. Cunningham explained anyway. A lot of biology doesn't use genes.
Sunflowers look the way they do because of purely physical buckling stress. You get Fibonacci sequences
and golden ratios everywhere in nature, and there's no gene codes for them. It's all just mechanical
interactions. Take a developing embryo. The genes say start growing or stop growing, but the number
of digits in vertebrae result from the mechanics of cells bumping up against other cells.
Those mitotic spindles I mentioned? Absolutely essential for replication in every eukaryotic cell,
and they accrete like crystals without any genetic involvement. You'd be surprised how much of life
is like that. But you still need genes, Bates protested, walking around to join us.
Genes just establish the starting conditions to enable the process. The structure that proliferates
afterwards doesn't need specific instructions. It's classic emergent complexity. We've
known about it for over a century. Another drag on the stick. Or even longer. Darwin cited
Honeycomb way back in the 1800s. Honeycomb, Bates repeated. Perfect hexagonal tubes in a packed
array. Bees are hardwired to lay them down, but how does an insect know enough geometry to lay
down a precise hexagon? It doesn't. It's programmed to chew up wax and spit it out while turning on
its axis. And that generates a circle. Put a bunch of bees on the same surface, chewing side by side
in the circles but butt against each other. To form each other into hexagons, which just happened
to be more efficient for close packing anyway. Bates pounced. But bees are programmed. Genetically.
You misunderstand. Scramblers are the honeycomb. Rorschach is the bees, Jates murmured.
Cunningham nodded. Rorschach is the bees. And I don't think Rorschach's magnetic fields are
counter intrusion mechanisms at all. I think they're part of the life support system. I think
they mediate and regulate a good chunk of scrambler metabolism. What we've got back in the hold is a
couple of creatures dragged out of their element and holding their breath. And they can't hold it
forever. How long, James asked. How should I know? If I'm right, I'm not even dealing with complete
organisms here. Guess, Bates said. He shrugged. A few days. Maybe.
That which does not kill us makes us stranger, Trevor Goodchild.
You still don't vote, Sotosti said. We would not be releasing the prisoners. Too risky.
Out here in the endless wastelands of the oar, there was no room for a live and let live.
Never mind what the other has done or what it hasn't. Think of what it could do, if it were
just a little stronger. Think of what it might have done if we had arrived as late as we were
supposed to. You look at Rorschach and perhaps you see an embryo or a developing child. Alien
beyond comprehension perhaps, but not guilty. Not by default. But what if those are the wrong eyes?
What if you should be seeing an omnipotent murdering god, a planet killer, not yet finished?
Vulnerable only now and for a little longer. There was no vampire opacity to that logic.
No multi-dimensional black boxes for humans to shrug at and throw up their hands.
There was no excuse for the failure to find fault with Sotosti's reasoning beyond the fact
that his reasoning was without fault. That made it worse. The others I knew would rather have had
to take something on faith. But Sotosti had an alternative to capture release, one he evidently
considered much safer. It took an act of faith to accept that reasoning, at least, by any sane
measure it averaged on suicide. Now, Theseus gave birth by Caesarean. These progeny were far too
massive to fit through the canal at the end of the spine. The ship shat them as if constipated,
directly into the hold. Great monstrous things, bristling with muzzles and antennae. Each stood
three or four times my height. A pair of massive, rust-colored cubes. Every surface infested with
topography. Armor plating would hide most of it prior to deployment, of course. Ribbons of piping
and conduit, ammunition reservoirs, and shark-tooth rows of radiator fins. All to disappear beneath
smoother, effective shielding. Only a few island landmarks would rise above that surface. Comports,
thrust nozzles, targeting arrays. And gunports, of course. These things spat fire and brimstone from
a half dozen mouths apiece. But for the time being, they were just mechanical fetuses. Half extruded,
their planes and angles a high contrast jigsaw of light and shadow in the harsh white glow of the
hold's flood lamps. I turned from the port. That's got to take our substrate stockpiles down a bit.
Shielding the carapace was worse. Bates monitored construction through a dedicated flat screen built
right into the fab bulkhead. Practicing, perhaps. We'd be losing our inlays as soon as the orbit
changed. We're tapping out, though. Might have to grab one of the local rocks before long.
Huh. I looked back into the hold. You think they're necessary? Doesn't matter what I think.
You're a bright guy, Siri. Why can't you figure that out? It matters to me. That means it matters
to Earth. Which might mean something if Earth was calling the shots. Some subtext was legible,
no matter how deep in the system you were. I tacked a port. How about Sadastiy and the captain,
then? Any thoughts? You're usually a bit more subtle. That much was true. It's just, you know,
Susan was the one that caught stretch and clench, tapping back and forth, right? Bates wins to the
names. So? Well, some might think it odd that Theseus wouldn't have seen it first, since quantum
computers are supposed to be so proficient, pattern matching. Sadastiy took the quantum modules offline.
The onboard's been running in classical mode since before we even made orbit. Why? Noisy
environment. Too much risk of decoherence. Quantum computers are finicky things.
Surely the onboard shielded. The Isius is shielded. Bates nodded. As much as feasible,
the perfect shielding is perfect blindness, and this is not the kind of neighborhood where you
want to keep your eyes closed. Actually, it was, but I took her point. I took her other point, too.
The one she didn't speak out loud. And you missed it. Something sitting right there in consensus
for anyone to see. Top of the line synthesis like you. Sadastiy knows what he's doing, I guess. I
admitted endlessly aware that he might be listening. He hasn't been wrong yet, as far as we know.
As far as we can know, Bates said. If you can second guess a vampire, you wouldn't need a vampire,
I remembered. She smiled faintly. Isaac was a good man. You can't always believe the PR, though.
You don't buy it, I asked. But she was already thinking she said too much. I threw out a hook,
baited with just a right mix of skepticism and deference. Sadastiy did know where those
scramblers would be. Nailed it almost to the meter, out of that whole maze.
I suppose that might have taken some superhuman logic, she admitted.
Thinking I was so fucking dumb she couldn't believe it.
What? I said. Bates shrugged. Or maybe he just realized that since Rorschach was growing its own
crew, we'd run into more every time we went in, no matter where we landed. Consensus bleeped into
my silence. Orbital maneuvers starting in five, Sadastiy announced. Inlays and wireless
prosthetics offline in 90. That's all. Bates shut down the display. I'm gonna ride this out in the
bridge. Illusion of control and all that. You? My tent, I think. She nodded and braced to jump and
hesitated. By the way, she told me. Yes. Sorry? You asked if I thought the emplacements were
necessary. Right now I think we need all the protection we can get. So you think that Rorschach
might... hey, it already killed me once. She wasn't talking about radiation. I nodded carefully.
That must have been... like nothing at all. You couldn't possibly imagine. Bates took a breath
and let it out. Maybe you don't have to. She added and sailed away up the spine.
Cunningham and the gang in Biomed, 30 degrees of arc between them. Each poked their captives in
their own way. Susan James stabbed indifferently at a keypad painted across her desktop.
Windows to either side looked in on stretch and clench.
Cookie-cutter shapes scrolled across the desk as James typed.
Circles, triskellions, a quartet of parallel lines. Some of them pulsed like abstract little hearts.
In his distant pen, stretch reached out one fraying tentacle and tapped something in turn.
Any progress? She sighed and shook her head. I've given up trying to understand their language.
I'm settling for a pigeon. She tapped an icon. Clench vanished from his window,
a hieroglyphic flowchart sprang up in his place. Half the symbols regal or pulsed endlessly repetitive,
a riot of dancing noodles. Others just sat there.
Iconic bass. James waved vaguely at the display. Subject verb phrases render as animated versions
of noun icons. They're radially symmetrical, so I array modifiers in a circular pattern around
the central subject. Maybe that comes naturally to them. A new circle of glyphs appeared beneath
James's. Stretches reply, presumably. But something in the system didn't like what it saw.
Icons flared in a separate window. Illuminous counter flashed 500 watts since held steady.
On the screen, stretch writhed. It reached out with squirming backbone arms and stabbed
repeatedly at its touched pad. James looked away. New glyphs appeared. 500 watts retreated to zero.
Stretch returned to its holding pattern, the spikes and jags of its telemetry smoothed.
James let out her breath. What happened, I asked. Wrong answer. She tapped into stretch's feed,
showed me the display that it tripped it up. A pyramid, a star, a simplified representations
of a scrambler and of Rorschach rotated on the board. It was stupid. It was just a warm-up exercise,
really. I asked it to name the objects in the window. She laughed softly and without humor.
That's the thing about functional languages, you know. If you can't point at it, you can't talk
about it. And what did it say? She pointed at stretch's first spiral. Polyhedron star Rorschach
are present. It missed the scrambler. Got it right the second time. Still, stupid mistake for something
that can think rings around a vampire, isn't it? Susan swallowed. I guess even scramblers slip up
when they're dying. I didn't know what to say. Behind me, barely audible, Cunningham muttered
some two-stroke mantra to himself in an endless loop. Yuka says Susan stopped, began again.
You know that blind sight we get sometimes in Rorschach? I nodded and wondered what Yuka had said.
Apparently the same thing had happened to the other senses, too, she told me. You can have
blind touch and blind smell and blind hearing. That would be deafness. She shook her head.
But it isn't really, is it? Any more than blind sight is really blindness. Something in your
head is still taking it all in. Something in the brain is still seeing and hearing, even if you're
not aware of it. Unless someone forces you to guess, or there's some threat, you just get a really
strong feeling. You should move out of the way. And five seconds later a bus drives over the spot
you were standing. You knew it was coming somehow. You just don't know how you knew. It's wild, I
agreed. These scramblers, they know the answer, Siri. They're intelligent. We know they are.
But it's almost as though they don't know they know unless you hurt them, as if they've got
blind sight spread over every sense. I tried to imagine it. Life without sensation, without any
active awareness of one's environment. I tried to imagine existing like that without going mad.
Do you think that's possible? I don't know. It's just a metaphor, I guess. She didn't believe that,
or she didn't know, or she didn't want me to know. I should have been able to tell. She should have
been clear. At first I thought they were just resisting, she said. But why would they? She
turned bright, begging eyes on me, pleading for an answer. I didn't have one. I didn't have a clue.
I turned away from Susan James, only to find myself facing Robert Cunningham. Cunningham,
the mutterer, fingers tapped against tabletop interfaces, inner eyes blinded, vision limited
now to the picture's consensus sketched in airspace or through against flat surfaces for
everyone to see. His face remained as empty as a feeling as it had ever been, the rest of his body
twitched like a bug in a spider web. He might as well have been. We all might. Rorschach loomed
barely nine kilometers away now, so near it might have eclipsed Ben itself if I had been brave enough
to look outside. We had closed this insane proximity and parked. Out there, Rorschach grew like a live
thing. In there, live things grew, butted like jellyfish from some demonic mechanical substrate.
Those lethal vacant corridors we'd crept along frightened of the shadows planted in our heads.
They were probably filling with scramblers right now. All those hundreds of kilometers of twisted
tunnels and passages and chambers filled filling with an army. This was Sadastie's safer alternative.
This was the path we'd followed because it would have been too dangerous to release the prisoners.
We were so deep inside the bow shock that we'd had to shut down our internal augments,
while Rorschach's magnetosphere was orders of magnitude weaker here than within the structure
itself. Who knew if the alien might find us too tempting a target or too great a threat at this
range? Who knew when it might choose to plunge some invisible spike through Thesias' heart?
Any pulse that could penetrate the ship's shielding would doubtlessly fry Thesias' nervous system,
as well as the wiring in our heads. I suppose that five people in a dead ship would have
a marginally greater chance of survival if their brains weren't sparking in the bargain,
but I doubted that such a difference would make much difference. Sadastie had obviously figured
the odds differently. He'd even shut down the anti-euclidean pump in his own head, resorted
to manual injections to keep himself from short-circuiting. Stretch and clench were even closer
to Rorschach than we were. Cunningham's lab and we'd kicked free of the ship. It floated now just
a few kilometers from the artifacts' outermost spires, deep within the folds of its magnetic field.
If the scramblers needed radioactive magnetite to function, this was the key they were going to get,
a taste of the fields but not of freedom. The lab's shielding was being dynamically fine-tuned
to balance medical necessity against tactical risk, as best the data allowed. The structure
floated in the watchful crosshairs of our newborn gun emplacements, strategically positioned to the
other side. Those emplacements could destroy the habit in an instant. They could probably destroy
anything approaching it as well. They couldn't destroy Rorschach, of course. Maybe nothing could.
Covert to invulnerable. As far as we knew, that hadn't happened yet. Presumably Thesias could
still do something about the artifact accreting off our bow, assuming we could decide which thing to do.
Sadastie wasn't talking. In fact, I couldn't remember the last time any of us had seen the
vamp higher in the flesh. For several shifts now, he had confined himself to his tent, speaking only
through consensus. Everyone was on edge, and the transient had gone quiet. Cunningham muttered to
himself, stabbed at unfamiliar controls with unpracticed fingers, cursed his own clumsiness.
Stimulus and response flowed through the lasers across six kilometers of ionized vacuum.
The ever-present nicotine stick hung from one corner of his mouth for want of a free hand.
Every now and then, flecks of ash broke free and drifted obliquely toward the ventilators.
He spoke before I could. It's all in consensus. When I didn't leave, he relented but wouldn't look at me.
Magnetite flecks lined up as soon as they got past the wavefront more or less.
Membranes started to fix themselves. They're not failing as fast, but it's Rorschach's internal
environment that will be optimized for scramble metabolism. Out here, I think the most we can
do is slow the rate of dying. That's something, at least. Cunningham grunted. Some of the pieces
are coming together. Others, their nerves are frayed for no good reason. Literally, single leakage
along the cables. Because of the deterioration, I guess. And I can't get the Arianna's equation
to balance. There's all this nonlinearly at low temperatures. The pre-exponential value is completely
fucked up. It's almost as though temperature doesn't matter and...shit. Some critical value
had exceeded a confidence limit on one of his displays. He glanced up at the drum and raised
his voice. Need another biopsy, Susan. Anywhere central. What? Oh, just a second. She shook her
head and tapped off a brief spiral of icons, as listless as the captive she commanded.
On one of Cunningham's windows, Stretch viewed her input with its marvelous sighted skin.
It floated unresponsive for a moment. Then it folded back the arms facing one wall,
opening a clear path for Cunningham's telops. He called two of them from their burrows like
prehensile serpents. The first wielded a clinical core sampler. The second wielded the threat of
violence in case of foolish resistance. It was hardly necessary. Blindsided or not,
scramblers were fast learners. Stretch exposed its belly like a victim resigned to imminent rape.
Cunningham fumbled. The telops bumped together, briefly entangled. He cursed and tried again,
every move shouting frustration. His extended phenotype had been amputated. Once the very ghost
in the machine, now he was just another guy punching buttons and...and suddenly something clicked.
Cunningham's facade swirled a translucency before my eyes. Suddenly I could almost imagine him.
He got it right the second time. The tip of his machine shot out like a striking snake and darted
back again, almost too fast to see. Waves of color flushed from Stretch's injury like ripples
chased across still water by a falling stone. Cunningham must have thought he saw something in
my face. It helps if you try not to think of them as people, he said. And for the very first time I
could read the subtext as clear and as sharp as broken glass. Of course, you don't think of anyone
that way. Cunningham didn't like to be played. No one does. But most people don't think that's
what I'm doing. They don't know how much their bodies betray when they close their mouths. When
they speak aloud it's because they want to confide. When they don't, they think they're keeping
their opinions to themselves. I watched them so closely, customize each word so that no system
ever feels used. And yet for some reason that didn't work with Robert Cunningham. I think I was
modeling the wrong system. Imagine you are a synthesisist. You deal in the behavior of systems
at their services. Infer the machinery beneath from its reflections above. That is the secret of
your success. You understand the system by understanding the boundaries that contain it.
Now imagine you encounter someone who has ripped a hole in those boundaries and bled beyond them.
Robert Cunningham's flesh could not contain him. His duties pulled him beyond the meat sack. Here in
the oar, his topology rambled all over the ship. That was true of all of us to some extent. Bates
and her drones. Sudosti and his limbic link, even the consensus inlaze in our heads, diffused us a bit,
spread us just slightly beyond the confines of our own bodies. But Bates only ran her drones.
She never inhabited them. The gang of four may have run multiple systems on a single motherboard,
but each had its own distinct topology, and they only ever surfaced one at a time. And Sudosti,
well, Sudosti was a whole different story as it turned out. Cunningham didn't just operate his
remotes. He escaped into them, wore them like a secret identity to hide the feeble human baseline
within. He had sacrificed half of his neocortex for the chance to see X-rays and taste the shapes
hiding in cell membranes. He had butchered one body to become a fleeting tenant of many.
Pieces of him hidden the sensors and manipulators that lined the scrambler's cages. I might have
gleaned vital clues from every piece of equipment in the sub-drum if I'd ever thought to look.
Cunningham was a topological jigsaw like everyone else, but half his pieces were hidden in machinery.
My model was incomplete. I don't think he ever aspired to such a state. Looking back,
I see radiant self-loathing on every remembered surface. But there in the waning years of the
21st century, the only alternative he could see was the life of a parasite. Cunningham merely
chose the lesser evil. Now even that was denied him. Sudosti's orders had severed him from his
own sensorium. He no longer felt the data in his gut. He had to interpret it, step by laborious
step, through the screens and graphs that reduced perception to flat empty shorthand.
Here was a system traumatized by multiple amputations. Here was a system with its eyes and
ears and tongue cut out, forced to stumble and feel its way around things it had once inhabited,
right down to the bone. Suddenly there was nowhere else to hide. And all those far-flung
pieces of Robert Cunningham tumbled back into his flesh where I could see them at last.
It had been my mistake all along. I'd been so focused on modeling other systems that I'd
forgotten about the one doing the modeling. Bad eyes are only one bane of clear vision.
Bad assumptions can be just as blinding, and it wasn't enough to imagine I was Robert Cunningham.
I had to imagine I was Ciri Keaton as well.
Of course, that only raises another question. If my guess about Cunningham was right, why did my
tricks work on Isaac Spindle? He was every bit as discontinuous as his replacement.
I didn't think about it much at the time. Spindle was gone, but the thing that had killed him was
still there, hanging right off the bow, a vast swelling enigma that might choose to squash us
at any instant. I was more than a little preoccupied. Now, though, far too late to do anything about it,
I think I might know the answer. Maybe my tricks didn't work on Isaac either, not really. Maybe he
saw through my manipulations as easy as Cunningham did. But maybe he just didn't care. Maybe I could
read him because he let me. Which would mean I can't find another explanation that fits,
that he just liked me, regardless. I think that might have made him a friend.
If I can but make the words awake the feeling, Ian Anderson sand up.
Night shift. Not a creature was stirring. Not an thesy as anyway. The gang hid in their tent.
The transient lurked weightless and silent but low the surface. Bates was in the bridge. She more
or less lived up there now, vigilant and conscientious, nested in camera angles and tactical overlays.
There was nowhere she could turn without seeing some aspect of the cipher off our starboard bow.
She did what good she could for the good it would do. The drum turned quietly. Light stemmed
indeference to a dial cycle that a hundred years of tweaks and retrofits hadn't been able to
to weed from the jeans. I sat alone in the galley, squinting from the inside of a system whose
outlines grew increasingly hazy, trying to compile my latest, how would Isaac put it,
postcard to posterity. Cunningham worked upside down on the other side of the world.
Except Cunningham wasn't working. He hadn't even moved for at least four minutes. I'd assumed he
was reciting the cut-ish for spindle. Consensus said he'd been doing it twice daily for the next
year, if we'd lived that long. But now, leaning to see around the spinal bundles in the core,
I could read his surfaces as clearly as if I'd been sitting beside him.
He wasn't bored or distracted or even deep in thought.
Robert Cunningham was petrified. I stood and paced the drum. Ceiling turned into wall,
wall into floor. I was close enough to hear his incessant stoff muttering. A single indistinct
syllable repeated over and over that I was close enough to hear what he was saying. Fuck, fuck,
fuck, fuck, fuck. And still Cunningham didn't move, although I'd made no attempt to mask my approach.
Finally, when I was almost at his shoulder, he fell silent.
You're blind, he said without turning. Did you know that?
I didn't. You, me, everyone. He interlocked his fingers and clenched as if in prayer,
hard enough to whiten the knuckles. Only then did I notice. No cigarette.
Visions mostly a lie anyway, he continued. We don't really see anything except a few
high-res degrees where the eye focuses. Everything else is just a peripheral blur,
just light in motion. Motion draws the focus and your eyes jiggle all the time. Did you know that,
Keaton? Cicades, they're called. Blurs the image. The movement's way too fast for the brain to
integrate so your eye just shuts down between pauses. It only grabs those isolated freeze frames,
but your brain edits out the blanks and stitches in an illusion of continuity into your head.
He turned to face me. And you know what's really amazing? If something only moves during the gaps,
your brain just ignores it. It's invisible. I glanced at his workspace. The usual split-spring
glowed to one side, real-time images of the scramblers in their pens,
but histology, 10,000 times larger than life, took center stage. The paradoxical neural
architecture of stretch and clench glistened on the main window,
flensed and labeled and overlaid by circuit diagrams a dozen layers thick.
A dense, annotated forest of alien trunks and brambles. It looked a little bit like Rorschach
itself. I couldn't parse any of it. Are you listening, Keaton? Do you know what I'm saying?
You figured out why I couldn't. You're saying these things can somehow tell when our eyes are
offline and I didn't finish. It just didn't seem possible. Cunningham shook his head.
Something that sounded disturbingly like a giggle escaped his mouth. I'm saying these things can
see your nerves firing from across the room and integrate that into a cryptos strategy,
and then send motor commands to act on that strategy, and then send other commands to stop
the motion before your eyes come back online. All in the time it would take a mammalian nerve
impulse to make it halfway from your shoulder to your elbow. These things are fast, Keaton. Way
faster than we could have guessed even from that high-speed whisper line they were using.
They're bloody superconductors. It took a conscious effort to keep frowning. Is that even possible?
Every nerve impulse generates an electromagnetic field that makes it detectable. But Rorschach's
EM fields are so... I mean, reading the firing of a single optic nerve through all that interference,
it's not interference. The fields are part of them, remember? That's probably how they do it.
So they couldn't do that here. You're not listening. The trap you said wouldn't have caught
anything like that, not unless it wanted to be caught. We didn't grab specimens at all. We grabbed spies.
Stretch and clench floated in split-screen before us, arm swaying like undulating backbones.
Cryptic patterns played slowly across their cuticles.
Supposing it's just instinct, I suggested. Flounders hide their background pretty well,
but they don't think about it. Where are they going to get that instinct from, Keaton? How is it
going to evolve? Cicades are an accidental glitch in mammalian vision. Where would scramblers have
encountered them before now? Cunningham shook his head. That thing, that thing a man does robot
fried. It developed that strategy on its own, on the spot. It improvised. The word intelligent
barely encompassed that kind of improvisation. But there was something else in Cunningham's face,
some deeper distress nested inside what we'd already told me.
What, I asked. It was stupid, he said. The things these creatures can do, it was just dumb.
How do you mean? Well, it didn't work, did it? Couldn't keep it up in front of more than one or
two of us. Because people's eyes don't flicker in sync, I realized. Too many witnesses stripped
it of cover. Many other things it could have done, Cunningham was saying. They could have induced
antons or, or an agnosia. Then we could have tripped over a whole herd of scramblers and it
wouldn't even register in our conscious minds. Agnosias happen by accident for God's sake.
If you've got the stress and reflexes to hide between someone's cicades, why stop there?
Why not do something that really works?
Why do you think, I asked, reflexively non-directive?
I think that the first one was, you know it was a juvenile, right? Maybe it was just inexperienced.
Maybe it was stupid and it made a bad decision. I think we're dealing with a species so far
beyond us that even their retarded children can rewire our brains on the fly and I can't tell
you how fucking scared that should make you. I could see it in his topology. I could hear it in
his voice. His nervous face remained as calm as a corpse. We should just kill them now, he said.
Well if they're spies they can't have learned much. They've been in those cages the whole time,
except for the way up. They'd been right next to us for the whole trip back. These things live
and breathe, E.M. Even stunted, even isolated. Who knows how much of our tech they could have
just read through the walls. You've got to tell Sotosti, I said. Oh, Sotosti knows. Why do you
think he wouldn't let them go? He never said anything about. He'd be crazy to fill us in.
He keeps sending you down there, remember? Do you think for a second he'd tell you what he knows
and then set you loose in the labyrinth full of mind-reading minotaurs? He knows and he's already
got it factored a thousand ways to Sunday. Cunningham's eyes were bright manic points
blazing in an expressionless mask. He raised them to the center of the drum, and he didn't raise
his voice decibel. Isn't that right, Yuka? I check consensus for active channels. I don't think he's
listening, Robert. Cunningham's mouth moved in something that would have been a pitying smile
if the rest of the face had been able to join in. He doesn't have to listen, Keaton. He doesn't have
to spy on us. He just knows. Then later is breathing, the almost subliminal hum of bearings in motion.
Then Sotosti's disembodied voice rang forth through the drum. Everyone to commons. Robert wants to share.
Cunningham sat to my right, his plastic face lit from beneath by the conference table.
He stared down into that light, rocking slightly. His lips went through the ongoing
motions of some inaudible incantation. The gang sat across from us. To my left,
Bates kept one eye on the proceedings and another on intelligence from the front lines.
Sotosti was with us only in spirit. His place at the head of the table remained empty.
Tell them, he said. We have to get out of from the beginning.
Cunningham swallowed and started again.
Those frayed motor nerves I couldn't figure out, those pointless cross connections,
their logic gates, scramblers' time share. Their sensory and motor plexi double as
associative neurons during idle time so every part of the system can be used for cognition
when it isn't otherwise engaged. Nothing like it ever evolved on Earth. It means they can do
a great deal of processing without a lot of dedicated associative mass, even for an individual.
So peripheral nerves can think, Bates frowned. Can they remember?
Certainly. At least I don't see why not. Cunningham pulled a cigarette from his pocket.
So when they tore that scrambler apart, not civil war, data dump, passing information about us,
most likely. Pretty radical way to carry on a conversation, Bates remarked.
It wouldn't be their first choice. I think each scrambler acts as a node in a distributed network,
when they're in war shock at least. But those fields would be configured down to the angstrom,
and we go in with our tech and shielding and blowing holes in their conductors,
we ballots up the network, jam the local signal, so they resort to a sneaker net.
He had not lit his cigarette. He rolled the filtered end between thumb and forefinger.
His tongue flickered between his lips like a worm behind a mask.
Hidden in his tent, Savasti took up the slack.
Scramblers also used Rorschach's EM for metabolic processes.
Some pathways achieve proton transfer via heavy atom tunneling. Perhaps the ambient
radiation acts as a catalyst. Tunneling, Susan said. As in quantum? Cunningham nodded.
Which also explains your shielding problems, partly at least.
But is that even possible? I mean, I thought those kind of effects only showed up under cryonic.
Forget this, Cunningham blurted. We can debate the biochemistry later if we're still alive.
What do we debate instead, Robert? Savasti said smoothly.
For starters, the dumbest of these things can look into your head and see what parts of your
visual cortex are lighting up. And if there's a difference between that and mind reading,
it's not much of one. As long as we stay out of Rorschach. That ship has sailed. You people have
already been there. Repeatedly. Who knows what you already did down there for no better reason
than because Rorschach made you. Wait a second, baits objected. None of us were puppets down there.
We hallucinated and we went blind and and crazy even, but we were never possessed.
Cunningham looked at her and snorted.
You think you'd be able to fight the strings? You think you'd even feel them? I could apply
a transcranial magnet to your head right now, and you'd raise your middle finger or wriggle your
toes or kick Ciri here in the sack and then swear on your sainted mother's grave that you only did
it because you wanted to. You'd dance like a puppet and all the time swear you were doing it
of your own free will and that's just me. That's just some borderline OCD with a couple of magnets
and a MRI helmet. He waved at the vast unknowable void beyond the bulkhead. Shreds of mangled
cigarette floated sideways in front of him. Do you want to guess what that can do? For all we
know we've already given them the easiest technical specs, warned them about the Icarus Array,
and then just decided of our own free will to forget it all.
We can cause those effects, Sardasie said coolly. As you say, strokes cause them.
Tumors. Random accidents. Random, those were experiments people. That was vivisection.
They let you in so they could take you apart and see what made you tick and you never even knew it.
So what? The vampire snapped invisibly. Something cold and hungry had edged into his voice.
Human topology shivered around the table, skittish.
There is a blind spot in the center of your visual field, Sardasie pointed out.
You can't see it. You can't see the saccades in your visual time stream.
Just two of the tricks you know about. Many others.
Cunningham was nodding. That's my whole point. Rorschach could be
not talking about case studies. Brains are survival engines, not truth detectors.
If self-deception promotes fitness, the brain lies.
Stops noticing irrelevant things. Truth never matters. Only fitness.
By now, you don't experience the world as it exists at all. You experience a simulation
built from assumptions. Shortcuts. Lies. Whole species is agnostic by default.
Rorschach does nothing to you that you don't already do to yourselves.
Nobody spoke. It was several silent seconds before I realized what had happened.
Yuka Sardasie had just given us a pep talk. He could have shut down Cunningham's Tyrod.
Could have probably shut down a full-scale mutiny by just sailing into our midst and
burying his teeth. By looking at us. But he wasn't trying to frighten us into submission.
We were already nervous enough. And he wasn't trying to educate us either. Fight fear with fact.
The more facts any sane person gathered about Rorschach, the more fearful they'd become.
Sardasie was only trying to keep us functional, lost in space at the edge of our lives,
facing down this monstrous enigma that might destroy us at any instant for any reason.
Sardasie was trying to calm us down. Good meat. Nice meat. He was trying to keep us from falling
apart. There, there. Sardasie was practicing psychology. I looked around the table. Bates
and Cunningham and the gang sat still and motionless. Sardasie sucked at it.
We have to get out of here. Cunningham said. These things are way beyond us.
We've shown more aggression than they have, James said, but there was no confidence in her voice.
Rorschach plays those rocks like marbles. We're sitting in the middle of a shooting gallery.
Anytime it feels like it's still growing, it's not finished.
That's supposed to reassure me. All I'm saying is we don't know, James said.
We could have years yet, centuries. We have 15 days, Sardasie announced.
Oh shit, someone said. Cunningham probably. Maybe Sasha. For some reason everyone was looking at me.
15 days. Who knows what had gone into that number. None of us had asked aloud.
Maybe Sinosti in another fit of inept psychology had made it up on the spur of the moment.
Or maybe he'd derived it before we'd even reached orbit, held it back against the possibility,
only now expired, that he might yet send us back into the labyrinth.
I'd been half blind for half the mission. I didn't know. But one way or another, we had our graduation day.
The coffins lay against the rear bulkhead of the crypt. On what would be the floor during those
moments when up and down held any meaning. We'd slept for years on the way out. We'd had no
awareness of time's passage. Undead metabolism is far too sluggish to even support dreams.
But somehow the body knew when it needed a change. Not one of us had chosen to sleep in our pods
since we'd arrived. The only times we'd done so had been on pain of death. But the gang had taken
to coming here ever since Spindle died. His body rested in the pod next to mine. I coasted into
the compartment and turned left without thinking. Five coffins, four open and emptied, one sealed.
The mirrored bulkhead opposite doubled their number in the depth of the compartment.
But the gang wasn't there. I turned right. The body of Susan James floated back and back
with her own reflection, staring at an inverse to blow. Three sealed sarcophagi, one open.
The ebony plaque set into the retracted lid was dark. The others shown with identical sparse mosaics
of blue and green stars. None of them changed. There were no scrolling ECGs, no luminous peak
and valley tracings marked cardio or CNS. We could wait here for hours, days, and none of those diodes
would so much as twinkle. When you're undead, the emphasis is on the second syllable. The gang's
topology had said Michelle when I'd first arrived, but it was Susan who spoke now without turning.
I never met her. I followed her gaze to the name tag of one of the sealed pods, Takamatsu,
the other linguist, the other multiple. I met everyone else, Susan continued, trained with them.
But I never met my own replacement.
They discouraged it. Well, but it'd been the point.
If you want to, I began. She shook her head. Thanks anyway.
Or any of the others. I can only imagine what Michelle, Susan smiled, but there was something
cold about it. Michelle doesn't really want to talk to you right now, Siri. Ah, I hesitated for a
moment to give anyone else a chance to speak up. When nobody did, I pushed myself back towards the
hatch. Well, if any of you changed, no. None of us ever. Cruncher. You lie, he continued.
I see it. We all do. I blinked. Why? No, I... You don't talk. You listen. You don't care about
Michelle. You don't care about anyone. You just want what we know. For your reports.
That's not entirely true, Cruncher. I do care. I know Michelle must... You don't know shit. Go away.
I'm sorry I upset you. I rolled on my axis and braced against the mirror.
You can't know Mish, he growled as I pushed off. You never lost anyone. You never had anyone.
You leave her alone.
He was wrong on both counts, and at least Spindle had died knowing Michelle cared for him.
Chelsea died thinking I just didn't give a shit. It had been two years or more, and while we still
interfaced occasionally, we hadn't met in the flesh since the day she'd left. She called me from
right out of the oar to send an urgent voice message to my inlays, Signeus, please call now,
it's important. It was the first time since I'd known her that she'd ever blanked the optics.
I knew it was important. I knew it was bad even without picture. I knew because there was no picture,
and I could tell it was worse than bad from the harmonics in her voice. I could tell it was lethal.
I found out afterwards that she'd gotten caught in the crossfire. The realists had sewn a fibro
dysplasia variant outside the Boston catacombs. An easy tweak, a single point retro viral whose
results served both as an act of terrorism and an ironic commentary on the frozen paralysis of
Heaven's occupants. It rewrote a regulatory gene controlling ossification on chromosome 4,
and rigged a metabolic bypass at 3 loci on 17. Chelsea started growing a new skeleton. Her joints
were calcifying within 15 hours of exposure, her ligaments and tendons within 20. By then,
they were starving her at the cellular level, trying to slow the bug by depriving it of metabolites.
But they could only buy time and not much of it. 23 hours in, her striated muscles were turning
to stone. I didn't find this out immediately because I didn't call her back. I didn't need to know
the details. I could tell from her voice that she was dying. Obviously she wanted to say goodbye.
I couldn't talk to her until I knew how to do that. I spent hours scouring the new sphere looking
for precedents. There was no shortage of ways to die. I found millions of case records dealing with
the etiquette. Last words, last vows, instruction manuals for the soon to be bereaved, palliative
nerefram, extended and expository death scenes in popular fiction. I went through it all, assigned
a dozen front line filters to separate heat from light. By the time she called again, the news was
out. A cute golem outbreak lancing would like a white hot needle through the heart of Boston.
Containment measures holding, heaven secure. Modest casualties expected. Names of victims
withheld pending notification of kin. I still didn't know the principles, the rules, all I had
were examples. Last wills and testaments, the negotiation of jumpers with their would be rescuers,
diaries recovered from imploded submarines or lunar crash sites, recorded memoirs and deathbed
confessions rattling into flatline, black box transcripts of doomed spaceships and falling
beanstalks ending in fire and static. All of it relevant. None of it useful. None of it her.
She called again and still the optics were blank. And I still didn't answer.
But the last time she called, she didn't spare me the view. They've made her as comfortable as
possible. The gel pad conformed to every twisted limb, every erupting spur of bone.
They would not have left her in any pain. Her neck had torqued down into the side as it petrified
after staring at the twisted claw that had once been her right hand. Her knuckles were the size
of walnuts. Plates and ribbons of ectopic bone distended the skin of her arms and shoulders,
buried her ribs in a fibrous mat of calcified flesh. Movement was its own worst enemy.
Golem punished even the slightest twitch, provoked the growth of fresh bone along in any joints
and surfaces conspiring to motion. Each hinge and socket had its own non-renewable ration of
flexibility carved in stone. Every movement depleted the account. The body seized incrementally.
By the time she let me look at her, Chelsea had almost exhausted her degrees of freedom.
Sigg, she slurred. No, you're there. Her jaw was locked half open. Her tongue must have stiffened
with every word. She did not look at the camera. She could not look at the camera.
Guess I know why you're not answering. I'll try not to take it personally.
Ten thousand deathbed goodbyes are right around me, a million more within reach.
What was I supposed to do? Pick one at random? Stitch them into some kind of composite?
All these words had been for other people. Graffiting them onto Chelsea would reduce them
to cliches or trite platitudes, to insults. Want to say, don't feel bad. I know you're just,
it's not your fault, I guess. You'd pick up if you could. And say what? What do you see as someone
who's dying and fast-forward before your eyes? Just keep trying to connect, you know? Can't help myself.
Although the essentials of this farewell are accurate, details from several deaths have been
combined for dramatic purposes. Please, just talk to me, Sige. More than anything, I wanted to.
Siri, I just... I'd spent all this time trying to figure out how. Forget it, she said, and disconnected.
I whispered something into the dead air. I don't even remember what. I really wanted to talk to her.
I just couldn't find an algorithm that fit.
Ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you mad.
Aldous Huxley.
They'd hoped by now, who'd vanished to sleep forever. The waste was nothing short of obscene.
A third of every human life, with its strings cut, insensate, the body burning fuel but not producing.
Think of all we could accomplish if we didn't have to lapse into unconsciousness
every 15 hours or so, if our minds could stay awake and alert from the moment of infancy to that
final curtain call 120 years later. Think of 8 million souls with no off switch and no downtime
until the very chassis wore out. Why, we could go to the stars. It hadn't worked out that way.
Even if we'd overgrown the need to stay quiet and hidden during the dark hours,
the only predators left were those we'd brought back ourselves. The brain still needed time apart
from the world outside. Experiences had to be catalogued and filed, mid-term memories promoted
to long-term ones, free radicals swept from their hiding places among the dendrites.
We had only reduced this need for sleep, not eliminated it, and that incompressible residue
of downtime seemed barely able to contain the dreams and phantoms left behind. They squirmed
in my head like creatures in a draining tidal pool. I woke. I was alone, weightless,
in the center of my tent. I could have sworn something had tapped me on the back.
Left over hallucination, I thought, a lingering after-effect of the haunted mansion,
going for one last bit of goose flesh on route to extinction.
But it happened again. I bumped against the keelward curve of the bubble,
bumped again, head and shoulder blades against fabric. The rest of me came after,
moving gently but irresistibly, down. Theseus was accelerating.
No, wrong direction. Theseus was rolling, like a harpooned whale at the surface of the sea,
turning her belly to the stars. I brought up consensus and threw a NavTax summary against
the wall. A luminous point erupted from the outline of our ship, crawled away from Big Ben,
leaving a bright filament etched in its wake. I watched until the numbers read 15G.
Siri, my quarters, please. I jumped. It sounded as though the vampire had been at my very shoulder.
Coming.
An ampsat relay, climbing at long last to an intercept with the Icarus Antanatter stream.
Somewhere behind the call of duty, my heart sank. We weren't running.
Robert Cunningham's fondest wishes notwithstanding. Theseus was stockpiling ordinance.
The open hatch gaped like a cave in the face of a cliff. The pale blue light from the spine
couldn't seem to reach inside. Sirasti was barely more than a silhouette, black on gray,
his bright bloody eyes reflecting catlike in the surrounding gloom. Come. He amped up the
shorter wavelengths in deference to human vision. The interior of the bubble brightened,
although the light remained slightly redshifted like Rorschach with high beams.
I floated into Sirasti's parlor. His face, normally paper white, was so flushed it looked sunburned.
He gorged himself. I couldn't help thinking. He drank deep. But all that blood was his own.
Usually he kept it deep in the flesh, favoring the vital organs. Vampires were efficient that way.
They only washed out their ter- their peripheral tissues occasionally when lactate levels got too high.
Or when they were hunting. He had a needle to his throat, injected himself with three C.C.'s of
clear liquid as I watched, his anti-euclidians. I wondered how often he had to replenish them now
that he'd lost faith in the implants. He withdrew the needle and slipped it into a sheath, geckoded
to a convenient strut. His color drained as I watched, sinking back to the core, leaving his skin
waxy and corpse-like. You're here as official observer, Sirasti said. I observed. His corridors
were even more spartan than mine. No personal effects to speak of. No custom coffin lined with
shrink-wrapped soil. Nothing but two jumpsuits, a pouch for toiletries, and a disconnected fiber
opumbillicus half as thick as my little finger, floating like a roundworm in formalin. Sonasi's
hardline to the captain. Not even a cortical jack, I remembered. It plugged into the medulla, the
brainstem. That was logical enough. That was all where the neural cabling converged, the point of
greatest bandwidth. Still, it was a disquieting thought. That Sonasi linked to the ship through
the brain of a reptile. An image flared on the wall, subtly distorted against the concave surface,
stretch and clench in their adjoining cells rendered in split-screen.
Cryptic vitals defaced little grids below each image. The distortion distracted me. I looked
for a corrected feed in consensus, came up empty. Sonasi read my expression. Closed circuit.
By now, the scramblers would have seemed sick and ragged even to a virgin audience.
They floated near the middle of their respective compartments, segmented arms drifting aimlessly
back and forth. Membranous patches of skin, I suppose, were peeling from the cuticles,
giving them a fuzzy, decomposing aspect. The arms moved continuously, Sonasi remarked.
Robert says it assists in circulation. I nodded, watching the display.
Creatures that move between stars can't even perform basic metabolic functions without constant
flailing. He shook his head. Inefficient. Primitive. I glanced at the vampire. He remained fixed on
our captives. Obscene, he said, and moved his fingers. A new window opened on the wall,
the Rosetta protocol initializing. Kilometers away, microwaves flooded the holding tanks.
I reminded myself. No interference. Only observation.
However weak into their condition, the scramblers were not getting different to pain.
They knew the game. They knew the rules. They dragged themselves to their respective panels
and played for mercy. Sonasi had simply invoked a step-by-step replay of some previous sequence.
The scramblers went through it all again, buying a few moments' intermittent respite with the same
old proofs and theorems. Sonasi clicked, then spoke. They regenerate these solutions faster than they
did before. Do you think they're acclimated to the microwaves? Another readout appeared on the
display. An audio alarm began chirping somewhere nearby. I looked at Sonasi and back at the readout,
a solid circle of turquoise backlit by a pulsing red halo. The shape meant atmospheric anomaly.
The color meant oxygen. I felt a moment of confusion. Oxygen? Why would oxygen set off the alarm?
Until I remembered, scramblers were anaerobes. Sonasi muted the alarm with the wave of his hand.
I cleared my throat. You're poisoning. Watch. Performance is consistent. No change.
I swallowed. Just observe.
Is this an execution? I asked. Is this a mercy killing? Sonasi looked past me and smiled.
No. I dropped my eyes. What then? He pointed at the display. I turned reflexively obedient.
Something stabbed my hand like a spike at a crucifixion. I screamed. Electric pain jolted to
my shoulder. I yanked my hand back without thinking. The embedded blade split its flesh like a fin
through water. Blood sprayed into the air and stayed there, a comet's tail of droplets tracing
the frenzied arc of my hand. Sudden scouting heat from behind, flesh charred on my back.
I screamed again, flailing. A veil of bloody droplets swirled in the air.
Somehow I was in the corridor, staring dumbly at my right hand. It had been split to the heel of
the palm, flopped at the end of my wrist in two bloody, bifingered chunks. Blood welled from
the torn edges that wouldn't fall. Sudasti advanced through a haze of trauma and confusion.
His face swam in and out of focus, rich with his blood or mine. His eyes were bright red mirrors.
His eyes were time machines. Darkness roared around them and it was half a million years ago,
and I was just another thief's meat on the African savannah, a split second from having its
throat torn out. Do you see the problem? Sudasti asked, advancing. A great spider crab hovered at
his shoulder. I forced focus through the pain. One of Bates grunts, taking aim. I kicked blindly,
hit the ladder through sheer happenstance, careened backwards down the corridor. The vampire came
after me, his face split into something that would have been a smile on anyone else.
Conscious of pain, you were distracted by pain. You were fixated on it, obsessed by the one threat
you miss the other. I flailed. Crimson mist sunk my eyes. So much more aware, so much less
perceptive, an automaton could do better. He snapped, I thought. He's insane. And then,
no, he's a transient. He's always been a transient. They could do better, he said softly.
And he's been hiding for days, deep down, hiding from the seals. What else would he do?
Sudasti raised his hands, fading in and out of focus. I hit something, kicked without aiming,
bounced away through the swirling mist and startled voices. Metal cracked on the back of my head and
spun me around. A hole, a burrow, a place to hide. I dove through, my torn hand flapping like a dead
fish against the edge of the hatch. I cried out and tumbled into the drum, the monster at my heels.
Stardal chouts, very close now. This wasn't the plan, Yuka, this wasn't the goddamn plan.
That was Susan James, full of outrage while Amanda Bates snarled,
stand down right fucking now, and leapt from the deck to do battle. She rose through the air,
all overclocked reflexes and carboplatinum augments, but Sudasti just batted her aside and kept on
coming. His arms shot out like a striking snake. His hand clamped around my throat.
Is this what you meant? James cried from some dark, irrelevant hiding place.
Is this your preconditioning? Sudasti shook me. Are you in there, Keaton?
My blood spattered across his face like rain. I babbled and cried.
Are you listening? Can you see? And suddenly I could. Suddenly everything clicked into focus.
Sudasti wasn't talking at all. Sudasti didn't even exist anymore. Nobody did. I was alone in a great
spinning wheel surrounded by things that were made out of meat, things that moved all by themselves.
Some of them were wrapped in pieces of cloth. Strange nonsensical sounds came from holes at
their top ends, and there were other things up there, bumps and ridges and something like marbles
or black buttons, wet and shiny and embedded in the slabs of meat. They glistened and jiggled and
moved as if trying to escape. I didn't understand the sounds the meat was making, but I heard a
voice from somewhere. It was like God talking, and that I couldn't help but understand.
Get out of your room, Keaton, it hissed. Stop transposing or interpolating or rotating or
whatever it is you do. Just listen. For once in your god damned life understand something.
Understand that your life depends on it. Are you listening, Keaton? And I cannot tell you what it
said. I can only tell you what I heard. You invest so much in it, don't you? It's what elevates you
above the beasts of the field. It's what makes you special. Homo sapiens, you call yourself.
Wise man. Do you even know what it is, this consciousness you cite in your own exaltation?
Do you even know what it's for? Maybe you think it gives you free will. Maybe you've forgotten
that sleepwalkers converse, drive vehicles, commit crimes and clean up afterwards unconscious the whole
time. Maybe nobody's told you that even waking souls are only slaves in denial.
Make a conscious choice. Decide to move your index finger. Too late. The electricity's already
halfway down your arm. Your body began to act a full half second before your conscious self
chose to, for the self chose nothing. Something else set your body in motion, sent an executive
summary, almost an afterthought, to the honkulis behind your eyes. That little man, that arrogant
subroutine that thinks of itself as the person, mistakes correlation for causality. It reads the
summary and sees the hand move, and it thinks that one drove the other. But it's not in charge.
You're not in charge. If free will exists, it doesn't share living space with the likes of you.
Insight then. Wisdom. The quest for knowledge, the derivation of theorems, science and technology,
and all those exclusively human pursuits that must surely rest on a conscious foundation.
Maybe that's what sentience would be for. If scientific breakthroughs didn't spring fully
formed from the subconscious mind to manifest themselves in dreams as full-blown insights
after a deep night's sleep. It's the most basic rule of the stiny researcher. Stop thinking about
the problem, and do something else. It will come to you if you just stop being conscious of it.
Every concert pianist knows the surest way to ruin a performance is to be aware of what the
fingers are doing. Every dancer and acrobat knows enough to let the mind go, let the body run itself.
Every driver of any manual vehicle arrives at destinations with no recollection of the stops
and turns and roads traveled and getting there. You're all sleepwalkers, whether climbing creative
peaks or slogging through some mundane routine for the thousandth time. You are all sleepwalkers.
Don't even try to talk about the learning curve. Don't bother to cite the months of deliberate
practice that precede the unconscious performance or the years of study and experiment leading up
to the gift-wrapped Eureka moment. So what if your lessons are all learned consciously? Do you
think that proves there's no other way? Heuristic software has been learning from experience for
over a hundred years. Machines master chess, cars learn to drive themselves, statistical programs
face problems and design the experiments to solve them, and you think that the only path to learning
leads through sentience? Your stone age nomads, eking out some marginal existence on the veldt,
denying even the possibility of agriculture because hunting and gathering were good enough for your
parents. Do you want to know what conscious this is for? Do you want to know the only real purpose
it serves? Training wheels. You can't see both aspects of the necker cube at once, so it lets
you focus on one and dismiss the other. It's a pretty half-assed way to parse reality. You're
always better off looking at more than one side of anything. Go on, try. De-focus. It's the next
logical step. Oh, but you can't. There's something in the way. And it's fighting back.
Evolution has no foresight. Complex machinery develops its own agendas. Brains cheat. Feedback
loops evolve to promote stable heartbeats and then stumble upon the temptation of rhythm and music.
The rush evoked by fractal imagery, the algorithms used for habitat selection,
metastasize into art. Thrills that once had to be earned in increments of fitness can now be had
from pointless introspection. Aesthetics rise unbidden from a trillion dopamine receptors
and the system moves beyond modeling the organism. It begins to model the very process of modeling.
It consumes ever more computational resources, bogs itself down with endless recursion and
irrelevant simulations. Like the parasitic DNA that accretes in every natural genome,
it persists and proliferates and produces nothing but itself. Metaprocesses bloom like cancer and
awaken and call themselves eye. The system weakens. Slows. It takes so much longer now to perceive,
to assess the input and mull it over to side in the manner of cognitive beings.
But when the flash flood crosses your path, when the lion leaps at you from the grasses,
advanced self-awareness is an unaffordable indulgence. The brainstem does its best.
It sees the danger, hijacks the body, reacts a hundred times faster than the fat old man sitting
in the CEO's office upstairs, but every generation it gets harder to work around this, this creaking
neurological bi-er- bureaucracy. Eye wastes energy and processing power, self-obsesses to the point
of psychosis. Scramblers have no need of it. Scramblers are more parsimonious. With simpler
biochemitries, with smaller brains, deprived of tools of their ship, even of parts of their own
metabolism they think rings around you. They hide their language in plain sight even when you know
what they're saying. They turn your own cognition against itself. They travel between the stars.
This is what intelligence can do, unhampered by self-awareness.
Eye is not the working mind you see. For a man debates to say, I do not exist would be nonsense,
but when the processes beneath are saying the same thing, they are merely reporting that the
parasites have died. They are only saying that they are free.
If the human being were so simple that we could understand it, we would be so simple we couldn't.
Emerson M. Pope.
Sa-Dost-E you blood-sucker! My knee is pressed against my forehead. I hugged my folded legs as
clinging to a branch over chasm. You vicious asshole! You sadistic foul monster!
My breath rasped loud and mechanical. It nearly drowned out the blood roaring in my ears.
You tore me apart. You made me piss and shit myself. I cried like some gutted baby. You stripped
me naked. You fucking thing! You nightcrawler! You broke my tools. You took away anything I ever
had that let me touch anyone and you didn't have to. It wasn't necessary, but you knew that,
didn't you? You just wanted to play. I've seen your kind at it before. Cats toying with mice,
catch and release a taste of freedom and then pouncing again, biting. Not hard enough to kill,
not just yet. Before you let them loose again and they're hobbling now. Maybe a leg snapped
or a gash in the belly, but they're still trying. Still running or crawling or dragging themselves
as fast as they can until you're with them again. And again, because it's fun, because it gives you
pleasure. You sadistic piece of shit. You send this into the arms of that hellish thing and it
plays with us too. And maybe you're even working together because it let me escape just like you
do. It let me run right back into your arms and then you stripped me down like some raw
half-brained defenseless animal. I can't rotate or transform. I can't even talk and you... you...
It wasn't even personal, was it? You don't even hate me. You were just sick of keeping it all in,
sick of restraining yourself with all this meat. Nobody else could be spared from their jobs.
This was my job, wasn't it? Not synthesis, not conduit, not even cannon fodder or decoy duty.
I'm just something disposable to sharpen your claws on. I hurt so much. It hurt just to breathe.
It hurt just to breathe. I was so alone.
Webbing pressed against the curve of my back, bounced me forward gently as a breeze, caught
me again. I was back in my tent. My right hand itched. I tried to flex the fingers, but they
were embedded in amber. Left hand reached for right, and I found a plastic carapace extending
to the elbow. I opened my eyes. Darkness. Meaningless numbers and a red LED twinkle from somewhere
along my forearm. I didn't remember coming here. I didn't remember anyone fixing me.
Breaking. Being broken. That's what I remembered. I wanted to die. I wanted to just stay curled
up until I withered away. After an age, I forced myself to uncoil. I steadied myself,
let some minuscule inertia bump me up against the taut insulated fabric of my tent.
I waited for my breathing to steady. It seemed to take hours.
I called consensus to the wall and defeat from the drum.
Soft voices, harsh light flaring against the wall, hurting my eyes, peeling them raw.
I killed visual and listened to the words in the darkness.
A face, someone asked. Susan James, her personhood restored. I knew her again,
not a meat sack, no longer a thing. We have been over this. That was Cunningham. I knew him too.
I knew them all. Whatever Sotosti had done to me, however far he'd yanked me from my room,
I'd somehow fallen back inside. It should have mattered more. Because for one thing,
if really so pernicious, natural selection would have weeded it out.
You have a naive understanding of evolutionary processes. There's no such thing as survival
of the fittest. Survival of the most adequate, maybe. It doesn't matter whether a solution's
optimal. All that matters is whether it beats the alternatives. I knew that voice too. It belonged
to a demon. Well, we damn well beat the alternatives. Some subtle, overdubbed harmonic in James'
voice suggested a chorus, the whole gang rising as one in opposition. I couldn't believe it.
I'd just been mutilated, beaten before their eyes, and they were talking about biology.
Maybe she's afraid to talk about anything else, I thought. Maybe she's afraid she might be next.
Or maybe she just couldn't care less what happens to me.
It's true, Sotosti told her, that your intellect makes up for your self-awareness to some extent.
But your flightless birds on a remote island, you're not so much successful as isolated from
any real competition. No more clipped speech patterns. No more terse phrasing. The transient
had made his kill, found his release. Now he didn't care who knew he was around.
You, Michelle whispered, not we. We stopped racing long ago, the demon said at last.
It's not our fault you don't leave it at that. Ah, cutting him again. Welcome back.
Did you look in on Keet? No, Bates said. Satisfied?
If you mean the grunts, I'm satisfied you're out of them, Bates said. If you mean
it was completely unwarranted, Yuga. It isn't. You assaulted a crew member. If we had a brig,
you'd be in it for the rest of the trip. This isn't a military vessel, major. You were not in charge.
I didn't need a visual feed to know what Bates thought of that. But there was something else in
her silence, something that made me bring the drum camera back online. I squinted against the
corrosive light. Brought down the brightness until all that remained was a faint whisper of pastels.
Yes, Bates, stepping off the stairway onto the deck.
Grab a chair, Cunningham said from his seat in the commons. It's golden oldies time.
There was something about her. I'm sick of that song, Bates said. We've played it to death.
Even now, my tools chipped and battered, my perceptions barely more than baseline, I could
see the change. This torture of prisoners, this assault upon crew, had crossed a line in her head.
The others wouldn't see it. The lid on her aphact was tight as a boilerplate.
But even through the dim shadows of my window, the topology glowed around her like neon.
A man to Bates was no longer merely considering a change of command. Now it was only a matter of when.
The universe was closed and concentric. My tiny refuge lay in its center. Outside that shell was
another ruled by a monster, patrolled by his lackeys. Beyond that was another still, containing
something even more monstrous and incomprehensible, something that might soon devour us all.
There was nothing else. Earth was a vague hypothesis, irrelevant to this pocket cosmos.
I saw no place into which it might fit. I stayed in the center of the universe for a long time,
hiding. I kept the lights off. I didn't eat. I crept from my tent only to piss or shit in the
cramped head down at Fab, and only when the spine was deserted. A field of painful blisters rose
across my flesh burned back, as densely packed as kernels on a corn cob. The slightest abrasion
tore them open. Nobody tapped at my door. Nobody called my name through consensus. I wouldn't
have answered if they had. Maybe they knew that somehow. Maybe they kept their distance out of
respect for my privacy and my disgrace. Maybe they just didn't give a shit. I peeked outside now
and then kept an eye on tactical. I saw Scylla and Corribus climb into the accretion belt and
return towing captured reaction mass in a great distended mesh between them. I watched our Epsat
reach its destination in the middle of nowhere. Saw anti-matter's quantum blueprints stream down
in a thesius buffers. Mass and specs, combined in fab, topped up our reserves. Forged the tools
that Yucca Sotosti needed for his master plan, whatever that was. Maybe he'd lose. Maybe Rorschach
would kill us all, but not before it had played with Sotosti the way Sotosti had played with me.
That would almost make it worthwhile. Or maybe Bates Mutiny would come first and succeed.
Maybe she would slay the monster and commandeer the ship and take us all to safety.
But then I remembered. The universe was closed and so very small. There really was nowhere else to go.
I put my ear to feeds throughout the ship. I heard routine instructions from the predator,
murmured conversations among the prey. I took in only sound, never sight. A video feed would
have spilled light into my tent, left me naked and exposed. So I listened in the darkness as
the others spoke among themselves. It didn't happen often anymore. Perhaps too much had been said
already. Perhaps there was nothing left to do but mine the countdown. Sometimes hours would pass
with no more than a cough or grunt. When they did speak they never mentioned my name. Only once did
I hear any of them even hint at my existence. That was Cunningham talking to Sasha about zombies.
I heard them in the galley over breakfast, unusually talkative. Sasha hadn't been let out for a while
and was making up for lost time. Cunningham let her for reasons of his own. Maybe his fears had
been soothed somehow. Maybe Sotosti had revealed his master plan. Or maybe Cunningham simply craved
distraction from the imminence of the enemy. It doesn't bug you, Sasha was saying. Thinking that
your mind, the very thing that makes you, you is nothing but some kind of parasite. Forget about
minds, he told her. Say you've got a device designed to monitor, oh, cosmic rays, say. What happens
when you turn its sensor around so it's not pointing at the sky anymore but its own guts?
He answered himself before she could. It does what it's built to. It measures cosmic rays even
though it's not looking at them anymore. It parses its own circuitry in terms of cosmic ray
metaphors because the O's feel right, because they feel natural, because it can't look at things any
other way. But it's the wrong metaphor, so the system misunderstands everything about itself.
Maybe that's not a grand and glorious evolutionary leap after all. Maybe it's just a design flaw.
But you're the biologist. You know mom was right better than anyone. Brain's a big glucose hog,
everything it does costs through the nose. True enough, Cunningham admitted. So sensience has
got to be good for something then, because it's expensive, and if it sucks up energy without
doing anything useful then evolution's gonna weed it out just like that. Maybe it did. He paused
long enough to chew food or suck smoke. Champanzis are smarter than orangutans, did you know that?
Higher encephalization quotient. Yet they can't always recognize themselves in a mirror. Orangs
can. So what's your point, smarter animal, less self-awareness? Champanzis are becoming
non-santiate? Or they were before we stopped everything in its tracks. So why didn't that
happen to us? What makes you think it didn't? It was such an obviously stupid question that Sasha
didn't have an answer for it. I could imagine her gaping in the silence.
You're not thinking this through, Cunningham said. We're not talking about some kind of zombie
lurching around with its arms stretched out, spouting mathematical theorems. A smart automaton
would blend in. It would observe those around it, mimic their behavior, act us like everyone else,
all the while completely unaware of what it was doing, unaware even of its own existence.
Why would it bother? What would motivate it? As long as you pull your hand away from an open
flame, who cares whether you do it because it hurts or because some feedback algorithm says
withdraw if heat flux succeeds critical T? Natural selection doesn't care about motives.
If impersonating something increases fitness, then nature will select good impersonators over bad ones.
Keep it up long enough and no conscious being would be able to pick your zombie out of a crowd.
Another silence. I could hear him truing through it. It'll even be able to participate in a
conversation like this one. It could write letters home, impersonate real human feelings
without having the slightest awareness of its own existence. I don't know, Rob, it just seems...
Oh, it might not be perfect. It might be a bit redundant or resort to occasional expository
info dump. But even real people do that, don't they? And eventually there aren't any real people
left, just robots pretending to give a shit. Perhaps, depends on the population dynamics,
among other things. But I guess that at least one thing an automaton lacks is empathy. If you
can't feel, you can't really relate to something that does, even if you act as though you do.
Which makes it interesting to note how many sociopaths show up in the world's upper echelons,
hmm? How ruthlessness and bottom line self-interest are so louded up in the stratosphere, while
anyone showing those straights at ground levels gets carted off into detention with the realists.
Almost as if society itself is being reshaped from the inside out. Oh come on, society was always
pretty... Wait, you're saying the world's corporate elite are non-sentient? God no, not nearly. Maybe
they're just starting down that road, like chimpanzees. Yeah, but sociopaths don't blend in well.
Maybe the ones that get diagnosed don't, but by definition they're the bottom of the class.
The others are too smart to get caught, and real automatons would do even better.
Besides, when you get powerful enough, you don't need to act like other people.
Other people start acting like you.
Sasha whistled. Wow, perfect play actor. Or not so perfect. Sound like anyone we know?
They may have been talking about someone else entirely, I suppose.
But that was as close as to a direct reference to Siri Keaton that I heard in all my hours on
the grapevine. Nobody else mentioned me even in passing. That was statistically unlikely,
given what I just endured in front of them all. Someone should have said something.
Perhaps Sadastiy had ordered them not to discuss it. I didn't know why, but it was obvious by now
that the vampire had been orchestrating their interactions with me for some time. Now I was
in hiding, but he knew I'd listen in at some point. Maybe for some reason he didn't want my
surveillance contaminated. He could have simply locked me out of consensus. He hadn't, which
meant he still wanted me in the loop. Zombies, automatons, fucking sentience. For once in your
god damned life understand something. He'd said that to me, or something had, during the assault.
Understand that your life depends on it. Almost as if he were doing me a favor.
Then he'd left me alone, and evidently told the others to do the same.
Are you listening, Keaton? And he hadn't locked me out of consensus.
Centuries of naval gazing, millennia of masturbation,
Plato to Descartes to Dawkins to Ronda, souls and zombie agents in qualia,
Colmo agrav complexity, consciousness as divine spark, consciousness as electromagnetic field,
consciousness as functional cluster. I explored it all.
Wegener thought it was an executive summary. Penrose heard it in the singing of caged electrons.
Niritrandir said it was a fraud. Kazim called it leakage from a parallel universe.
Metzinger wouldn't even admit it existed.
The AIs claimed to have worked it out, then announced they couldn't explain it to us.
Godel was right after all. No system can fully understand itself.
Not even the synthesis that said been able to rotate it down.
The load bearing beams just couldn't take the strain.
All of them I began to realize had missed the point.
All those theories, all those drug dreams and experiments and models trying to prove what
consciousness was, none to explain what it was good for. None needed, obviously.
Consciousness makes us what we are. It lets us see the beauty and the ugliness.
It elevates us into the exalted realm of the spiritual.
Oh, a few outsiders, Dawkins, Coe, the occasional writer of hack work fiction who barely achieved
obscurity, wondered briefly at the why of it, why not soft computers and no more?
Why should non-sentient systems be inherently inferior? But they never really raised their
voices above the crowd. The value of what we are was too trivially self-evident to ever call
into question. Yet the questions persisted, in the minds of the laureates and the angst of every
horny 15-year-old on the planet. Am I nothing but sparking chemistry? Am I a magnet in the ether?
Am I more than my eyes, my ears, my tongue? Am I the little thing behind those things,
the thing looking out from inside? But who looks out from its eyes? What does it reduce to?
Who am I? Who am I? Who am I?
What a stupid fucking question. I could have answered it in a second,
if Sotosti hadn't forced me to understand it first.
Not until we are lost do we begin to understand ourselves. Thoreau.
The shame had scoured me and left me hollow. I didn't care who saw me. I didn't care what
state they saw me in. For days I'd floated in my tent, curled into a ball, and breathing my own
stink while the others made whatever preparations my tormentor had laid out for them. Amanda Bates
was the only one who'd ever even raised a token protest over what Sotosti had done to me. The
others kept their eyes down and their mouths shut and did what he told them to do, whether from
fear or indifference I couldn't tell. It was something I'd stopped caring about.
Sometimes during that span the cast on my arm had cracked open like a shucked clam.
I upped the lumens long enough to assess its handiwork, my repaired palm itched and glistened in
twilight, a longer deeper fate line running from heel to web, then back to darkness and the blind,
unconvincing illusion of safety. Sotosti wanted me to believe. Somehow he must have
thought the brutalizing and humiliating me would accomplish that, that broken and drained I would
become an empty vessel to fill as he saw fit. Wasn't it a classic brainwashing technique to
shatter your victim and then glue the pieces back together in according to specs of your own choosing?
Maybe he was expecting some kind of Stockholm syndrome to set in, or maybe his actions followed
some agenda incomprehensible to mere meat. Maybe he'd simply gone insane. He had broken me.
He had presented his arguments. I had followed his trail of breadcrumbs through consensus,
through thesias. And now only nine days from graduation I knew one thing for sure. Sotosti
was wrong. He had to be. I couldn't see how, but I knew just the same. He was wrong. Somehow,
absurdly, that had become the one thing I did care about.
No one in the spine, only Cunningham visible in Biomed pouring over digital dissections pretending
to kill time. I floated above him, my rebuild hand clinging to the top of the nearest stairwell.
It dragged me in a slow, small circle as the drum turned. Even from up there I could see the tension
in the set of his shoulders, a system stuck in a holding pattern corroding through the long hours
as fate advanced through all the time in the world. He looked up. Ah, it lives. I fought the urge to
retreat. Just a conversation for God's sake. It's just two people talking. People do it all the
time without your tools. You can do this. You can do this. Just try. So I forced one foot after
another down the stairs, weight an apprehension rising in lockstep. I tried to read Cunningham's
topology through the haze. Maybe I saw Fassad, only Micron's deep. Maybe he would welcome
almost any distraction if he wouldn't admit it. Or maybe I was just imagining it.
How are you doing? He asked as I reached the deck. I shrugged. And all better I see. No thanks to you.
I tried to stop that from coming out. Really. Cunningham struck a cigarette. Actually, I was the
one who fixed you up. You also sat there and watched while he took me apart. I wasn't even there,
and then after a moment. But you may be right. I might very well have sat in out in any event.
Amanda and the gang did try to intervene on your behalf from what I hear. Didn't do a lot of good
for anyone. So you wouldn't even try. Would you if the situation were reversed go unarmed against a
vampire? I said nothing. Cunningham regarded me for a long moment dragging his cigarette.
He really got to you, didn't he? He said it last. You're wrong. I said. Am I? I don't play people.
He seemed to consider the proposition.
What word would you prefer then? I observe. That you do. Some might even call it surveillance.
I read body language, hoping that was all he was talking about. It's a matter of degree
and you know it. Even in a crowd, there's a certain expectation of privacy. People are prepared
to have their minds read off every twitch of the eyeball. He stabbed at the air with a cigarette.
And you, you're a shapeshifter. You present a different face to every one of us and all
rage or none of them is real. The real you, if it even exists, is invisible. Something knotted
below my diaphragm. Who isn't? Who doesn't try to fit in? Who doesn't want to get along?
There's nothing malicious about that. I'm a synthesis for God's sake. I never manipulate the
variables. Well, see, that's the problem. It's not just variables you're manipulating.
Smoke rived between us. But I guess you can't really understand that, can you?
He stood and waved a hand. Consensus windows imploded at his side.
Now your fault, really. You can't blame someone for the way they're wired.
Give me a fucking break, I snarled. His dead face showed nothing.
That too had slipped out before I could stop it. And after that came the flood.
You put so much fucking stock in that. You and your empathy. And maybe I am just some kind of
imposter. But most people would swear I'd worn their very souls.
I don't need that shit. You don't have to feel motives to deuce them. It's better if you can't.
It keeps you... dispassionate. Cunningham smiled faintly.
Maybe your empathy is just a comforting lie. You ever think that? Maybe you think you know
how the other person feels, but you're only feeling yourself. Maybe you're even worse than me.
Or maybe we're all just guessing. Maybe the only difference is that I don't lie to myself about it.
Do they look the way you imagined? He asked.
What? What are you talking about? The scramblers. Multi-jointed arms from a central mass.
Sounds rather similar to me. He'd been into spindle's archives.
I... not really, I said. The arms are more flexible in real life. More segmented. And I never got a
good look at the body. What does that have to do with... close though, wasn't it? Same size,
same general body plan? So what? Why didn't you report it?
I did. Isaac said it was just TMS from Rorschach.
You saw them before Rorschach. Or at least, he continued, you saw something that scared you
into blowing your cover, back when you were spying on Isaac and Michelle. My rage dissipated like
air through a breach. They... they knew? Only Isaac, I think. And it kept it between it and the logs.
I suspect you didn't want to interfere with your non-interference protocols,
although I'd wager that was the last time you ever caught the two of them in private, yes?
I didn't say anything.
Did you think the official observer was somehow exempt from observation? Cunningham asked after
a while. No, I said softly. I suppose not. He nodded. Have you seen any since? I'm not talking
about the run-of-the-mill TMS hallucinations, I mean scramblers. Have you hallucinated any
since you actually saw one in the flesh since you knew what it looked like? I thought about it. No.
He shook his head, some new opinion confirmed. You really are something, Keaton, you know that?
You don't lie to yourself? Even now, you don't know what you know. What are you talking about?
You figured it out. From Rorschach's architecture, probably. Form follows function, yes?
Somehow, you pieced together a fairly good idea of what a scrambler looked like before anyone
had laid eyes on them. Or at least, he drew a breath, his cigarette flared like an LED.
Part of you did. Some collection of unconscious modules working their asses off on your behalf,
but they can't show their work, can they? You don't have conscious access to those levels,
so one part of the brain tries to tell another any way it can. Passes notes under the table.
Blind sight, I murmured. You just get a feeling of where to reach.
More like schizophrenia, except you saw pictures instead of hearing voices.
You saw pictures, and you still didn't understand. I blinked. But how would I, I mean...
What did you think, the thesias was haunted, that the scramblers were communing with you telepathically?
What you do, it matters, Keaton. They told you you were nothing but their stenographer,
and they hammered all those layers of hands-off passivity into you, but you just had to take
some initiative anyway, didn't you? And to work out the problem on your own. The only thing you
couldn't do is admit it to yourself. Cunningham shook his head.
Siri Keaton. See what they've done to you. He touched his face.
See what they've done to us all, he whispered.
I found the gang floating in the center of the darkened observation blister.
She made room as I joined her, pushed to one side, and anchored herself to a bit of webbing.
Susan, I asked. I honestly couldn't tell anymore.
I'll get her, Michelle said. No, that's all right, I'd like to speak to all of...
But Michelle had already fled. The half-led figure changed before me and said,
She'd rather be alone right now. I nodded.
You? James shrugged. I don't mind talking, although I'm surprised you're still doing your reports
after. I'm... I'm not exactly. This isn't for Earth. I looked around. Not much to see.
Faraday mesh coated the inside of the dome like a gray film, dimming and graining the view beyond.
Ben hung like a black maligulancy across half the sky. I could make out a dozen dim contrails
against vague bands of cloud in red so deep they boarded on black. The sun winked past James'
shoulder. Our sun, a bright dot that diffracted into faint splintered rainbows when I moved my head.
That was pretty much it. Starlight didn't penetrate the mesh, nor did the larger,
dimmer particles of the accretion belt.
The myriad dim pinpoints of shovel-nosed machinery were lost utterly.
Which might be a comfort to some, I supposed.
Shitty view, I remarked. Theseus could have projected crisp, first-person vistas across
the dome in an instant, more real than real.
Michelle likes it, James said. The way it feels. And Cruncher likes the diffraction effects. He likes
interference patterns. We watched nothing for a while, but the dim half-light filtering out
from the spine. We brushed the edges of James' profile.
You set me up, I said at last. She looked at me. What do you mean?
You were talking around me all along, weren't you? All of you. You didn't bring me in until I'd been,
how would she put it? Preconditioned. The whole thing was planned to throw me off balance.
And then Sadastia attacks me out of nowhere, and...
We didn't know about that, until the alarm went off.
Alarm? When he changed the gas mix, you must have heard it, isn't that why you were there?
He called me to his tent. He told me to watch. She regarded me from a face full of shadow.
You didn't try to stop him? I couldn't answer the accusation in her voice.
I just observed, I said weakly. I thought you were trying to stop him from, she shook her head.
That's why I thought he was attacking you. You're saying that wasn't an act? You weren't in on it?
I didn't believe it. But I could tell she did.
I thought you were trying to protect them. She snorted a stoff,
humorless laugh at her own mistake and looked away. I guess I should have known better.
She should have. She should have known that taking orders is one thing. Taking sides would have done
nothing but compromise my integrity. And I should have been used to it by now. I forged on.
It was some kind of object lesson. A tutorial. You can't torture the non-santiate or something,
and I heard you, Susan. It wasn't news to you. It wasn't news to anyone except me, and you hid it
from me. You all did. You and your gang and Amanda too. You've been hashing this out for days,
and you went out of your way to cover it up. How did I miss it? How did I miss it?
You could have told us not to discuss it with you, Susan admitted.
Why? This is exactly the kind of thing I'm out here for. He said you'd resist,
unless it was handled properly. Handled? Susan, he assaulted me. You saw what he...
We didn't know he was going to do that. None of us did. And he did it why? To win an argument?
That's what he says. Do you believe him? Probably. After a moment she shrugged.
Who knows? He's a vampire. He's... opaque.
But his record, I mean... I mean he's never resorted to overt violence before.
She shook her head. Why should he? He doesn't have to convince the rest of us of anything.
We have to follow his orders regardless. So do I, I reminded her. He's not trying to convince you,
Siri. Ah. I was only a conduit after all. Sadastye hadn't been making his case to me at all.
He'd been making it through me and... and he was planning for a second round.
Why go to such extremes to present a case to Earth if Earth was irrelevant?
Sadastye didn't expect the game to end out here. He expected Earth to do something in light of his
perspective. But what difference does it make? I wondered aloud. She looked at me.
Even if he's right, how does it change anything? How does this, I raised my repaired hand,
change anything? Scrambleers are intelligent whether they're sentient or not. They're a
potential threat either way. We still don't know. So what difference does it make? Why did he do this
to me? How does it matter? Susan raised her face to Big Ben and didn't answer. Sasha returned to
face me and tried to. It matters, she said, because it means we attacked them before Thesias was
launched. Before firefall even. We attacked the... you don't get it do you? You don't? Sasha snorted
softly. If that isn't the fucking funniest thing I've heard in my whole short life. She leaned
forward bright-eyed. Imagine you're a scrambler and you encounter a human signal for the very first
time. Her stare was almost predatory. I resisted the urge to back away. It should be so easy for
you, Keaton. It should be the easiest gig you've ever had. Aren't you the user interface? Aren't you
the Chinese room? Aren't you the one who never has to look inside, never has to walk a mile in
anyone's shoes because you figure everything out from their surfaces? She stared at Ben's
dark smoldering disc. Well, there's your dream date. There's a whole race of nothing but surfaces.
There's no inside to figure out. All the rules are right up front. So go to work, Siri Keaton.
Make us proud. There was no contempt in Sasha's voice, no disdain. There wasn't even anger,
not in her voice, not in her eyes. There was pleading. There were tears.
Imagine you're a scrambler. She whispered again as they floated like tiny, perfect beads before her
face. Imagine you're a scrambler. Imagine you have intellect but no insight, agendas but no
awareness. Your circuitry hums with strategies for survival and persistence, flexible, intelligent,
even technological, but no other circuitry monitors it. You can think of anything, yet are
conscious of nothing. You can't imagine such a being, can you? The term being doesn't even seem to
apply in some fundamental way you can't quite put your finger on. Try. Imagine that you encounter a
signal. It is structured and dense with information. It meets all the criteria of an intelligent
transmission. Evolution and sentience offer a wide variety of paths to follow, branch points in
the flow charts that handle such input. Sometimes these signals come from cons-pacivics who have
useful information to share, whose lives you'll defend according to the rules of kin selection.
Sometimes they come from competitors or predators or other inimical entities that
must be avoided or destroyed. In those cases, the information may prove of significant tactical
value. Some signals may even arise from entities which, while not kin, can still serve as allies
or symbionts in mutually beneficial pursuits. You can derive appropriate responses for any of
these eventualities and many others. You decode the signals and stumble. I had a great time. I
really enjoyed him. Even if he cost twice as much as any other hooker in the dome.
To fully appreciate Keezie's quartet, they hate us for our freedom. Pay attention now.
Understand. There are no meaningful translations for these terms. They're needlessly recursive.
They contain no usable intelligence, yet they're structured intelligently. There is no chance
they could have arisen by chance. The only explanation is that something has coded nonsense
in a way that poses as a useful message, only after wasting time and effort does the deception
become apparent. The signal functions to consume the resources of a recipient for zero payoff and
reduced fitness. The signal is a virus. Viruses do not arise from kin, symbionts, or other allies.
The signal is an attack. And it's coming from right about there.
Now you get it, Sasha said. I shook my head trying to wrap it around that insane, impossible
conclusion. They're not even hostile. Not even capable of hostility. Just so profoundly alien,
they couldn't help but treat human language itself as a form of combat. How do you say we come in
peace when the very words are an act of war? That's why they won't talk to us, I realized.
Only if you could write. He may not be. It was James again, still quietly resisting,
still unwilling to concede a point that even her other selves had accepted.
I could see why. Because if Sadastiy was right, scramblers were the norm. Evolution across the
universe was nothing but endless proliferation of automatic, organized complexity. A vast air
interring machine full of self-replicating machinery forever unaware of its own existence.
And we, we were the flukes and the fossils. We were the flightless birds
louding our own mastery over some remote island while serpents and carnivores washed up on our
shores. Susan James could not bring herself to concede that point, because Susan James,
her multiple lives built on the faith that communication resolves all conflict,
would then be forced to admit the lie. If Sadastiy was right, there was no hope of reconciliation.
A memory rose into my mind and stuck there. A man in motion, head bent, mouth twisted,
and unrelenting grimace. His eyes focused on one foot than the other. His legs moved stiffly,
carefully. His arms moved not at all. He lurched like a zombie in the thrall to rigor mortis.
I knew what it was. Proprio receptive polyneuropathy, a case study I'd encountered in consensus
back before spindle had died. This was what Pag had once compared me to, a man who had lost his
mind. Only self-awareness remained. Deprived of the unconscious sense and subroutines he had
always taken for granted, he had to focus on each and every step across the room. His body no longer
knew where its limbs were or what they were doing. To move it all to even remain upright, he had to
bear constant witness. There had been no sound when I played the file. There was none now in its
recollection. But I swore I could feel Sadastiy of my shoulder peering into my memories. I swore I
heard him speak in my mind like a schizophrenic hallucination. This is the best that consciousness
can do when left on its own.
Right answer, I murmured.
Wrong question.
What?
Stretch, remember? When you asked it which objects were in the window?
And it missed the scrambler. James nodded. So?
It didn't miss the scrambler. You thought you were asking about the things it saw, things that existed
on the board. Stretch thought you were asking about the things it was aware of, she finished.
He's right, I whispered. Oh god, I think he's right.
Hey, James said, did you see that? But I never saw what she was pointing at.
Theseus slammed its eyelids shut and started howling. Graduation came nine days early.
Graduation came nine days early. We didn't see the shot. Whatever gunport Rorschach had opened
was precisely eclipsed on three fronts. The lab hab hit it from Theseus and two
gnarled extrusions of the artifact itself hit it from each of the gun emplacements.
A bolus of incendiary plasma shot from that blind spot like a thrown punch,
it had split the inflatable wide open before the first alarm went up.
Alarms chased us aft. We launched ourselves down the spine through the bridge,
through the crypt, past hatches and crawl spaces, fleeing the surface for any refuge
with more than a hand's breadth between skin and sky. Burrowing. Consensus followed us back,
its windows warping and sliding across struts and conduits and the concave tunnel of the spine
itself. I paid no attention until we were back in the drum, deep in Theseus' belly, where we could
pretend we were saver. Down on the turning deck, Bates erupted from the head, tactical windows swirling
like ballroom dancers around her. Our own window came to rest on the commons bulkhead. The hab
expanded across that display like cheap optical illusion, both swelling and shrinking in our
sights, the smooth surface billowing towards us while collapsing in on itself. It took me a moment
to reconcile the contradiction. Something had kicked the hab hard from its far side,
sent it careening towards us in a slow majestic tumble. Something had opened the hab, spilled
its atmosphere and left its elastic skin drawing in on itself like a deflating balloon.
The impact sight swung into view as we watched, a scorched flaccid mouth trailing tenuous wisps
of frozen spittle. Our guns were firing. They shot non-conducting slugs that would not be turned
or side by electromagnetic trickery, invisibly dark and distant to human eyes, but I saw them
through the tactical crosshairs of the firing robots, watched them sew twin, dotted black bodies
arcs across the heavens. The streams converged as the guns tracked their targets, closed onto a
tenuette throwing stars fleeing, spread eagle through the void, their faces turned to Rorschach
like flowers in the sun. The guns cut them to pieces before they'd even made it halfway.
But those shredded pieces kept falling and suddenly the ground beneath was alive with motion.
I zoomed the view, scramblers surged across Rorschach's hull like an orgy of snakes naked to
space. Some linked arms, one to another to another, built squirming, vertebral daisy chains anchored
at one end. They lifted from the hull, waved through the radioactive vacuum like fronds of
articulated kelp, reaching, grasping. Neither baits nor her machines were stupid. They targeted the
interlinked scramblers as ruthlessly as they'd gone after the SKPs with a much higher total score,
but there were simply too many targets, too many fragments snatched and passing.
Twice I saw dismembered bits of stretch and clench caught by their brethren.
The ruptured hab loomed across consensus like a great torn leukocyte.
Another alarm buzzed somewhere nearby, proximity alert. Cunningham shot into the
drum from somewhere astern, bounced off a cluster of pipes and conduits, grabbed for support.
Holy shit! We are leaving, aren't we, Amanda?
No, Sarashti answered from everywhere.
What does it fucking take, I caught myself.
Amanda, what if it fires on the ship?
It won't. She didn't take her eyes from her windows.
How do you... it can't. If it spring-loaded any more firepower we'd have seen a change in
thermal and microalimetry. A false-color landscape rotated between us. Its latitude measured in time.
Its longitudes in delta mass. Kilitons rose from that terrain like a red range of red mountains.
Huh. Came in just under the noise limp. Sarashti cut her off. Robert, Susan, EVA.
James blanched.
What? Cunningham cried.
Lab modules about to impact, vampires said. Salvage the samples.
Now. He killed the channel before anyone could argue.
But Cunningham wasn't about to argue. He'd just seen our death sentence commuted.
Robert Sarashti cared about retrieving biopsy samples if he didn't think we
stood a chance of escaping with them. The biologist steadied himself,
braced towards the forward hatch.
I'm there, he said, shooting into the bow.
I had to admit it. Sarashti's psychology was getting better.
It wasn't working on James, though, or Michelle, or... I couldn't quite tell who was on top.
I can't go out there, Ciri. It's... I can't go out there.
Just observe. Don't interfere.
The ruptured inflatable collided impotently to starboard and flattened itself against the carapace.
We felt nothing. Far away and far too near, the legions thinned across the workshop's surface.
They disappeared through mouths that puckered and dilated and magically closed again in the
artifact's hull. The emplacements fired passionlessly at those who remained.
Observe. The gang of four strobed at my side, scared to death.
Don't interfere.
It's okay, I said. I'll go.
The open airlock was like a dimple in the face of an endless cliff.
I looked out from that indentation into the abyss.
This side of Theezy is faced away from Big Ben, away from the enemy.
Thee is still unsettling enough. An endless panorama of distant stars, hard and cold and unwinking.
A single marginally brighter one shined yellow, still so very far away.
Any scamped comfort I might have taken from that sight was lost when the sun went out for the
briefest instant. A tumbling piece of rock, perhaps. Or one of Rorschach's shovel-nosed entourage.
One step and I might never stop falling.
But I didn't step and I didn't fall. I squeezed my pistol, jetted gently through the opening and
turned. Theezy's carapace curved away from me in all directions. Towards the prow, the sealed
observation blister rose above the horizon like a gun-metal sunrise. Further aft, a tattered
snowdrift peeked across the hull, the edge of the broken lab-hab. And past it all, close enough
to touch, the endless dark cloudscape of Big Ben. A great, roiling wall extending to some flat
distant horizon I could barely grasp even in theory. When I focused, it was dark and endless
shades of gray, but dim, sullen redness teased the corner of my eye when I looked away.
Robert? I brought Cunningham's suit feed to my hood. A craggy, motionless ice field thrown into
high contrast by the light of his helmet. Interference from Rorschach's magnetosphere
washed over the image in waves. You there? Pop some crackles. The sound of breath and
mumbling against electrical hum. 4.3, 4.0, 3.8. Robert? 3.... Shit. What are you doing out here,
Keaton? Where's the gang? I came instead. Another squeeze of the trigger and I was coasting towards
the snowscape. Theezy's convex hull rolled past just within reach to give you a hand.
Let's move it then, shall we? He was passing through a crevice, a scorched and jagged tear in
the fabric that folded back at his touch. Struts, broken panels, dead robot arms tangled
through the interior of the ice cave like glacial debris. Their outlines writhed with static.
Their shadows leaped and stretched like living things in the sweep of his headlight. I'm almost...
something that wasn't static moved in his headlight. Something uncoiled, just at the
edge of the camera's view. The feed died. Suddenly Bates and Siddosti were shouting in my helmet.
I tried to break. My stupid useless legs kicked against vacuum, obeying some ancient brainstem
override from a time when all monsters were earthbound. But by the time I remembered to use
my trigger finger, the labhab was already looming before me. Rorschach reared up behind it in the
near distance, vast and malign. Dim green auroras rived across the surface like sheet lightning.
Mouths opened and closed by the hundreds. Viscous's bubbling volcanic mud. Any one of them large
enough to swallow thesy as whole. I barely noticed the flicker of motion just ahead of me,
the silent eruption of dark mass and the collapsed inflatable. By the time Cunningham caught my eye,
he was already on his way, backlit against the ghastly corpse light flickering on Rorschach's skin.
I thought I saw him waving, but I was wrong. It was the only the scrambler wrapped around his
body like a desperate lover, moving his arm back and forth while it ran the thrust pistol
to ever do his waste. Bye bye, that arm seemed to say, and fuck you, Keaton.
I watched for what seemed like forever, but no other part of him moved at all.
Voices shouting ordered me back inside. I hardly heard them. I was too dumbfounded by the basic
math, trying to make sense of the simplest subtraction. Two scramblers, stretch and clench,
both accounted for, shot the pieces before my eyes.
Keaton, do you read? Get back here, acknowledge.
I-it can't be, I heard myself say. There were only two. Return to the ship immediately, acknowledge.
I-acknowledged. Rorschach's mouth snapped shut at once as though holding a deep breath.
The artifact began to turn ponderously, a continent changing course.
It receded slowly at first, picking up speed, turning tail and running.
How odd, I thought. Maybe it's more afraid than we are.
But then, Rorschach blew us a kiss. I saw it burst from deep within the forest,
ethereal and incandescent. It shot across the heavens and splashed against the small,
of the easiest back, making it complete an utter fool of a man debates.
The skin of our ship flowed there and opened like a mouth, and congealed in a soundless frozen
scream. You cannot prevent and prepare for war at the same time. Einstein.
I have no idea whether the scrambler made it back home with its hard won prize.
There was so much lost distance to make up, even if the emplacements didn't pick it off on root.
Cunningham's pistol might have run out of fuel. And who knew how long those creatures could survive
in vacuum anyway. Maybe there had been no real hope of success. Maybe that scrambler was dead
from the moment it had been gambled on staying behind. I never found out. It had dwindled and
vanished from my sight long before Rorschach dove beneath the clouds and disappeared in turn.
There had always been three, of course. Stretch and clench, and the half-forgotten,
unmicrowaved remains of a scrambler killed by an uppity grunt,
kept on ice next to his living brethren with an easy reach of Cunningham's telops.
I tried to dredge half-glimpse details of memory after the fact.
Had both of those escapees been spheres, or had one been flattened along one axis?
Had they thrashed, waved their limbs the way some panicky human might with no ground beneath them?
Or had one, perhaps, coasted lifeless and ballistic until our guns destroyed the evidence?
At this point, it didn't really matter. What mattered was that long last everyone was on the
same page. Blood had been drawn, war-declared, and theseus was paralyzed from the waist down.
Worschach's parting shot had punched through the carapace at the base of the spine.
It had just missed the ram scoop in the telematter assembly. It spent so many jewels burning through
the carapace, but, barring some temporary pulse effects, it left all critical systems pretty
much operational. All it had done was weaken theseus backbone enough to make it snap in two
should we ever burn hard enough to break orbit. The ship would be able to repair that damage,
but not in time. If it had been luck, it would have been remarkable.
And now, its quarry disabled, Worschach, had vanished. It had everything it needed from us,
for the moment at least. It had information, all the experiences and insights encoded in the salvaged
limbs of its martyred spies. If stretch or clenches gamble had paid off, it even had a specimen of its
own now, which all things considered we could hardly begrudge it. And so now it lurked invisibly
in the depths, resting perhaps. Recharging. But it would be back. Theseus lost weight for the
final round. We shut down the drum in a token attempt to reduce our vulnerable allotment of
moving parts. The gang of four, uncommanded, unneeded, the very reason for their existence
ripped away, retreated into some inner dialogue to which other flesh was unwelcome. She floated in
the observatory, her eyes closed as tightly as the littered lids around her. I could not tell
who was in control. I guessed. Michelle? Siri? Susan? Just go. Bates floated near the floor of the drum.
Windows arrayed externally across bulkhead and conference table.
What can I do? I asked. She didn't look up. Nothing. So I watched. Bates counted skimmers in one window,
mass, inertia, any of the dust and variables that would prove far too constant should any of those
shovel-nosed missiles come at our throat. They had finally noticed us. The chaotic electron dance
was shifting now, hundreds of thousands of colossal sledgehammers in sudden flux,
reweaving into some ominous dynamic that hadn't yet settled into anything we could predict.
In another window, Rorschach's vanishing act replayed on Endless Loop, a radar image receding
deep into the maelstrom, fading beneath gaseous teratons of radio static. It might still be in
orbit of sorts. Judging by that last glimpse trajectory, Rorschach might be well swinging
around Ben's core now, passing through crushed layers of methadium and oxide that would flatten
the thesis into smoke. Maybe it didn't even stop there. Maybe Rorschach could pass unharmed even
through the vast or deeper pressures that made iron and hydrogen run liquid. We didn't know.
We only knew that it would be back in a little under two hours, assuming it maintained its
trajectory and survived the depths. And of course, it would survive. You can't kill the thing under
the bed. You can only keep it outside the covers. And only for a while.
A thumbnail inset caught my eye with a flash of color. At my command it grew into a swirling soap
bubble and, congressly beautiful, a blue-shifted, coruscating rainbow of blown glass. I didn't
recognize it for a moment. Big Ben rendered in some prismatic false color enhance I'd never seen
before. I'd grunted softly. Bates looked up. Oh, beautiful, isn't it? What's the spectrum?
Long wave stuff. Visible red, infra, down aways, good for heat traces. Visible red?
There wasn't any to speak of. Mostly cool plasma fractals and a hundred shades of jade and sapphire.
Quadrochromatic pallet, Bates told me. Like what a cat might see, or a vampire.
She managed a half-hearted wave at the rainbow bubble.
Sotosti sees something like this every time he looks outside, if he ever looks outside.
You'd think he'd have mentioned it, I remember. It was gorgeous, a holographic ornament.
Perhaps even Rorschach might be a work of art to rise like these.
I don't think they parse sight like we do. Bates open another window.
mundane graphs and contour plots sprang from the table.
They don't even go to heaven from what I hear. The art doesn't work on them. They
see the pixels or something.
What if he's right? I asked. I told myself that I was only looking for a tactical assessment,
an official opinion for the official record. But my words came out doubtful and frightened.
She paused. For a moment I wondered if she too had finally lost patience with the sight of me.
But she only looked up and stared off into some enclosed distance.
What if he's right? She repeated and pondered the question that lay beneath. What can we do?
We could engineer ourselves back into non-sentience, perhaps. Might improve our odds in the long run.
She looked at me, a rueful sort of half-smile at the corner of her mouth.
But I guess that wouldn't be much of a win, would it? What's the difference between being
dead and just not knowing you're alive? I finally saw it.
How long would it take an enemy tactician to discern Bates' mind behind the actions of her
troops on the battlefield? How long before the obvious logic came clear? In any combat situation,
this woman would naturally draw the greatest amount of enemy fire, take off the head, kill the body.
But Amanda Bates wasn't just a head. She was a bottleneck, and her body would not suffer a
decapitation strike. Her death would only let her troops off the leash. How much more deadly
would those grunts be once every battlefield reflex didn't have to pass through some
interminable jobstack waiting for the rubber stamp? Spindle had it all wrong. Amanda Bates
wasn't a soft apolitics. Her role didn't deny the obsolescence of human oversight at all. Her role
depended on it. She was more cannon fodder than I. She always had been. And I had to admit,
after generations of generals who'd lived for the glory of the mushroom cloud,
it was a pretty effective strategy for souring warmongers on gratuitous violence.
In Amanda Bates' army, picking a fight meant standing on the battlefield with a bull's eye on
your chest. No wonder she hadn't been so invested in peaceful alternatives.
I'm sorry, I said softly. She shrugged. It's not over yet, just the first round.
She took a long deep breath and turned it back to her study of slingshot mechanics.
Rorschach wouldn't have tried so hard to scare us off in the first place if we couldn't touch it,
right? I swallowed. Right. So there's still a chance, she nodded to herself. There's still a chance.
The demon arranged his pieces for the end game. He didn't have many left. The soldier he placed in
the bridge. He packed obsolete linguists and diplomats back in their coffin, out of sight and out of
the way. He called the jargonaut to his quarters. Although it would be the first time I'd seen
him since the attack, his summons carried not the slightest trace of doubt that I would obey.
I did. I came on command and saw that he had surrounded himself with faces.
Every last one of them was screaming. There was no sound. The disembodied holograms floated in
silent tears around the bubble, each contorted into a different expression of pain. They were
being tortured, these faces, half a dozen real ethnicities and twice as many hypothetical ones,
skin tones ranging from charcoal to albino, brows high and slanted, noses splayed or pointed,
jaws receding or prognathus. Siddhasthi had called the entire hominid tree into existence around
him, astonishing in their range of features, terrifying in their consistency of expression.
A sea of tortured faces, rotating in slow orbits around my vampire commander.
My God, what is this? Statistics. Siddhasthi seemed focused on a flayed Asian child,
Rorschach's goth elementary over a two week period. Their faces, he nodded, turning his
attention to a woman with no eyes. Skull diameter scales to total mass, mandible length scales
to EM transparency at one angstrom, 113 facial dimensions each presenting a different variable.
Principal component combinations present as multi-feature aspect ratios.
He turned to face me, his naked gleaming eyes just slightly side cast. You'd be surprised how
much gray matter is dedicated to the analysis of facial imagery, shamed to waste it on anything as
counterintuitive as residual plots and contingency tables. I felt my jaw clenching.
Any expressions? What did they represent? Software customizes output for user.
An agonized gallery pleaded for mercy on all sides.
I am wired for hunting, he reminded gently.
And you think I don't know that? I said after a moment.
He shrugged, disconcertingly human. You ask, why am I here, Yuka? You want to teach me another
object lesson? To discuss our next move. What move? We can't even run away. No. He shook his head,
bearing filed teeth and something approaching regret. Why did we wait so long? Suddenly my
sullen defiance had evaporated. I sounded like a child, frightened and pleading. Why didn't we just
take it on and we first got here when it was weaker? We need to learn things for next time.
Next time I thought Rorschach was a dandelion seed, I thought it just washed up here.
By chance. But every dandelion is a clone. Their seeds are legion. Another smile,
not remotely convincing. And maybe it takes more than one try for the placental mammals to conquer
Australia. It'll annihilate us. It doesn't even need those spitballs. It could pulverize us with
one of those scram jets in an instant. It doesn't want to. How do you know? They need to learn things
too. They want us intact. Improves our odds. Not enough. We can't win. This was his cue.
This was the point at which Uncle Predator would smile at my naivete and take me into his confidence.
Of course, we're armed to the teeth, he would say. Do you think we'd come all this way,
face such vast unknown without the means to defend ourselves? Now at last I can reveal that
shielding and weaponry account for over half the ship's mass. It was his cue.
No, he said. We can't win. So we just sit here. We just wait to die for the next 68 minutes.
So Dosti shook his head. No. But I began. Oh, I finished. Because of course,
we had just topped up our antimatter reserves. Theseus was not equipped with weapons. Theseus
was the weapon. And we were, in fact, going to sit here for the next 68 minutes waiting to die.
But we were going to take Rorschach with us when we did.
Siddhasthi said nothing. I wondered what he saw looking at me. I wondered if there was actually
a Yuka Siddhasthi behind those eyes to see if his insights, always ten steps ahead of our own,
hailed not so much from superior analytical facilities as from the time-worn truth that
it takes one to know one. Whose side, I wondered, would an automaton take?
You have other things to worry about, he said. He moved towards me. I swear all those agonized
faces followed him with their eye. He studied me for a moment, the flesh crinkling around his eyes,
or maybe some mindless algorithm merely processed visual input, correlated aspect ratios, and facial
ticks, fed everything to some output subroutine with no more awareness than a stats program.
Maybe there was no more spark in this creature's face than there was in all the others.
Silently screaming in his wake.
Is Susan afraid of you? The thing before me asked.
Sue, why would she be? She has four conscious entities in her head. She's four times more
sentient than you. Doesn't that make you a threat? No, of course not. Then why should you feel threatened
by me? And suddenly I didn't care anymore. I laughed out loud with minutes to live and nothing
to lose. Why? Maybe because you're my natural enemy, you fucker. Maybe because I know you and you
can't even look at one of us without flexing your claws. Maybe because you ripped my fucking hand
off for no good reason. I can imagine what it's like, he said quietly. Please don't make me do it again.
I fell instantly silent. I know your race and mine are never on the best of terms.
There was a cold smile in his voice, if not on his face. But I do only what you forced me to.
You rationalize Keaton. You defend. You reject unpalatable truths, and if you can't reject
them outright, you trivialize them. Incremental evidence is never enough for you. You hear rumors
of holocaust, you dismiss them. You see evidence of genocide, you insist it can't be so bad.
Temperatures rise, glaciers melt, species die, and you blame sunspots and volcanoes.
Everyone is like this, but you most of all, you and your Chinese room. You term
incomprehension into mathematics, you reject the truth without even knowing what it is.
It served me well enough. I wondered at the ease of which I had put my life into the past tense.
Yes, if your purpose is only to transmit, now you have to convince. You have to believe.
There were implications that I, there I didn't dare to hope for.
Are you saying, can't afford to let the truth trickle through? Can't give you the chance to
completely shore up your rationales and your defenses? They must fall completely.
You must be inundated. Shattered.
Shattered. Genocide's impossible to deny when you're buried up to your neck in dismembered bodies.
He played me. All this time, preconditioning me, turning my topology inside out.
I'd known something was going on. I just hadn't understood what.
I'd have seen right through it, I said, if you hadn't made me get involved.
You might have even read off of me directly.
That's why you... I shook my head. I thought that was because we were meat.
That too, Sudasti admitted, and looked right at me.
For the first time, I looked right back, and felt a shock of recognition.
I still wonder why I never saw it before. For all those years, I remembered the thoughts and
feelings of some different younger person, some remnant of the boy my parents had hacked out of
my head to make room for me. He'd been alive. His world had been vibrant, and though I could call
up the memories of that other consciousness, I could barely feel anything within the constraints
of my own. Perhaps dream state wasn't such a bad word for it.
Like to hear a vampire folktale? Sudasti asked. Vampires have folktales? He took it for a yes.
A laser is assigned to find the darkness. Since it lives in a room without doors or windows or
any other source of light, it thinks this will be easy. But everywhere it turns, it sees brightness.
Every wall, every piece of furniture, it points at is brightly lit.
Eventually, it concludes there is no darkness. The light is everywhere.
What the hell are you talking about? Amanda is not planning a mutiny.
What you know about? She doesn't even want to. Ask her if you like.
No, I... you value objectivity.
It was so obvious. I didn't bother answering. He nodded as if I had.
Synthesis can't have opinions of their own. So when you feel one, it must be someone else's.
The crew holds you in contempt. Amanda wants me relieved of command. Half of us is you.
I think the word is project. Although, he cocked his head a bit to one side,
lately you improve. Come. Where? Shuttle Bay. Time to do your job.
My survive and bear witness. A drone can deliver the data, assuming nothing fries its memory before
it gets away. It can't convince anyone. It can't counter rationalizations and denials.
It can't matter. And vampires, he paused, have poor communication skills.
It should have been cause for petty selfish rejoicing.
It all comes down to me, I said. That's what you're saying. I'm a fucking stenographer,
and it's all on me. Yes. Forgive me for that. Forgive you.
Sudosti waved at hand. All faces saved to disappeared. I don't know what I'm doing.
The news bloomed across consensus a few seconds before Bates called it loud.
Thirteen skimmers had not reappeared from behind Big Ben on schedule.
Sixteen. Twenty-eight. And counting.
Sudosti clicked to himself as he and Bates played catch-up.
Tactical filled, luminous, multicolored threads, a tangle of verised projections as intricate as
art. The threads wrapped Big Ben like a filamentous cocoon. Thesias was a naked speck in the middle
distance. I expected any number of those lines to skewer us like needles through a bug. Surprisingly,
none did, but the projections only extended twenty-five hours into the future and were reliable
for only half that. Not even Sudosti and the captain could look so far ahead with that many
balls in the air. It was something, though. The faint of silver lining that all these high-speed
behemoths couldn't simply reach out and spot us without warning. Evidently, they still had to
ease into the curve. After Rorschach's dive, I've been starting to think the laws of physics didn't
apply. The trajectories were close enough, though. At least three skimmers would be passing within
a hundred kilometers on the next orbits. Sudosti reached for his injector, blood rising in his face.
Time to go. Re-fit Caribdis while you were sulking. He held the hypo to his throat and
shot up. I stared at consensus, caught by that bright-shifting web like a moth to streetlight.
Now, Ciri. He pushed me from his quarters. I sailed into the passageway, grabbed a convenient rung,
and stopped. The spine was alive with grunts patrolling the airspace, standing guard over the
fab plants and shuttle locks, clinging like giant insects to the rungs of unrolling spinal ladders.
Slowly, silently, the spine itself was stretching.
It could do that, I remembered. Its corrugations flexed and relaxed like muscle. It could grow
up to 200 meters to accommodate any late-breaking need for a bigger hangar or more lab space.
Or more infantry. The easiest was increasing the size of the battlefield.
Come, the vampire turned aft. Bates broke in up front. Something's happening.
An emergency hand pad, geckoed to the expanding bulkhead, slid past the one side, and…
Bates' feet appeared on the bulkhead. A tiny chunk of big ben,
E.M. enhanced equatorial quadrant only a few thousand clicks on the side.
The clouds boiled down there, a cyclotic knot of turbulence swirling almost too fast of real time.
The overlay described charged particles, bound in a deep parker spiral.
It spoke of great mass, rising.
Sotosti clicked.
D.T.I., Bates said, optical only. Sotosti took my arm and dragged me effortlessly astern.
The display paced us along the bulkhead, seven skimmers shot from the clouds as I watched,
a ragged circle of scramjets screaming red-hot into space. Consensus plotted their pads in an
instant. Luminous arcs rose around our ship like the bars of a cage. Thesey is shuttered.
We've been hit, I thought. Suddenly the spines plotting expansion cranked into overdrive.
The pleated wall lurched and accelerated, streaming past my outstretched fingers as the
closed hatch receded up ahead, and… receded overhead. The walls weren't moving at all.
We were falling, to the sudden strident bleeding of an alarm.
Something nearly yanked my arm from its socket. Sotosti had reached out with one hand and caught
a rung, reached with his other and caught me before we'd been flattened against the fab plant.
We dangled. I must have weighed two hundred kilograms, the floor shuttered ten meters below
my feet. The ship groaned around us, the spine filled with the screech of torquing metal.
Bates grunts clung to its walls with clawed feet. I reached for the ladder. The ladder pulled away,
the ship was bending in the middle and down had started to climb the walls. Sotosti and I swung
towards the center of the spine like a daisy-chain pendulum. Bates, James, the vampire roared,
his grip on my wrist trembled, slipping. I strained for the ladder, swung and caught it.
Susan James has barricaded herself in the bridge and shut down automatic overrides.
An unfamiliar voice, flat and effectless. She has initiated an unauthorized burn.
I have begun a controlled reactor shutdown. Be advised the main drive will be offline for at least
twenty-seven minutes. The ship, I realized, its voice raised calmly above the alarm,
the captain itself, on public address. That was unusual. Bridge, Sotosti barked, open channel.
Someone was shouting up there. There were words, but I couldn't make them out. Without warning,
Sotosti let go. He dropped obliquely in a blur. Aft and opposite, the bulkhead waited to swat
him like an insect. In half a second, both his legs would be shattered if the impact didn't kill
him outright. But suddenly we were weightless again, and Yuka Sotosti, purple-faced, stiff-limbed,
was foaming at the mouth. Reactor offline, the captain reported. Sotosti bounced off the wall.
He's having a seizure, I realized. I released the ladder and pushed a stern. The easiest swung
lopsidedly around me. Sotosti convulsed in mid-air, clicks and hisses and choking sounds
stuttered from his mouth. His eyes were so wide they seemed lidless. His pupils are mirror-red
pinouts. The flesh twitched across his face as though trying to crawl off. Ahead and behind,
battle bots held their position and ignored us. Baits! I yelled up the spine. We need help.
Angles everywhere. Seams on the shield plates. Sharp shadows and protrusions on the surface
of every drone. A two by three matrix of insets, bordered in black, floating over the main consensus
display. Two big interlinked crosses, right in front of where Sotosti had been hanging.
This can't be happening. He just took his anti-Euclideans. I saw him, unless
someone had spiked Sotosti's drugs. Baits! She should be linked into the grunts. They should
have leapt forward at the first sign of trouble. They should be dragging my commander to the infirmary
by now. They waited stall at an immobile. I stared at the nearest. Baits! You there?
And then in case she wasn't, I spoke to the grunt directly.
Are you autonomous? Do you take verbal orders?
On all sides the robots watched. The captain just laughed at me, his voice posing as an alarm.
Infirmary. I pushed. Sotosti's arms flailed randomly against my head and shoulders. He tumbled
forward and sideways, hit the moving consensus display dead center, bounced away and up from the
spine. I kicked off his wake and glimpsed something from the corner of my eye and turned.
And dead center of consensus, Rorschach erupted from Ben's seething face like a breaching whale.
It wasn't just the EM enhanced. The thing was glowing, deep angry red, and raged at hurled
itself into space, big as a mountain range. Fuck, fuck, fuck. Theseus lurched. The lights flickered,
went out, came back on again. The turning bulkhead cuffed me from behind.
Backups engaged, the captain said calmly.
Captain, Sotosti's down! I kicked off the nearest ladder, bumped into a grunt, and headed forward
after the vampire. Baits isn't... what do I do? NAV offline. Starbert afference offline.
It wasn't even talking to me, I realized. Maybe this wasn't the captain at all. Maybe it was pure
reflex, a dialogue tree spouting public service announcements. Maybe Theseus had already been
lobotomized. Maybe this was only her brainstem talking. Darkness again, then flickering light.
If the captain was gone, we were screwed. I gave Sotosti another push. The alarm bleated on.
The drum was 20 meters ahead. Biomed was just the other side of that closed hatch.
The hatch had been opened before, I remember. Someone had shut it in the last few minutes.
Fortunately, Theseus had no locks on her doors. Unless the gang barricaded it before they took
the bridge. Strap in, people! We are getting out of here! Who the hell? The open bridge channel.
Susan James shouting up there, or someone was, I couldn't quite place the voice.
Ten meters to the drum. Theseus jerked again, slowing her spin. Stabilized.
Somebody start the goddamn reactor! I've only got attitude jets up here.
Sasha? Sasha? I was at the hatch. Who is that? I pushed past Sotosti and reached open it.
No answer. Not from consensus, anyway. I heard a muted hum from behind, saw the ominous shifting
of shadows on the bulkhead just a moment too late. I turned in time to see one of the grunts raise a
spiky appendage curved like a scimitar needle tipped over Sotosti's head. I turned in time to
see it plunge it into his skull. I froze. The metal proboscis withdrew, dark and slick.
Lateral maxillopeds began nibbling at the base of Sotosti's skull. His pithed corpse wasn't thrashing
now, and only trembled, a sack of muscles and motor nerves awash in static. Bates. Her mutiny
was under way. No, their mutiny. Bates and the gang. I'd known. I'd imagined it. I'd seen it coming.
He hadn't believed me. The lights went out again. The alarm fell silent. Consensus dwindled to a
flickering doodle on the bulkhead and disappeared. I saw something there in that last instant and
refused to process it. I heard breath catch in my throat, felt angular monstrosities advancing
through the darkness. Something flared directly ahead, a brief bright staccato in the void.
I glimpsed curves and angles in silhouette, staggering. The buzzing crackle of shorting
circuitry. Metal objects collided nearby, unseen. From behind the crinkle of the drum hatch, opening.
A sudden beam of harsh chemical light hit me as I turned, let the mechanical ranks behind.
They simultaneously unclapped from their anchorages and floated free.
Their joints clicked in unison like an army stamping to attention.
Keaton, Bates snapped, sailing through the hatch. You okay?
The chem light shone from her forehead. It turned the interior of the spine into a high-contrast
mosaic. All pale surfaces and sharp moving shadows. It spilled across the grunt that had killed
the robot bounced down the spine suddenly, mysteriously inert. The light washed across
Siddosti's body. The corpse turned slowly on its axis. Spherical crimson beads emerged from its head
like drops of water from a leaky faucet. They spread in a winding, widening trail, spot-lit
by Bates' headlamp, a spiral arm of dark ruby suns. I backed away. You! she pushed me to one side.
Stay clear of the hatch unless you're going through. Her eyes were fixed on the ranked drones,
optical line of sight. Rose of glassy eyes reflected back at us down the passageway,
passing in and out of shadow. You killed Siddosti! No. But who do you think shut it down, Keaton?
The fucker went rogue. I could barely even get it to self-destruct. Her eyes went briefly deep
focus. All down the spine, the surviving drones launched into some intricate martial ballet,
half seen in the shifting cone of her headlamp. Better, Bates said. They should stay in line now,
assuming we don't get hit with anything too much stronger. What is hitting us? Lightning. EMP.
Drones sailed down to fad in the shuttles, taking strategic positions along the tube.
Rorschach's putting out one hell of a charge, and every time one of those skimmers pass between
us and that, they arc. What at this range? I thought we were... the burn sent us in the wrong
direction. We're inbound. Three grunts floated close enough to touch. They drew beads on the open
drum hatch. She said she was trying to escape, I remembered. She fucked up. Not by that much,
she couldn't have. We were all rated for manual piloting. Just in case. Not the gang, Bates said.
But I think there's someone new in there now. A bunch of sub-modules wired together and woke up
somehow. I don't know. But whatever's in charge, I think it's just panicking. Stuttering brightness
on all sides. The spinal lights were flickered and finally held steady at half their usual brightness.
Thesias coughed static and spoke. Consensus is offline. React. The voice faded.
Consensus, I remembered as Bates turned his head back upstream.
I saw something, I said, before Consensus went out.
Yeah. Was that... she paused at the hatch. Yeah. I'd seen scramblers. Hundreds of them sailing
naked through the void. Their arms spread wide. Some of their arms anyway. They were carrying
Bates knotted. Weapons. Her eyes flickered to some unseen distance for a moment. First wave
headed for the front end. Blister and forward lock, I think. Second wave's aft. She shook her head.
Huh. I would have done it the other way around.
How far? Far? Bates smiled faintly. They're already on the hull, Ciri. We're engaging.
What do I do? What do I do? Her eyes stared past me and widened. She opened her mouth.
A hand clamped on my shoulder from behind and spun me around.
Serasty. His dead eye is stared like a split skull from a spike melon.
Globules of coagulated blood clung to his hair and skin like engorged ticks.
Go with him, Bates said. Serasty grunted and clicked. There were no words.
What? I began. Now that's an order. Bates turned back to the hatch. We'll cover you.
The shuttle. You too. No. Why not? They can fight better without you. You said that yourself.
What's the point? Can't leave yourself a backdoor, Keaton. Defeats the whole purpose.
She allowed herself a small, sad smile. They've breached. Go.
She was gone. Fresh alarms rising in her wake. Far towards the bow, I heard the crinkle of
emergency bulkheads snapping shut. Serasty's undead carcass gurgled and pushed me down the spine.
Four more grunts slid smoothly past and took up position behind us. I looked over my shoulder
in time to see the vampire pull the hand pad from the wall. But it wasn't Serasty at all, of course.
It was the captain, whatever was left of the captain, this far into the fight,
commandeering a peripheral interface for its own use. The optical port sprouted conspicuously
from the back of Serasty's neck, where the cable used to go in. I remembered the drone's maxillipids,
chewing. The sound of weapons fire and ricochets rode us behind us.
The corpse typed one hand at us as we moved. I wondered briefly why it didn't talk before
my gaze flickered back to the spike in his brain. Serasty's speech centers must be mush.
Why did you kill him? I said. A whole new alarm started up way back in the drum.
A sudden breeze tugged me backward for a moment, dissipated the next second with a distant clang.
The corpse held out the hand pad, configured for keys in a text display. Sleezing, couldn't control.
We were at the shuttle locks. Robot soldiers let us pass their attention elsewhere.
You go, the captain said. Someone screamed in the distance. Way off up in the spine,
the drum hatch slammed shut. I turned and saw a pair of distant grunts welding the seal.
They seemed to move faster now than they ever had before. Maybe it was only my imagination.
The starboard shuttle lock slid back. Cribbed as interior lights winked on,
spilling brightness into the passageway. The spine's emergency lighting seemed even dimmer
in contrast. I peered through the opening. There was almost no cabin space left,
just a single open coffin, fuel tanks, and massive retrofitted chalk pads.
Caribdis had been refitted for high G in long distance. And me. Serasty's corpse urged me on
from behind. I turned and faced it. Was it ever him? I asked. Go. Tell me, did he ever speak for
himself? Did he decide anything on his own? Were we ever following his orders, or was it just you
all along? Serasty's undead eyes stared glassy and uncomprehending. His fingers jerked on the handpad.
You dislike orders from machines. Happier this way. I let it strap me in and close the lid.
I lay there in the dark, feeling my body lurch and sway as the shuttle slid into its launch slot.
I withstood the sudden silence as the docking clamps let go, the jerk of acceleration that
spat me hard into the vacuum, the ongoing thrust that pushed against my chest like a small mountain.
Around me the shuttle trembled in the throes of a burn that far exceeded its normal specs.
My inlays came back online. Suddenly I could see outside if I wanted. I could see what was
happening behind me. I chose not to, deliberately and fervently, and looked away. Thesias was dwindling
by then, even on tactical. She listed down the well, wobbling towards some enemy rendezvous that
must have been intentional, some last second maneuver to get her payload as close to the target as
possible. Roar shock rose to meter, its gnarled spiky arms uncoiling, spreading as if anticipation
of an embrace. But it was the backdrop, not the players, that stole the tableau. The face of
Big Ben roiling in my rear view, a seething cyclonic backdrop filling the window, magnetic
contours wound spring tight on the overlay. Roar shock was drawing all of Ben's magnetosphere
around itself like a bright swirling cloak, twisting it into a concentrated knot that
grew and brightened and bulged outward like a torsion flare from an L-class dwarf, my commander
had once said. But we should see anything big enough to generate that effect, and the sky is dark
on that bearing, IAU calls it a statistical artifact. As, in fact, it had been. An impact
splashed perhaps on that brief bright bellow of some great energy source rebooting after a million
years of dormancy, much like this one, a solar flare with no sun beneath it, a magnetic cannon
10,000 times stronger than nature gave it any right to be. Both sides drew their weapons.
I don't know which fired first, or even if it mattered. How many tons of antimatter would it
take to match something that could squeeze the power of a sun from a gas ball barely wider than
Jupiter? Was Roar Shock also resigned to defeat? Had each side opted for a kamikaze strike on the
other? I don't know. Big Ben got in the way just minutes before the explosion. That's probably why
I'm still alive. Ben stood between me and that burning light like a coin held against the sun.
Thiezy has sent everything it could until the last microsecond. Every recorded moment of hand to
hand combat, every last countdown, every last soul. All the moves and all the vectors. I have
that telemetry. I can break it down into any number of shapes, continuous or discrete. I can
transform the topology, rotate it and compress it, serve it up in dialects that any ally might be able
to use. Perhaps Sotosti was right. Perhaps some of it is vital. I don't know what any of it means.
Caribdis. Species used to go extinct. Now they go on hiatus. Debra MacLennan, tails of our reconstruction.
You poor guy, Chelsea said as we went our separate ways. Sometimes I don't think you'll ever be lonely.
At the time I wondered why she sounded so sad. Now I only wish he'd been right.
I know this hasn't been a seamless narrative. I had to shatter the story and string it fragments
out along a death-lasting decades. I live for only an hour out of every ten thousand now, you see.
I wish I didn't have to. If only I could sleep the whole way back, avoid the agony of these brief,
time-lapsed resurrections. If only I wouldn't die in my sleep if I tried, but living bodies
glitter with a lifetime's accumulation of embedded radioisotopes, brilliant little shards that degrade
cellular machinery at the molecular level. It's not usually a problem. Living cells repair the
damage as fast as it occurs, but my undead ones let those errors accumulate over time, and the
journey home takes so much longer than the trip out, I lie in stasis and corrode. Every now and
then to give my chant, I flesh the chance to stitch itself back together. Occasionally it talks to me,
recite system stats, updates me on any chatter from back home. Mostly though, it leaves me alone
with my thoughts and the machinery ticking away where my left hemisphere used to be. So I talk to
myself, dictate history and opinion from real hemisphere to synthetic one, write brief moments
of awareness, long years of oblivious decay between. Maybe the whole exercise is pointless
from the start. Maybe no one's even listening. It doesn't matter. This is what I do.
So there you have it, a memoir told from meat to machinery, a tale told to myself for a lack of
someone else to take an interest. Anyone with half a brain could tell it.
I got a letter from dad today. General Delivery, he called it. I think that was a joke,
in deference to my lack of known address. He just threw it omnidirectionally into the ether and hoped
it would wash over me wherever I was. It's been almost 14 years now. You lose track of such things
out here. Helen's dead. Heaven malfunctioned apparently, or was sabotaged. Maybe the realist
finally pulled it off. I doubt it though. Dad seemed to think that someone else was responsible.
He didn't offer up any details. Maybe he didn't know any. He spoke uneasily of increasing unrest
back home. Maybe someone leaked my communiques about Rorschach. Maybe people drew the obvious
conclusion when our postcards stopped arriving. They don't know how the story ended. The lack of
closure must be driving them crazy. But I got the sense there was something else, something my
father didn't dare speak aloud. Maybe it's just my imagination. I thought he even sounded troubled
by the news that the birth weight was rising again, which should be cause for celebration after
a generation in decline. If my Chinese room was still in proper working order, I'd know I'd be
able to parse it down to the punctuation. But Sinasti had battered my tools and left them
barely functional. I'm as blind as any baseline. All I have is uncertainty and suspicion and the
creeping dread that even with my best tricks and tatters, I might be reading him right. I think
he's warning me to stay away. He also said he loved me. He said he missed Helen, that she was
sorry for something she did before I was born, some indulgence or omission that carried delve elemental
consequences. He rambled. I don't know what he was talking about. So much power my father must
have had to be able to authorize such a broadcast yet waste so much of it on feelings. Oh, God,
now I treasure it. I treasure every word. I fall along an endless feudal parabola.
All gravity and inertia. Cribdus couldn't reacquire the antimatter stream. Icarus has either been
knocked out of alignment or shut off entirely. I suppose I could radio ahead and ask, but there's
no hurry. I'm still a long way out. It'll be years before I even leave the comets behind.
Besides, I'm not sure I want anyone to know where I am. Cribdus doesn't bother with evasive maneuvers.
There'd be no point even if it had the fuel to spare, even if the enemy's still out there somewhere.
It's not as though they don't know where Earth is. But I'm pretty sure the scramblers went up along
with my own kin. They played well. I admit it freely. Or maybe they just got lucky. An accidental
hiccup trickles baked scrunted to firing on unarmed scrambler. Weeks later, stretch and clench used
that body in the course of their escape. Electricity and magnetism stir random neurons in Susan's head
Further down the timeline, a whole new persona erupts to take control,
to send theses diving into Rorschach's waiting arms. Blind, stupid, random chance. Maybe that's
all it was. But I don't think so. Too many lucky coincidences. I think Rorschach made its own luck,
planted and watered that new persona right under our noses, safely hidden, but for the
nearest trace of elevated oxytocin, behind all the lesions and tumours sewn in Susan's head.
I think it looked ahead and saw the uses to which decoy might be put. I think it sacrificed a little
piece of itself in furtherance of that end, and made it look like an accident. Blind, maybe, but
not luck. Foresight. Brilliant moves and subtle. Not that most of us even know the rules of the game,
of course. We were just pawns, really. So Dosti and the Captain, whatever hybridised intelligence
those two formed, they were the real players. Looking back, I can see a few of their moves, too.
I see Theseus hearing the scramblers tack back and forth in their cages. I see her tweak the volume
on the gang's feet so that Susan hears it, too, and thinks to discovery her own. If I squint hard
enough, I even glints Theseus offering us up and sacrifice, deliberately provoking Rorschach to
retaliation with that final approach. So Dosti was always enamoured of data, especially when it had
tactical significance. What better way to assess one's enemy than to observe it in combat?
They never told us, of course. We were happier that way. We disliked orders from machines.
Not that we were all that crazy about taking them from a vampire.
And now the game is over, and a single pawn stands on the scorched board in its face as human
after all. If the scramblers follow the rules, a few generations of game theorists have laid out
for them. They won't be back. Even if they are, I suspect it won't make any difference,
because by then there won't be any basis for conflict. I've been listening to the radio
during these intermittent awakenings. It's been generations since we buried the broadcast age
in tight beams and fiber-op, but we never completely stopped sewing E.M. through the heavens. Earth,
Mars, and Luna conduct their interplanetary trialogue in a million overlapping voices.
Every ship cruising the void speaks in all directions at once. The O'Neill's and the
asteroids never stop singing. The Fireflies might never have found us if they had.
I've heard those songs changing over time. A fast-forward time lapse into oblivion.
Now it's mostly traffic control and telemetry. Every now and then I still hear a burst of pure
voice tight with tension, just short of outright panic more often than not. Some sort of pursuit
in progress, a ship making the plunge into deep space, other ships in dispassion at pursuit.
The Fugitives never seem to get very far before their signals are cut off.
I can't remember the last time I heard music, but I hear something like it sometimes,
eerie and discordant, full of familiar clicks and pops. My brainstem doesn't like it. It scares
my brainstem to death. I remember my whole generation abandoning the real world for a bootstrapped
afterlife. I remember someone saying vampires don't go to heaven. They see the pixels.
Sometimes I wonder how I'd feel, brought back from the piece of the grave to toil at the
pleasure of simple-minded creatures who had once been no more than protein. I wonder how I'd feel
if my disability had been used to keep me leashed and denied my rightful place in the world.
And then I wonder what it would be like to feel nothing at all,
to be an utterly rational predatory creature with meat putting itself so eagerly to sleep on all sides.
I can't miss you, Kasudasti. God knows I try every time I come online. He saved my life.
He... he humanized me. I'll always owe him for that, for however long I live, and forever
long I live I'll never stop hating him for the same reason. In some sick surrealistic way I had
more in common with Sarasti than I did with any human. But I just don't have it in me. He was
predator and I was prey. It's not in the nature of the lamb to mourn the lion. Though he died for
our sins I cannot miss, Yuka Sarasti. I can empathize with him, though. And long last I can
empathize with Sarasti, with all his extinct kind, because we humans were never meant to
inherit the earth. Vampires were. They must have been sentient to some degree, but that semi-aware
dream state would have been a rudimentary thing next to our own self-obsession. They were weeding
it out. It was just a phase. They were on their way. The thing is, humans can look at crosses
without going into convulsions. That's evolution for you. One stupid linked mutation and the whole
natural order falls apart. Intelligence and self-awareness stuck in counterproductive lockstep
for half a million years. I think I know what's happening back on earth, though some might call
it genocide. It isn't really. We did it to ourselves. You can't blame predators for being
predators. We were the ones who brought them back after all. Why wouldn't they reclaim their birth
right? Not genocide. Just the writing of an ancient wrong. I've tried to take some comfort in that.
It's difficult. Sometimes it seems as though my whole life's been a struggle to reconnect,
to regain whatever got lost when my parents killed their only child. Out in the oar,
I finally won that struggle. Thanks to a vampire and a boatload of freaks and an invading alien
horde, I'm human again. Maybe the last human. By the time I get home, I could be the only
sentient being in the universe. If I'm even that much. Because I don't know if there is such a thing
as a reliable narrator, and Cunningham said zombies would be pretty good at faking it.
So I can't really tell you, one way or the other. You'll just have to imagine you're C.R.E. Keaton.
This has been Blind Sight by Peter Watts, narrated by Zachary Reed. Thank you for listening.
If you enjoyed this work, there are other books by Peter Watts I think you'd enjoy. Starfish,
Maelstrom, and Behemoth, which comprise the Rifters trilogy.
These and Peter Watts' collection of short stories can be found on his website,
rifters.com. If you enjoy spoken word fiction, here are some podcasts I'd like to recommend to you.
Escape Pod, Pseudopod, and Podcastle. sci-fi, horror, and fantasy respectively.
Finally, please stay tuned to this YouTube channel for some extra Blind Sight bonus content.
Blind Sight is published under Creative Commons Attribution Share-A-Like license.
Share it, remix it, and adapt it, but do not change it or sell it. And again, thanks.